<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Baptismalogia, or, A treatise concerning baptisms whereto is added a discourse concerning the supper, bread and vvine, called also, communion / by Thomas Lawson.</title>
            <author>Lawson, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 238 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36244</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15620429</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15620429</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104215</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104215)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1151:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Baptismalogia, or, A treatise concerning baptisms whereto is added a discourse concerning the supper, bread and vvine, called also, communion / by Thomas Lawson.</title>
                  <author>Lawson, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 105 [i.e. 108] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677/8.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>P. 9-12 missing in numbering.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Controversial literature --  Quaker authors.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Controversial literature --  Quaker authors.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104215:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104215:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>ΒΑPΤΙΣΜΑΛΟΓΙΑ OR A TREATISE CONCERNING Baptiſms: Whereto is added a DISCOURSE CONCERNING THE Supper, Bread and VVine, Called alſo COMMUNION.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Thomas Lawſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year 167<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104215:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104215:2"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>READER,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN this following Treatiſe is preſented to thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye:
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1.</hi> The Temporary Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> with Water.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2.</hi> The Permanent or Continuing Baptiſm of Chriſt with the Spirit.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3.</hi> The irrepititious Cuſtom of <hi>Rantiſm,</hi> that is, Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Infants.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Herein alſo thou mayſt ſee, that after the Primitive Times, the Fall of the Star from Heaven was manifeſted, Sun and Air (thorow the Smoke of the Bottomleſs Pit, Maman Wiſdom, Heatheniſh Learning, Spoiling Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, School Divinity) was darkned, thorow the ſteaming in of which Chriſt's Baptiſm in and with the Spirit came to be loſt, then Water-Baptiſm and Rantiſm came to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſumed.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> One while baptizing or ſprinkling Old People on their Death-Beds.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Another while baptizing of People ſooner, as when they were capable of being catechiſed.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> After this Baptizing or Sprinkling of Infants.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Some Baptized People after they were Dead, and put the Sacramental Bread (as 'tis called) in their Mouthes.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Hence ſprung in the Cuſtom of Baptizing the Living for the Dead.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Hence aroſe the Cuſtom of Baptizing Children in the Womb, before they were born.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> Some have had the Character of a Croſs made in their Fore-heads with a Burning Iron, which was called Chriſt's Baptiſm with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:104215:3"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> Many, yea, almoſt all, for Ages, were Baptized Naked.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> Many Baptized Themſelves every Year.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And theſe various Unſcriptural Proceedings were and are cryed up by the Obſervers thereof to be of Divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Here alſo thou mayſt read, how that in this Night of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, which hath come upon the Churches profeſſing <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> ſprung up the uſe of Godfathers, Godmothers, Goſſips, Fonts, Exorciſms, Sign of the Croſs, Albs, Salt; all which things, with others, are more or leſs touched in this following Treatiſe.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104215:3"/>
                  <head>ΒΑPΤΙΣΜΑΛΟΓΙΑ Or a TREATISE concerning BAPTISM</head>
                  <p>I Confeſs, I have often been very ſerious concerning the Doctrine of Baptiſms, and have not let any thing ſlip from me, written or ſpoken in Vindication of Baptiſm and Rantiſm, that is, <hi>Dipping</hi> and <hi>Sprinkling,</hi> without ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, ſo to anſwer the Deſires of ſome ſober Perſons, but primarily Divine Requirings, I was induced to ſharpen the Neb of my Pen, and to commit to writing my Belief in reference thereto; and to the end I may the better be underſtood of ſuch as read me, I have reduced the <hi>Contents</hi> of the enſuing Diſcourſe into four Heads or <hi>Aſſertions,</hi> which be as follow.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I.</hi> The <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>John</hi> with Water, and the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the Spirit, were not one, and the ſame, but two, that is to ſay, Diſtinct Baptiſms.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II. John</hi>'s <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> in or with Water, was a Figure, or a Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> in or with the Spirit, ſo thereby fulfilled and ended.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III. Chriſt</hi>'s, <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in or with the Spirit, is the Baptiſm on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to continue in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the End of the World.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IV. Rantiſm,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Sprinkling of Infants,</hi> is a Caſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſidented in the Primitive Times, an irrepetitious Cuſtom ſprung up in the Night of Apoſtacy, after the Revolt from Chriſt, the Captain of the true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> the Fall from the primitive Order.</item>
                  </list>
                  <div n="1" type="assertion">
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104215:4"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The Firſt ASSERTION.</hi> The <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>John</hi> with Water, and the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the Spirit, were not one, but two, that is to ſay, Diſtinct Baptiſms.</head>
                     <p>THE Truth of this is clear and evident to every one, whoſe Eyes are opened by the Influence of the Almighty, and I may produce a Cloud of Witneſſes for the Confirmation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, though indeed many late Writers and Teachers have and do affirm, <hi>That</hi> John's Baptiſm <hi>and</hi> Chriſt's Baptiſm <hi>make but up one Baptiſm; that the Spirit goes along with the Water, making up one Baptiſm; or that the Water thorough the Word of Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath a ſuper-natural Virtue, effectual to the Sanctification, Ablution, that is, Waſhing and Regeneration of Man:</hi> this is an Antichriſtian-Doctrine, to aſcribe ſuch things to viſible elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Water, which are the Effects and Products of the Blood of Chriſt, the Water of Life, <hi>John, Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> make them diſtinct.</p>
                     <p>Now for the determining of this Controverſie, obſerve the Record of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, that is, <hi>John the Dipper;</hi> ſo call'd becauſe he was authorized to Baptize in Water, as alſo to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh him from <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, Mat. 3.11. <hi>I indeed bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize you with Water,</hi> &amp;c. (ſaith John) <hi>but he that comes after me,</hi> (to wit, Chriſt) <hi>he ſhall baptize you with the Holy Ghost and with Fire.</hi> Conſider this, <hi>John</hi> makes them diſtinct Baptiſms, as if he ſhould have ſaid, I am to baptize with Water only, that is my Work, my Office, thereto I am commiſſioned from Heaven, even to waſh the Body, the Filth of the outward man; but when Chriſt is come, he ſhall have another Work, of a more Heavenly Nature; what is that? he ſhall baptize you with the Holy Spirit and with Fire: he doth not ſay, he will baptize you with Water, neither doth he ſay, he will baptize you with Water and with the Spirit, but he will baptize you with the Holy Spirit only; ſo that <hi>John</hi> abſolutely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104215:4"/>concludes them to be diſtinct Baptiſms, he with Water, Chriſt with the Spirit.</p>
                     <p>See alſo <hi>Mark</hi> 1.8. where the very ſame Record is born of <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, and Chriſt's Baptiſm, <hi>I indeed have baptized you with Water, but he ſhall baptize you with the Holy Spirit.</hi> Mark this, [I have] but [he ſhall] this denotes the two Baptiſms.</p>
                     <p>See alſo <hi>Luke</hi> the third, there was a great muſing about <hi>John,</hi> as whether he was the Chriſt or no; people entertained high Thoughts of him, as being born in an extraordinary manner, and living in the Wilderneſs, his Apparel and Diet being unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, as a Raiment of Camels Hair, Locuſts and Wild Honey being his Food, his Baptiſm was new and ſtrange; theſe things being conſidered, occaſioned much Reaſoning among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as, whether he was the <hi>Meſſias</hi> or no: now for a removal and ſcouring away of ſuch Reaſonings, <hi>John</hi> tells them plainly and evidently, he was not the Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.15, 16. ſaying, <hi>I indeed baptize you with Water;</hi> my Work is to waſh your Bodies with the viſible Element of Water, that's my Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but (ſaith he) <hi>Amightier then I comes after me, and he ſhall baptize you with the Holy Spirit.</hi> Here <hi>John</hi> holds out his Miniſtration of Water-Baptiſm, and the Miniſtration of Chriſt's Spiritual Baptiſm to be diſtinct.</p>
                     <p>See alſo Joh. 1.33. where the very ſame Record is born, <hi>I with Water,</hi> which reaches to the Ablution of the outward Man; <hi>Chriſt with the Spirit,</hi> which is effectual to the Ablution or Waſhing of the inward Man.</p>
                     <p>The four Evangeliſts, who were <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that is, <hi>divinely inſpired,</hi> are unanimous in the diſtinction of the Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> and of the Baptiſm of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Further, In <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. the Apoſtle ſpeaking of ſome of the initial Points of the true Religion, makes meniton of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Baptiſms, not Baptiſm, but Baptiſms, in the plural number, and that theſe are <hi>John</hi>'s with Water, and <hi>Christ</hi>'s with the Spirit, may be proved by a fruitful and plentiful Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of Teſtimonies.</p>
                     <p>So they err greatly who affirm that the Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> and the Baptiſm of <hi>Chriſt</hi> made up but One Baptiſm, it being ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104215:5"/>evident in Scripture, that they were diſtinct, which may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus appear:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Firſt,</hi> They were diſtinct in <hi>Name;</hi> for <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm ſtill kept its Name, yea, when the Apoſtles uſed it, it was ſtill cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Baptiſm of John;</hi> why ſo? becauſe it was required of him, his Office and Work by divine Inſtitution, Joh. 1.33. yea, after Chriſt's Baptiſm with the Spirit came in, <hi>John</hi>'s Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm with Water ſtill retained its Name, as being diſtinct from it, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.24, 25.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Secondly,</hi> They were diſtinct in <hi>Manifestation;</hi> that is, Chriſt's Baptiſm was to follow <hi>John</hi>'s, and did not go along with it, at the ſame time, as men now would jumble them together, ſaying, The Spirit goes along with the Water, and both make up but One Baptiſm, after the Reſurrection of Chriſt, before his aſcending; though <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm had been uſed ſeveral years, yet Chriſt told them, that what <hi>John</hi> ſpoke concerning him, of his baptizing with the Holy Spirit, was not fulfilled, but ſhortly to be fulfilled, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Christ being aſſembled with the Apostles, commanded them not to depart from</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>but to wait for the Promiſe of the Father, which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>you have heard of me; for</hi> John <hi>truly baptized with Water, but ye ſhall be baptized with the Holy Spirie not many dayes hence,</hi> which was fulfilled at the day of Pentecoſt: So that Chriſt's Baptiſm did not accompany <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, to make up one entire Baptiſm; for it followed it ſeveral years after it: ſo that the Effuſion of the Holy Spirit is Chriſt's Baptiſm, the great Bleſſing of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-dayes, of the Evangelical Diſpenſation, which qualified and doth qualifie to be the Lord's True and Living Witneſſes.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thirdly,</hi> John's Baptiſm and Chriſt's were diſtinct; foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as thoſe that <hi>John</hi> baptized had need of the Baptiſm of Chriſt: Now, if <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm had been one and the ſame with Chriſt's, that only had been ſufficient; but <hi>John</hi>'s baptizing of them with Water left them in need of the Baptiſm of Chriſt: <hi>John</hi> ſaid unto Chriſt (who came from <hi>Galilet</hi> to <hi>Jordan</hi> to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104215:5"/>baptized of him) <hi>I have need to be baptized of thee, and comest thou unto me?</hi> Mat. 3.13, 14. So that <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> knew his Baptiſm to be inferiour to Chriſt's Baptiſm, ſo deſired more fully to partake of it. See alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 19.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Paul</hi> found certain Diſciples Partakers of <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, but they had not received the Spirit, as they themſelves confeſſed; ſo that the Spirit, and Water outward go not along to make up One Baptiſm; <hi>Paul</hi> laid his hands on them, and they received the Spirit, ſo knew its Baptiſm; theſe had <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they received the Spirit and its Baptiſm, which proves them diſtinct Baptiſms.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They are diſtinct, inaſmuch as the Figure and the Subſtance are diſtinct, as Circumciſion Outward and Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Inward were not One, but Two, that is, diſtinct Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: ſo the Baptiſm of <hi>Iohn</hi> with Water, and the Baptiſm of Chriſt with the Spiria, were diſtinct Baptiſms, whereby the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Judgments of ſuch appear, who affirm, teach and preach <hi>That the Spirit goes along with the Water, and both make up One Baptiſm; and that the Water is ſo influenced with a ſupernatural Vertue by the Word of Inſtitution, that Children</hi> (damnati priuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam nati, <hi>damn'd before they be born</hi>) <hi>are thereby made Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, Children of God and Inheriters of the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> And though ſince the Primitive Times, to fulfil Divine Praedictions, Darkneſs, yea, groſs Darkneſs hath benighted the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, and the peccant Humour of Error, Hereſie, Schiſm and Miſapprehenſions of Divine Truths hath been predominant in the infirm and crazy Body of nominal Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, yet the Lord hath ſo far opened the Eyes of ſome, as that they have dropped forth Teſtimonies in Vindication of that Truth here aſſerted, that is, that the Baptiſm of <hi>Iohn</hi> with Water, and the Baptiſm of Chriſt with the Spirit, without Water, were diſtinct Baptiſms, and that none may have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to render this a groundleſs Flouriſh, I ſhall here ſubjoyn a few Teſtimonies.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid in a certain place, <q>Illud manifeſtum eſt, alium
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104215:6"/>fuiſſe baptiſmum Johannes alium Chriſti; that is, <hi>It is clear and evident, that there was One Baptiſm of</hi> John, <hi>and another Baptiſm of</hi> Chriſt, Contr. Lit. Petil. 2.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paſor</hi> paraphraſing on <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. of the Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms, ſaid, <q>Here the Plural Number ſhews forth the Outward and Inward Baptiſm.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chryſoſtom ſaith, <q>That in the Apoſtles time the Baptiſm of Water, and the Baptiſm of the Spirit were different Baptiſms, and done at different Times, <hi>Magd.</hi> 5. <hi>Cent.</hi> 363.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> who lived about the year 230. ſaid, <q>The Baptiſm of <hi>Iohn</hi> waſhed the outward Body, but the Baptiſm of Chriſt cleanſeth the inward Man from the Defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sin, <hi>Polydor.</hi> lib. 4. cap. 4.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>The Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> gives not ſpiritual Grace nor Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sins; but Chriſt forgives Sins, and gives the Spirit plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully, <hi>Theophylact</hi> on Mat. 3.11.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſent to baptize with Water, but the Baptiſm of the Spirit was committed to Chriſt: <hi>John</hi> baptized with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, inviting to Repentance; Chriſt by his Spirit, wherewith he baptizeth, renews the Heart, and ſanctifieth by his Grace, <hi>Aug. Marlolat</hi> on <hi>Acts</hi> 1.5.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>
                           <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> makes Chriſt the Author of ſpiritual Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, but himſelf the Miniſter of outward Baptiſm only, not the putting away of the filth of the Fleſh, the Work of <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, but the Anſwer of a good Conſcience, which is an Effect of Chriſt's Baptiſm, ſaith <hi>Aug. Marlolat</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11.</q> A clear Diſtinction of the two Baptiſms is here im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Spark,</hi> the King's Chaplain, ſpeaking of the pouring forth of the Spirit upon the Apoſtles, ſaith, <q>They had before <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmum fluminis,</hi> the Watry Baptiſm of <hi>Iohn;</hi> but now <hi>baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum flaminis,</hi> the Baptiſm of the Holy Spirit; their Tongues were touched with a Coal from the Heavenly Altar.</q> A full Diſtinction of the two Baptiſms.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>The Baptiſm of <hi>Iohn</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Spark</hi>) doth not take away Sin, but puts them in mind thereof; but Chriſt's Baptiſm takes away Sin, his Spirit (ſaith he) is our <hi>Iordan.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104215:6"/>
                     <p>
                        <q>Forgiveneſs of Sins was not in nor by <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, but in our Baptiſm all ſins are blotted out, ſaith <hi>Ven. Bed. Hiſtor. Eccleſ.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Piſcator</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. ſpeaking of 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. ſaith, <q>Leſt any ſhould think that Outward Baptiſm ſaves us, <hi>Peter</hi> makes a Diſtinction, and aſcribes Salvation to Inward Baptiſm, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Not Outward Baptiſm, whereby the Filth of the Fleſh is put off, ſave us, but Inward Baptiſm, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>There is a two fold Baptiſm (ſaith <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11.) viz. <hi>fluminis et flaminis,</hi> that is, of Water, and of the Spirit; by <hi>John</hi>'s, with Water, the Polution of the Fleſh is put away; by Chriſt's, with the Spirit, the Anſwer of a Good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, purged from Dead Works, to God-ward is known.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. concerning the Doctrine of Baptiſms, makes a clear Diſtinction betwixt the <hi>outward</hi> Baptiſm of <hi>Iohn</hi> with Water, and the <hi>inward</hi> Baptiſm of Chriſt with the Spirit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Piſcator</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. ſaith, <q>There is a two-fold Baptiſm, the one Outward, whereby the Body is cleanſed, the other Inward by the Spirit, whereby men are regenerated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, waſhed and purged from the Filth of Sin.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>People were to be taught (ſaith <hi>Wilſon</hi> in his <hi>Comple at Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-Dictonary</hi>) 'to put a Difference betwixt Outward Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm by the Miniſter, and the Inward Baptiſm by the Spirit, wherewith Chriſt baptizeth.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>The Miniſter (ſaith the ſame <hi>Wilſon</hi>) baptizeth by Sprinkling with water, Chriſt baptizes by beſtowing the Gifts of his ſpirit.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prudentius</hi> holds out a clear Diſtinction betwixt <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm with Water, and Chriſt's Baptiſm with the Spirit; ſaying in his <hi>Euchirid,</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>'Perfundit fluvio paſtus Baptiſta locuſtus</l>
                           <l>'Sylvarumque ſavis, et amiſtus veſte Cameli</l>
                           <l>'Tinxerat et Chriſtum, ſed ſpirit us aethere miſſus</l>
                           <l>'Teſtatur tinctum, qui tinctis crimina donot.</l>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>John</hi> fed with Locuſts, and with Honey wild,</l>
                           <l>Clothed with Camel's Hair, the Baptiſt ſtil'd,</l>
                           <l>He dipped Chriſt, Chriſt by the Spirit's Grace</l>
                           <l>Baptizeth his, and doth their Sins deface.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="assertion">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104215:7"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The Second Aſſertion. John</hi>'s Baptiſm in or with Water, was a Figure or a Shadow of Chriſt's Baptiſm, in or with the Spirit, ſo thereby fulfilled and ended.</head>
                     <p>THE Living God made Man perfect and upright at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, as a Garden watered with Heavenly Drops, beautified with Fruits of Righteouſneſs, according to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the noble Seed in him, yet he kept not his original Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but was entangled in the Net of the Helliſh Spider, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Fruits of Unrighteouſneſs ſprung up in him, the Foundation of another Kingdom was laid, ſo that a world of Wickedneſs was uſher'd in, the comfortable Sun-ſhine of the Lord's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence was loſt; yet in this State there iſſued out from the Court of Heaven a Hu-and-Cry (as I may ſay) after faln and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn man, and it was proclaimed, yea, evangelized to and in his Ears, that <hi>The Seed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpent's Head,</hi> Gen. 3.15. Now, after this, in Ages and Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, this Seed was figured out by Types and Shadows, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Faithful were led as by the hand, to look after and wait for the Promiſed Seed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abel</hi> in his day offered a Firſtling of the Flock, ſhadowing out the Seed of the Woman, Chriſt Jeſus, the Firſt and the Laſt, Lord of and in his Flock, who was to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Noah,</hi> after the Flood, builded an Altar unto the Lord, and offered clean Beaſts and clean Fowl thereon, unto the Lord which the Apoſtle witneſſed fulfilled, when he ſaid, <hi>We have an Altar, whereof they have no Right to eat, who ſerve the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> Hebr. 13.10. <hi>in which Altar only is offered up a Clean Heart and Holy Hands.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the dayes of <hi>Abraham</hi> Circumciſion outward was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104215:7"/>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. a Shadow of a Circumciſion without hands in and through Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſaac</hi> burded an Altar, and called on the Name of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.25.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jacob</hi> erected an Altar, and called it, <hi>El Elohe Iſrael;</hi> which is, being interpreted, <hi>God, the God of Iſrael, Gen.</hi> 33.20.</p>
                     <p>And among the other Figures of the firſt Prieſthood, which time fails me to ſpeak of particularly, <hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to make a Laver of Bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, and to put Water therein, and <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons were to waſh their Hands and their Feet therein, leſt they dye, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who are of God, they read theſe things, and ſee what was pointed out thereby. Now when <hi>John</hi> was come, who was not the Chriſt, but <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>the Fore-runner of Chriſt,</hi> it pleaſed the Lord, that he ſhould not be without ſomething in his Diſpenſation, which might point out that which ſhould ſhortly be revealed, as others before him in their reſpective Ages and Generations had; and what was that? even to <hi>baptize with Water ſuch as repented and believed, to clenſe away the filth of the fleſh outwardly;</hi> figuring thereby Chriſt Jeſus, who by the Power of his Spirit ſhould purifie, waſh and clenſe inwardly all that received him; ſo that Chriſt being come, who was before <hi>Abel,</hi> yea, before the Hills and Mountains were; he put an End, not only to <hi>Abel</hi>'s Firſtlings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to <hi>Noah</hi>'s Altar, to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s Circumciſion, to <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Altar, to <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Laver-waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but alſo to <hi>John's</hi> Jordan-waſhing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet I ſay, though theſe things were but outward, and availed nothing to the purifying of the Conſcience, yet inaſmuch as they were divine Commands, and Shadows of a future Glory, they were not to be diſputed, but practiſed, owned and honoured in their time and ſeaſon: To this purpoſe well ſaid <hi>Bernard,</hi> Non attend it verus obediens, quale ſit quod praecipitur, hoc ſolo contentus quia praecipitur: that is, <hi>One truly obedient minds not what like the thing is, which is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in this only contenting himſelf, or acquieſcing, becauſe it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, if <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Water-baptiſm</hi> was a Figure, a Shadow, a Type of Chriſt, the Life, the Glory, the Treaſury of the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſpenſation, the Head of his Body, the Church, his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104215:8"/>which ſtands not in Words, but in Power; not in Shadows, Types and Figures, but in Subſtance, in Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the holy Spirit: and that it was a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> Writers have born evidence, and plentifully, then by Chriſt ended and fulfilled, ſo bears no Evangelical Perpetuity.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. calls <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> a <hi>Ceremony.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Piſcator</hi> on <hi>John</hi> 1. ſaith, <hi>When</hi> John <hi>had inſtituted a new cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, thoſe that were ſent enquired of him, By that Authority he did thoſe things, if he was neither</hi> Chriſt <hi>nor</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Repentance and Faith</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>were the Qualifications of</hi> John<hi>'s Typical Baptiſm, which was in ſlain Water, without Oyl, Salt, Spittle, Cream, which are Antichriſtian Additaments.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Danvers,</hi> in his <hi>Treatiſe of Baptiſm,</hi> calls it, <hi>a Sign or a Figure of the Myſtery of the Goſpel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Baxter</hi> calls <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> a <hi>Sign of Regeneration,</hi> pag. 117.</p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> calls <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> a <hi>Shadow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Sacraments of Baptiſm, and of the Supper of the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Juel</hi> in his <hi>Apologet</hi>) <hi>we with</hi> Tertullian, Origen, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Jerome, Chriſoſtom, Baſil, Dioniſius, <hi>and othe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, do call them Figures, Ceremonies, Signs, Types, Shadows, Similitudes, Remembrances, &amp;c. And every Type hath its Anti-type, by the which it is ended and fulfilled.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>was not inſtituted to have Grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably tyed to it, but to figure out the Power of divine Grace;</hi> giving theſe Reaſons, 1ſt, <hi>That</hi> John <hi>made a Diſtinction, I with Water, Chriſt with the Spirit.</hi> 2dly, <hi>Otherwiſe all the Baptized ſhould be regenerated, which appears otherwiſe in</hi> Simon Magus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias, Saphira, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Calvin,</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> calls <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> a <hi>Sign,</hi> a <hi>Figure;</hi> ſaying, <hi>If men be Partakers of the thing ſignified, that is, of the Subſtance, why ſhall they be with-held from the Sign? If they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Truth, why ſhall they be driven from the Figure?</hi> Lib. 4. Cap. 16. In calling it a <hi>Sign,</hi> a <hi>Figure,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Well, but his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is Carnal and Antichriſtian, in ſaying, if men have the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, why ſhould they not have the Figure, by this crooked Rule of Reaſoning, might all the ritual Obſervances of</hi> Moſes <hi>be impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Goſpel-Believers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104215:8"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hammond,</hi> in his <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> and <hi>Annotations</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. calls <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Baptiſm</hi> a <hi>Ceremony,</hi> ſaying, John <hi>initiated Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with Water, but</hi> Chriſt <hi>with Fire;</hi> yea, and on <hi>Mark</hi> 1.5, 8. he paraphraſeth, ſaying, <hi>Water is the only Signal that</hi> John <hi>uſed, after the Jewiſh manner; but</hi> Chriſt <hi>was to ſend down the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from Heaven; and is not Chriſt the End of</hi> Ceremonies, Types, Figures <hi>and</hi> Shadows? John<hi>'s Water-Baptiſm, as all the Shadows of</hi> Moſes, <hi>were but to endure for a time; for as all the Prophets were until</hi> John, <hi>ſo</hi> John <hi>was until</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>by his internal Waſhing, the Laver of Regeneration, not only fulfilled and ended</hi> Moſes's <hi>Laver, but</hi> John's <hi>Jordan-waſhing, by fulfilling inwardly that which they repreſented outwardly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>Chriſt himſelf was Baptized with Water, doth not that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate Water-Baptiſm in the Church?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt was Circumciſed, not that from thence Outward Circumciſion ſhould be continued; he went into the Temple, and taught there, and caſt out the Prophaners thereof; he ſaid to the clenſed Leper, <hi>Go and ſhew thy felf to the Prieſt, and offer a Gift according to the Law,</hi> Mat. 8. ſo he was baptized, not that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended thereby to perpetuate or continue theſe things, Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Subſtance and Anti-type, owned the Shadows, Types and Figures in their place, and this tended to the Conviction of ſuch who queſtioned the Authority of thoſe Typical Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Baptizatus eſt Chriſtus a Johanne, ut Johannis miniſterium approbaret,</hi> ſaith <hi>Martinius:</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt was baptized by</hi> John, <hi>that he might approve of the Miniſtration of</hi> John, <hi>to juſtifie it in its Time, Place and Seaſon, againſt ſuch as queſtion'd the Authority of it.</hi> So 'twas ſaid, <hi>The Phariſees and Lawyers rejected the counſel of God againſt themſelves, being not baptized of</hi> John, Luke 7.30. And Chriſt put a Query to the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Baptiſm of</hi> John <hi>is it from Heaven, or of men?</hi> Luke 20.4. Chriſt owning the Figures in their time and place, proved thereby their Inſtitution to be divine, but all this was before he was offered up; for when he was offered up, then he blotted out the Hand-writing of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, took it out of the way, nailed it to his Croſs, Col. 2.14.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104215:9"/>
                        <hi>When Chriſt,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Piſcator</hi> on this place) <hi>was nailed to the Croſs, even then the Ritual Obſervances of</hi> Moſes <hi>were ſore wounded, yea, aboliſhed. The firſt Covenant</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſtood only in Meats and Drinks, and divers Waſhings or Baptiſms, and carnet Ordinances, impoſed until the time of Reformation, the Figures, which could not perfect the Obſervers, as pertaining to the conſcience, were to give way to the Evangelical and Spiritual VVorſhip brought in by the Subſtance,</hi> Hebr. 9. The Goſpel-Time is a Time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; ſo ſuch as ſtick to the Figure, and will not have the black Lines of their Corruptions waſhed away by the Blood of the Lamb, ſuch remain unreformed. Though Chriſt owned the Shadows before he was offered up, yet when he was offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, riſen and aſcended, and the Promiſe of the Father fulfilled, the Spirit, wherewith Chriſt baptizes, revealed, then theſe things were not preached up, but againſt; then <hi>Paul</hi> preached againſt <hi>circumciſion</hi> outward, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2. ſaying, <hi>If ye be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall proſit you nothing;</hi> yea, he tell them, they <hi>bewitch'd them,</hi> who entangled them in the droughty Deſert of Ritual Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances; and he preached <hi>circumciſion inward: Stephen</hi> bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſaying, <hi>The Moſt High dwells not in Temples made with hands, Acts</hi> 7. Yea, and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Prieſthood was changed,</hi> Hebr. 7.12. Yea, and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.17. ſaying further, <hi>There is one Lord, one Faith, one baptiſm, Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. There had been two Baptiſms, <hi>John</hi>'s with Water, Chriſt's with the Spirit without Water; but now the Shadow had given way to the Subſtance, one Baptiſm, ſaith he; and he tells what it was, <hi>by one Spirit into one Body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. by one Spirit, not by Water: So that the Spirit's Baptiſm, which is Chriſt's Baptiſm, is the One Baptiſm which he preached up in the Churches: Who are of God, may read here the Temporary Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> laid aſide, and the Spirit's Baptiſm preached up; Shadows have no footing in Chriſt's Kingdom. When Jeſus was baptized, he went ſtraight-way out of the Water, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit deſcended like a Dove upon him, the Spirit wherewith Chriſt baptizeth; and a Voice from Heaven ſaid, <hi>This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> Mat. 3. and in another place, <hi>Hear ye him:</hi> Not <hi>Moſes</hi> with his Laver-Waſhing, not <hi>Iohn</hi> with his Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan-Waſhing,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104215:9"/>hear the Son, who baptizes with the holy Spirit and with Fire, not with viſible Water: thus the Legal Rites, which Chriſt allowed of before he was offered up, the Apoſtles, after his return in Spirit, they teſtified againſt the ſame, yet in ſo doing were not Tranſgreſſors of Chriſt's Doctrine, but had his Mind: Theſe things being truly conſidered, and weighed in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, it cannot but appear, that it ſhews no ſoundneſs of Judgment to plead, that Chriſt's being baptized by <hi>Iohn,</hi> perpetuates Water-Baptiſm or Rantiſm in the Evangelical Diſpenſation. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Colloſſions, If ye be dead with Chriſt, from the Rudiments of the world, why as though living in the world are ye ſubject to</hi> Ordinances? <hi>touch not, taſte not, handle not,</hi> Col. 2.20, 21. Things that had been of Divine Inſtitution, when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued beyond the Bounds of their ſeaſon and time, became world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rudiments and Doctrines of Men.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt; doth not this Inſtitution enjoyn all Miniſters to Baptize?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw</hi> This Scripture hath been much abuſed by Tranſlators and Interpreters, and alledged to patronize the Formal Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, as may appear by what follows, being truly interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 'tis thus rendred, <hi>Go ye therefore, diſciple all Nations, baptizing or dipping them into the Name of the Father; and of the Son, and of the holy Spirit:</hi> and it makes nothing for Water Baptiſm, nor for Rantiſm; for Chriſt having qualified his Apoſtles to be his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to the uttermoſt parts of the Earth, ſent them not to preach up <hi>Iohn,</hi> and his <hi>VVater-baptiſm,</hi> but to preach the Everlaſting Goſpel, Chriſt, and his Baptiſm, which is ſpiritual: <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid and bare record, that <hi>he baptized with VVater; but he that was to come, Chriſt Jeſus, ſhould baptize with the holy spirit.</hi> Now, to ſay, Chriſt baptized with Water, or ſent his Apoſtles to baptize there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, is to queſtion the Teſtimony and Record of <hi>Iohn,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>he ſhould baptize with the holy spirit.</hi> After Chriſt was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from the Dead, he met his Diſciples on a Montain in <hi>Galilee,</hi> firſt telling them, that all Power was given unto him in Heaven
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104215:10"/>and in Earth, then he informed them what their Work ſhould be.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> To Diſciple the Nations; that is, by the Power of their Miniſtry to bring them to be Diſciples of Chriſt, to learn of him to know his Teaching, to take up his Yoke, to bear the ſame, to learn Obedience, to come into the ſelf-denying ſtate of Diſciple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſo the word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>riginally imports, ſaith <hi>Bullenger, Zwinglius, Leigh, Fiſher, &amp;c. Trapp.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> He told his Diſciples, that they ſhould <hi>baptize</hi> or <hi>dip</hi> the Nations, not in the Name, but <hi>into</hi> the Name of the Father, &amp;c. <hi>Dell, Fiſher, Hammon, Trapp.</hi> And what is it to baptize or dip into the Name of the Father? Even the ſame that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke of, when he ſaid, <hi>By one spirit we are all bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>zed into one body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. So that it is the Spirit that baptizeth into one Body, as alſo into the Name of the Father, to be a living Member of that Body, whereof Chriſt is the Head; 'tis the Spirit that effects this, not viſible Water.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore, Chriſt in theſe words commanded not his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to turn back to <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration, to dip them in <hi>Jordan,</hi> or in any other River, or in a Bowl, Baſon or Font, but into the Name of the Father, &amp;c. which is no other thing then by the Power of the Spirit, whereof they were Miniſters, to bring them into the Power of God, to have fellowſhip with him through the Spirit. Now, the Name of God is his Vertue or Power, as, <hi>In my Name they ſhall caſt out Devils;</hi> that is, <hi>in my Power;</hi> this <hi>Zwinglius</hi> on this place obſerves.</p>
                     <p>Teachers in Sprinkling of Infants, which they call Baptiſm, uſe this Scripture as a Form of words, ſaying, <hi>I baptize thee in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> which thing the Apoſtles did not, which undoubtedly they would have done, if Chriſt had commanded it, as an abſolute Form.</p>
                     <p>Further, <hi>Zwinglius</hi> ſaid of this place, <hi>Chriſtus Jeſus baptiſmi, formulam qua uteremur, his verbis, non inſtituit, quemadmodum Theologi hactenus falſo tradiderunt:</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus did not in theſe words inſtitute a form of Baptiſm, which we ſhould uſe, as Divines have hitherto falſly taught.</hi> This was the Teſtimony of <hi>Zwinglius,</hi> who in his Day was a great Oppoſer of <hi>Anabaptiſts,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104215:10"/>Lib de bap.</hi> pag. 66. Tom. 2. oper. <hi>Piſcator</hi> on the ſame place peaks fully to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>Again, This place cannot be meant of Water-baptiſm, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> thanked God he had baptized none but ſuch and ſuch; <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.14, 15, 16, 17. yet he fulfilled that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Goſpel in a circuit from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Illyricum,</hi> and many by his Miniſtry were diſcipled, brought into the ſtate of Diſciples, to learn of Chriſt, yea, and into the Name of God, that is, into his Power; many were baptized into the Name of the Father, as his Sons; into the Name of his Son, as his Jewels and Ranſomed Ones; into the Name of the Holy Spirit, as his Sanctified Ones; theſe knew the One Baptiſm, by One Spirit, into One Body.</p>
                     <p>Why doth <hi>Paul</hi> thank God, that he baptized none but ſuch and ſuch? 1ſt, Becauſe he ſaw them idolizing and jangling about it, which he knew to be a thing not of abſolute Neceſſity, not a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, but uſed or born with for a ſeaſon, for the ſake of the Weak, and others, in reference to <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Miniſtry, if he had commonly practiſed it before, from his Practice, they might have been ſtrengthned in their Thoughts about it, he being a great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He thanks God, that he baptized none but ſuch and ſuch; And why? Becauſe he was not ſent of Chriſt ſo to do. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Leſt ſome ſhould ſay, that he baptized in his own Name, <hi>rather into his own Name,</hi> as the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies and divers <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlations render it; ſeeing from Chriſt, in whoſe Name he came, he had no Command ſo to do. What Ambaſſadour of an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prince, commiſſioned to treat with a forreign Prince, about e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecial Matters if he fail, in reference to the Contents of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and treat about Matters whereto he was not commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; can he expect that his Prince's Favour ſhould be unto him as Dew upon the Graſs, or rather that his Wrath ſhould be as the Roaring of a Lyon? So if that in <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. had been a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand obligatory to all Goſpel-Miniſters, to Baptize with outward Water, could <hi>Paul</hi> have Cauſe of Rejoycing in that he fulfilled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot the Command? Conſider this, and judge.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104215:11"/>
                     <p>Cbj. <hi>That in</hi> Mat. 28. <hi>muſt needs relate to outward Water; for the Apoſtles could not Baptize with the Spirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who as thus reaſon, are ignorant of the Miniſtry of Chriſt, which is a Miniſtry of the Spirit; for all that are ſent of Chriſt, through their Miniſtry people are turned from Darkneſs to Light, and tranſlated from Death to Life, where Chriſt's Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is known; and this they do as indued with Power from above, John 17.18. <hi>As thou haſt ſent me into the World</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo ſend I them.</hi> And muſt not Chriſt and his Miniſters be found in one Work? even to turn people from Satan's power to the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, where the ſpiritual Baptiſm is. While <hi>Peter</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and his Kinſmen and near Friends, the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit fell on them, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. wherein Chriſt's Baptiſm is. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Paul</hi> laid his Hands on certain, and the holy Spirit fell upon them, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. even that Spirit wherewith Chriſt baptizeth. Yea, and in <hi>Acts</hi> 26. <hi>Paul</hi> gave a Relation of his Call, as alſo of his Work; <hi>I</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>have appeared unto thee for this purpoſe, to make thee a Miniſter:</hi> And what was his Work? <hi>In preaching to the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>to open their Eyes, to turn them from Darkneſs to Light, from the power of Satan usto God, that they may receive For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of Sins, and an Inheritance among them that are ſanctified by Faith in Chriſt Ieſus. Paul</hi> declared his Commiſſion to preach, and the Effects of it was glorious, Converſion, Faith, Remiſſion of Sins, Sanctification, Salvation; he took not Fleſh and Blood into counſel, evil Counſellors for the Soul; but ſilencing Fleſh, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining a noble Reſolution, he put himſelf into the hand of God, ſaying in effect, <hi>Te duce, vera ſequor; To duce, falſa nego.</hi> Conſider, <hi>Paul</hi> in and through the Virtue of him that ſent him, opened peoples Eyes, and turned them from Darkneſs to Light, and from Satan's power unto God: Were not theſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Spirit's Baptiſm? Yes; for without the Spirit, and its Baptiſm, none come to God, nor out of Satans power: Thus <hi>Paul</hi> diſcipled the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that received his Teſtimony, and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized them in and through the Spirit, into the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104215:11"/>and of the Son, and of the holy Spirit; and this was and is done, not by Water-baptiſm without, but by the Spirit's Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm within.</p>
                     <p>Again, 2 Cor. 3.6. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies, <hi>That they were made of God able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit,</hi> even of the Spirit in which Chriſt's Baptiſm is revealed: And <hi>Paul</hi> demanded of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Received ye the Spirit by the Works of the Law, or by the hearing of Faith?</hi> Gal. 3.2. As if he ſhould have ſaid, True it is, you have received the Spirit, but not by the Works of the Law, but by the hearing of Faith; ſo that the Apoſtles preaching the Word of Faith unto them, they received the Spirit, even that Spirit which baptizeth into one Body.</p>
                     <p>So that it is clear unto me, that ſuch as alledge this Scripture, <hi>Go and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, &amp;c.</hi> to patronize Water-Baptiſm or Rantiſm, that is, <hi>dipping</hi> or <hi>ſprinkling,</hi> in Goſpel-dayes, they are Wreſters and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verters of the Scripture; and that this Scripture, as many others, hath in the dark Night of Apoſtacy been wreſted, perverted, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed and miſ-interpreted, beſide what hath been ſpoken, may be more fully made apparent.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zuinglius</hi> and <hi>Piſcator</hi> ſay expreſly, that <q>Chriſt Jeſus did not in thoſe words inſtitute a Form of Baptiſm, and that Divines had taught falſly, who held it out as a Form.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>One <hi>Gulielmus,</hi> who was a <hi>Roman-Catholick,</hi> taught, <q>That the Form of Baptiſm ſhould be thus, I baptize thee in the Name of the Father, of the Son, of the holy Ghoſt, and of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> Cent. 13. Mag. 419.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>There was a certain Prieſt, who being a Lack Latin, ſaid in baptizing, <hi>Baptizo te in nomine patria, et filia, et ſpiritu ſancta;</hi> which is falſe Latine, as Latiniſts know; about this there was no ſmall contention, as, whether the Baptiſm was lawful, yea or nay, where Falſe Latin was broached; <hi>Bonifacius</hi> Biſhop under <hi>Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Magnus,</hi> was of Opinion, that the Party thus baptized ought to be Re-baptized; upon which Pope <hi>Zacharias</hi> wrote to <hi>Doni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facius,</hi> That he ſhould not be Re-baptized, for that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Falſe Latine, it was True Baptiſm; he alſo put him in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104215:12"/>mind of the Cuſtom of the Church, that if any were baptized by Hereticks, ſuch ſhould not be re-baptized, but only purged by Impoſition of Hands: Thus Falſe Latin got the Day.</p>
                     <p>A Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> in a Synod expreſſed himſelf thus, <q>Let Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm be celebrated with Reverence, and let the Prieſt be very cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in the Diſtinction and Pronuntiation of Words, in which all the Vertue of the Sacrament and the Salvation of Children conſiſts, <hi>Statut. Synodal. Odonis Pariſienſis Epiſcopi.</hi>
                        </q> This is a ſtrange, yea, an unchriſtian Doctrine, denying the Virgin's Birth, Jeſus, by interpretation a <hi>Saviour,</hi> in whom alone Salvation is, and aſcribing the ſame to Water without, Formal Words, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions and Pronuntiation without.</p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>The Apoſtles practiſed</hi> Water-baptiſm, <hi>not only before the coming in of Chriſt's</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>but after, as 'tis evident in the</hi> Acts of the Apoſtles; <hi>doth not this infer the continuance of it in Goſpol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> As it was ſaid in a certain Caſe, ſo may I ſay in this, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis officium eſt, ut res; it a tempora rerum; Quarere</hi>— that is, A Judge muſt not only enquire after things, but alſo after their Times and Seaſons: True it is, the Apoſtles for a ſeaſon practiſed Water-Baptiſm, not Rantiſm, that is, Dipping, not Sprinkling; but whether they did it by Command, or by Permiſſion, hath been a point of controverſie: As for me and Thouſands more, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that they did it not by Command from Chriſt, but took it up, and continued it for a ſeaſon, in relation to <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Water-Baptiſm, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in a certain caſe, 1 Cor. 7.6. <hi>But I speak this by Permiſſion, and not by Commandment.</hi> After the Aſcenſion of Chriſt ſome of the Apoſtles uſed outward circumciſion, not as by Chriſt's Command, but in relation to <hi>Moſes,</hi> for their ſakes (for a ſeaſon) who were weak, or otherwiſe affected, certainly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſoon after the Virtue and Purity of Circumciſion made without Hands, would put an End to Circumciſion outward; for the Moſaical Shadows and Figures were the moſt truly put off when t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ey felt the Subſtance, Chriſt, the Life, the End of ſuch things riſen in their mortal Bodies; for, as the Sun-light ſwallows
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104215:12"/>up the Moon-light, and as Darkneſs is chaſed away when the Sun appears, and mounts up in its luſtre, ſo all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Shadows, Types and Figures, from the dayes of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Abel</hi> to <hi>John,</hi> were to vaniſh as the Life of Chriſt came to be exalted in his Church; <hi>John</hi> intimated thus much when he ſaid, <hi>I muſt decreaſe, he muſt increaſe:</hi> So <hi>John</hi>'s Water-baptiſm was to decreaſe, <hi>Iohn</hi> being a Fore-runner, and his Servant, was to reſign up his Baptiſm to Chriſt, yea, and as a Servant to deliver all things into his hands, as Heir and Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: <hi>Iohn's</hi> Baptiſm reached unto Chriſt's Kingdom, but hath no place therein; yea, and to bring Shadows and Figures into his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is (if rightly underſtood) antichriſtian; for his Kingdom is wholely ſpiritual, and in his Church he is a Bundle of Myrh, yes, that very thing which from <hi>Abel</hi> to <hi>Iohn</hi> was repreſented by outward Shadows.</p>
                     <p>So that thoſe the Apoſtles baptized, as internally, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, they did it for a ſeaſon in relation to <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration, for the ſake of the Weak, and of others, the Day being but even dawning, which was to put an End unto and fulfil the Laver-Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, yea, and the <hi>Jordan</hi>-waſhing, as all other Shadows from <hi>Abel</hi> to that very ſeaſon.</p>
                     <p>And that they baptized on this Account, and not by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, ſeveral Grounds induce me to believe:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt, Paul</hi> a choſen Veſſel, who planted many Churches, yet altogether ceaſed from <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration of Water-baptiſm, after that he had uſed it twice or thrice, as probably all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14, 15, 16, 17. he thanks God that he baptized none but ſuch and ſuch, ſaying expreſly, <hi>Chriſt ſent him not to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, dip or plung their Bodies in Outward Water, though he did is to a few, yet he had no command for it:</hi> Hence it neceſſarily follows, that he did it by Permiſſion, in reference to <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration, for the ſake of the Weak, or of others, and the preſent time, till the Lord Chriſt, the End of all Figures, was more revealed in them: What was he ſent to do? To preach the Goſpel, Chriſt, and his Baptiſm, which waſhes inwardly, fulfilling outward Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhings.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> This <hi>Paul,</hi> who had the Mind of Chriſt, held out
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104215:13"/>but one continuing Baptiſm in the Kingdom of Chriſt, writing to the Saints at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>There is one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm,</hi> Epheſ. 4.5. There had been two Baptiſms, <hi>Iohn's</hi> with Water, Chriſt's with the Spirit; yet the one is repealed, and not preached up among them. So to the wiſe in heart I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, whether this one Baptiſm he preached up, was <hi>John's</hi> with Water, or Chriſt's with the Spirit; and whatever thou be that ſayes that the one Baptiſm which the Apoſtle preached up, was <hi>John's</hi> Water Baptiſm, I tell thee thou denyes Chriſt, and his Baptiſm with the Spirit, and ſets <hi>John</hi> and his Water-baptiſm in his Throne, thou ſtumbleſt at the Rock, the Day-Star thou knoweſt not, nor the Sun of Righteouſneſs riſen, and the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows flown away. Now if any ſcruple this Scripture, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply deſires to be reſolved, whether Baptiſm he preaches up, the Mouth of <hi>Paul</hi> in another place may inform thee, 1 Cor. 12.13. <hi>By one Spirit we are all baptized into one Body.</hi> Here thou may'ſt be ſatisfied, he tells thee, there is One Baptiſm; he alſo informs thee, what that one Baptiſm is, not into <hi>Iordan,</hi> not into a Bowl, Baſon or Font, but by the one Spirit into one Body. So to every ſeeing Eye <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Water-baptiſm is here laid aſide, his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance thereto repeal'd. Now it being that <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to baptize with Water, and that he preached up one baptiſm, and that of the Spirit, it neceſſarily follows, that whom he baptized with Water, he did it by Permiſſion in reference to <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; Uſing and Inſtituting are two things; the Apoſtles Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcended where they never Commanded.</p>
                     <p>And whereas ſome alledge, <hi>The Eunuch ſaid unto</hi> Philip, <hi>Here is Water, what doth hinder me to be baptized?</hi> Philip <hi>ſaid, If thou believe with all thy heart, thou mayeſt,</hi> Acts 8.36, 37. He ſaith not <hi>thou muſt;</hi> he held it not to be of abſolute Neceſſity, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended, as before: The holy Spirit, which ſeals up to God, was received without Water-baptiſm, or Rantiſm; where then is the Neceſſity of <hi>Dipping</hi> or <hi>Sprinkling?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, in reference to what was laſt objected, ſeveral Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies conſonant to what I here aſſert, might be produced, and that of ſuch, who were not of mean Account in their Day, their Works by many yet had in eſteem.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:104215:13"/>
                     <p>
                        <q>The uſe of the Ceremonial Law (ſaith <hi>Wollebius</hi> in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places) was profitab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e before the Death of Chriſt; after his Death unto the Promulgation or ſpreading abroad of the Goſpel, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> as indifferent, but after the Promulgation or clear publiſhing of the Goſpel, the obſervation of Ceremonies is not only unwholſome, and unprofitable, but alſo deadly. Hence <hi>Paul</hi> at the beginning, would have <hi>Timothy</hi> Circumciſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the weakneſs of the <hi>Jews, Acts</hi> 16.3. but after that the Goſpel was more fully Preached; he would not yield that <hi>Titus</hi> ſhould be Circumciſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. And ſaith he, 'The Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Ceremonies would now be nothing but a denying of the Coming and Death of Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſt.</q> So there was a time (ſay I) when <hi>Iordan</hi>-waſhing was profitable; there was a time, when it was indifferent, in which time the Apoſtles made ſome uſe of it; and there is a time, when it may be ſaid to be Antichriſtian, in pleading for the outward Waſhing, when the Laver of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, filled with the Water of Life, for the clenſing of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man, is ſet open, and when performed in that Spirit which is at Enmity unto Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wilfred,</hi> a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> reaſoning with Biſhop <hi>Coleman,</hi> about the time of the <hi>celebration of Eaſter,</hi> ſaid, <q>God forbid we ſhou'd accuſe the Apoſtle of Folly, when he obſerved the Precepts of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Church as yet <hi>Iudaizing</hi> in many things; neither were the Apoſtles on a ſudden able to aboliſh all Legal Obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which had been of Divine Inſtitution: On this account <hi>Paul</hi> circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> offered in the Temple; purified himſelf, allowed of Head-ſhaving, had his Head ſhorn at <hi>Cencrea,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to no other end, but to avoid miniſtring of Offence to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who being weak ſaw not the End of theſe things; in the year 664.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Piſcator</hi> on <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. ſaith, <q>After the Example of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> that the Weak may be gained, let us not refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto troubleſome things, which otherwiſe we might with a good Conſcience forbear.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>
                           <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaith <hi>Trapp</hi> on 1 Cor. 9.) became all things to all men that he might ſave ſome; and how? not in conforming to their Impieties, but in the Uſe of things indifferent, in Bowels of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104215:14"/>Compaſſion to them. <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaith he) harp'd much of this String, out of a fervent and ardent Deſire to gain Souls to the Lord.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Though many Legal Types (ſaith <hi>Gell</hi>) continued ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time after Chriſt's Death, yet they loſt their poſitive and obligatory Power, and were uſed only as <hi>Adiaphora,</hi> things indifferent, in Compliance with the inveterate Prejudices of new Converts, lately brought over from <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> who could not quickly lay aſide that great Veneration, which they had for the Rites of <hi>Moſaik</hi> Inſtitutions.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Obj. Peter <hi>baptized ſome</hi> Gentiles <hi>after that the Spirit was fain upon them; doth not this perpetuate Water-Baptiſm?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> True it is, while <hi>Peter</hi> preached the Everlaſting Goſpel unto the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the Gift of the Holy Spirit was poured out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; then ſaid <hi>Peter, Can any man forbid Water, that theſe ſhould not be baptized, which have received the Holy Spirit as well as we?</hi> Acts 10.44, &amp;c. The Grounds and Reaſons why Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Baptiſm, <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration, was ſome time uſed for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the primitive times by the Apoſtles, are before mentioned: I do not believe, that <hi>Peter</hi> had any more Command for Water-Baptiſm then <hi>Paul</hi> had, who ſaid expreſly, <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the Gospel:</hi> Yea, and this <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27. <hi>I have not ſhunned to declare unto you the whole Counſel of God.</hi> It ſeems <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration of Water-Baptiſm's Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance was not of his Counſel: Where did he exhort <hi>Timothy, Titus, Philemon,</hi> or any of the Churches he wrote Epiſtles to, to continue Water-baptiſm? on the contrary he ſhews it was fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ended, repealed, as hath before been ſpoken to, though in Relation to <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Miniſtration, and in Compliance with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State, he baptized ſome few, as others upon the ſame grounds did. <hi>Paul</hi> circumciſed <hi>Timothy;</hi> yet in 1 Cor. 7.19. he ſaith, <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion is nothing; but the keeping of the commandments of God:</hi> The ſame may be ſaid of Water-baptiſm, 'Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not <hi>Dipping,</hi> or <hi>Not Dipping,</hi> but the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Commandments of God; this is the <hi>bonum hominis,</hi>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:104215:14"/>the <hi>totum hominis,</hi> the <hi>one thing neceſſary,</hi> 'twas not eaſie to bring them from what had been commanded, but as Truth diſcovered it ſelf to be the Subſtance thereof: <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Galatians</hi> ſaid, <hi>How turn ye again to the weak and beggarly Elements, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye deſire again to be in Bondage?</hi> Gal. 4.9. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at is earthly and beggarly is not of power to enrich with ſpiritual Bleſſings: Water is an Element, &amp; appertains to the elemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ary Part in man, which is to paſs away, in the Revelation of the Subſtance, which turns out the earthly within, and earthly Rudiments without, eſtabliſhing a Kingdom in Righteouſneſs and Subſtance, out of Figures and Shadows. <hi>Peter</hi> never aſcribed Regeneration to outward Water; neither did he preach, That Children (<hi>damnati priuſquam nati;</hi> that is, <hi>damned before they be born,</hi> as the Doctrine is now) by ſprinkling Water upon them, are made Members of Chriſt, Children of God, and Inheritors of the Kingdom of Heaven; but he aſcribed Regeneration to the Eternal Word, ſaying, <hi>Being born again, not of corruptible Seed, but of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, by the Word of God, which lives and abides forever,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.23.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Peter,</hi> a Fiſher of Men, having caught a Draught of <hi>Gentiles,</hi> was right-glad thereof; ſo in Compliance with the preſent Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as others did, condeſcended to Outward Water, which wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes the Outward Man, and might take Occaſion therefrom to exhort them to wait for an Encreaſe of the Spirit's Virtue and Power, the Heavenly Baptiſm, which waſheth the Inward Man, for inward cleanſing; the Effect of the Spirit's Baptiſm is a gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Work.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="assertion">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104215:15"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The Third Aſſertion. Chriſt</hi>'s Baptiſm in or with the Spirit only, is the Baptiſm that is to continue in the Church to the End of the World.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>JOhn</hi> being the Fore-runner of Chriſt, according to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Appointment, was to baptize with Outward Water, <hi>John</hi> 1.33. to waſh away the Filth of the Outward Man, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing out Chriſt ready to be revealed, and by his ſpiritual Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm to cleanſe the Inward Man, to make it a Habitation of God; and this Water-baptiſm was to be of leſs Continuance then the Shadows of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as the Morning-Star, though brighter then the other Stars, ſhines leſs while then they, becauſe the ſudden Appearance of the Sun ſwallows it up: So <hi>John</hi>'s Water-baptiſm, though its Beginning was long after Circumciſion, commanded in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s dayes, and the Shadows of the Firſt Prieſthood, commanded in the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet was it to have an End with them: for when as after Chriſt's Aſcenſion, Chriſt's Baptiſm began, cleanſing inwardly, then <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, a Figure thereof was ended and fulfilled, the Shadow was to give way to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the Sign to the Truth, the Letter to the Spirit, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the Son; for, as the Prophets were until <hi>John,</hi> ſo <hi>John</hi> was until Chriſt; and <hi>John</hi> muſt no more exceed his Bounds, then <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets theirs: as the Prophets gave up to <hi>John,</hi> ſo <hi>Iohn</hi> was to give up to Chriſt: <hi>Iohn,</hi> a Creature, had a Temporary Baptiſm; but Chriſt, who is the ſame to day, yeſterday and forever, hath an Everlaſting Baptiſm, by the Spirit into one Body: and Chriſt's Kingdom ſtands not in Signs, Figures and Shadows, but in Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in that Spirit wherewith he baptizeth.</p>
                     <p>Now, after <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Water-Baptiſm had continued ſome 4 Years, then Chriſt's Baptiſm with the Spirit, without Water, began to be manifeſted, as you may ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 1.5. Chriſt told his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſaying, John <hi>truly baptized with Water, but ye ſhall be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104215:15"/>with the holy Spirit not many dayes hence.</hi> Confider, they were not to ſtick in <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Baptiſm, much leſ. in Rantiſm, a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then unheard of, nor build their Tarbernacles there, nor judge it ſufficient, but were to wait for the Promiſe of the Father, even the Spirit, wherewith Chriſt baptizeth; the plentiful effuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit was reſerved as the great Bleſſing of Goſpel-days, of the Evangelical State and Diſpenſation, which is to run parallel with the Age and Duration of the World; herein the Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Goſpel is preached to Kindreds Tongues and Nations.</p>
                     <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is precious Promiſe of the Father was accompliſhed and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled at the Day of Pentecoſt, when the Diſciples were waiting together in one Place, Cloven Tongues, like, as of Fire, ſate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on each of them, and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and ſpake with other Tongues, as the Spirit gave them Utterance, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4. Thus it was evident and manifeſt, that <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was a true Prophet, who ſaid, <hi>I baptize with Water, but Chriſt ſhall baptize with the Holy Spirit and with Fire.</hi> Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> Chap. 1. bad them wait for the promiſe of the Father; he told them what the Promiſe was, even the Baptiſm with the holy Spirit; and they received what they waited for at the Day of Pentecoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. they were filled with the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which was Chriſt's Baptiſm without Water; mark this, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Water, more excellent then <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Baptiſm with Water. Now <hi>Baptiſts</hi> and <hi>Rantiſts, Dippers</hi> and <hi>Sprinklers,</hi> for the moſt part are faln into that Diminution, Deprivation, or utter Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of divine Underſtanding, as that it ſeems ridiculous, or al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ogether erroneous, to tell them of a Baptiſm without Waters This of Pentecoſt was the beginning of Chriſt's Baptiſm, after he was aſcended; to this <hi>Iohn</hi> witneſſed, ſaying, Joh. 7.39. <hi>He that believeth on me</hi> (ſaid Chriſt) <hi>out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of living Water:</hi> but this ſpake he of the Spirit, which they that believe on him ſhould receive; for the holy Spirit was not yet gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe that Jeſus was not yet glorified; but as ſoon as he was glorified, then he began to let out the Power of his Spirit, even his Baptiſm, the Progreſs of Chriſt's Spiritual Baptiſm was further manifeſted, as <hi>Acts</hi> 8.17. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> laid their hands on the Believing. <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and they received the holy Spirit;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104215:16"/>after this the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> preached Chriſt to <hi>Correlius,</hi> his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and Friends, the holy Spirit fell upon them, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44. Moreover, all the Saints at <hi>Pome,</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi> in <hi>Galatia,</hi> in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> in <hi>Philippi,</hi> in <hi>Coloſs,</hi> in <hi>Pontus,</hi> in <hi>Capadocia,</hi> in <hi>Aſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> in <hi>Bithyniae,</hi> yea, and all the true Churches were in their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Meaſures Partakers of the Spirit of the Lord, and of its Baptiſm, which was and is the One Baptiſm to continue in the Church of Chriſt to the End of the World; for, in the Church, the Kingdom of Chriſt, the Apoſtles preached not up Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion nor Baptiſms, but one Circumciſion made without Hands, one Baptiſm by the Spirit into one Body, and of the Neceſſity of the Continuance of the Spirit's Baptiſm in the Church of Chriſt, let the Wiſe in Heart, who read theſe things, conſider:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Firſt,</hi> Without the Spirit's Baptiſm, none come to fee the Volumn of Corruptions in his Heart to be cancelled, none eſcape the Bondage, Slavery, Darkneſs, Defilements and Reprobate State of corrupt Nature, but who walk in the Light, wherewith Chriſt hath enlightned them, and ſubmit to its Guidance, they encreaſe in heavenly Encreaſes, they grow in the Spirit, and ſeel its Baptiſm, ſo receive a New Nature, and their Thoughts, Words and Works are ſavoury, Effects and Fruits of this new and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Nature: <hi>Peter</hi> wrote to the Saints who were Partakers of the Divine Nature, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. Here the Image of God is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, the Life of God known, Fellowſhip with him in his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Purity, yea, in his Bleſſedneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, in the beatifical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Brightneſs of his Glory, this Outward Waſhing, though a Thouſand times over, can never bring unto, but leaves the old Nature, the curſed Nature, alive and vigorous in the Creature.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Secondly,</hi> Chriſt's Baptiſm gives a New Name, who hearken to Wiſdom's Teaching, and in the Croſ of Chriſt ſee Sin cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in their Mortal Bodies, and with the Sword of the Spirit, in which the Evangelical Baptiſm is, ſee the Enmity ſlain, ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a New Name; <hi>To him that overcomes, will I give to eat of the hidden Manna; I will give him a white Stone, and in the Stone a New Name written, which no man knows ſaving he that receives it,</hi>
                              <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104215:16"/>Rev. 2.17. The Lord's Worthies are fed with Heavenly Manna, hidden from the Wiſe, from the Prudent, from the Princes of this World; they have a White Stone, in which they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, notwithſtanding all the black Coles, wherewith the world ſeeks to beſmear them; this Stone may ſpiritually be called <hi>Eben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ezer,</hi> by interpretation, <hi>the Stone of Help;</hi> theſe have a New Name, better then that of Son; and Daughters, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.5. Here, not thorough Willing, Runeing and carnal Conformity, but through Faith, the Spirit of Adoption is received, wherein Chriſt's Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſm is witneſſed; and becauſe you are Sons, God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Son, crying, <hi>Abba</hi> Father, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. God hath no Still-born Children; the Spirit of Grace is a Spirit of Supplication, to this New Name, Adoption, Cry of <hi>Abba</hi> Father, Outward Waſhing cannot bring; 'tis a rich, yea, an enriching Gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t, neceived by the Hand of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Spirit's Baptiſm muſt continue in the Church, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe no true Worſhip, without it the true Worſhip is not known; the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> acknowledging Chriſt to be a Prophet, forth-with ſhe ſought to be ſatisfied in a Caſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, concerning Worſhipping in that Mountain, or in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> Chriſt ſaid unto her, <hi>The hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>worſhip the Father; for God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in Truth,</hi> John 4.24. How? In Spirit, in Oppoſition to the carnal and idolatrous Worſhip of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who worſhipped God under the Repreſentation of a <hi>Dove:</hi> How muſt God be worſhipped? In Truth, in Oppoſition to the Typical and Figurative Worſhip of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which was but a Shadow of the Goſpel-worſhip. <hi>Paul</hi> bare record unto this Worſhip, ſaying, <hi>We are the Circumciſion, which worſhip God in the Spirit;</hi> as truly it may be ſaid, They are of Chriſts Baptiſm, who worſhip God in the Spirit; ſuch as have their Luxuriances lopped of, unruly Paſſions mortified, and caſt away as a ſuperfluou. Fore-skin; ſuch are inwardly circumciſed, inwardly baptized by the One Spirit into One Body, in which the true Worſhip is.</item>
                           <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104215:17"/>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Spirit's Baptiſm muſt continue in the Church, elſe no Tranſlation into the Kingdom of Light; 'tis through the Spirit that Entrance is known thereinto: ſo that the Doctrine of Men, who preach, reach and affirm, that <hi>sprinkling of Infants,</hi> which they call Baptiſm, <hi>makes a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>mber of Chriſt, a Child of God, an Inheritor of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> is an antichriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſetting outward Water in the place of the Spirit of Chriſt, whoſe Work only tranſlates into the Kingdom of God; ſo that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> gave thanks to God, <hi>who had delivered them from the power of Darkneſs, and had tranſlated them into the Kingdom of his dear Son,</hi> Col. 1.13. So 'tis the Power of God, who is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that tranſlates into the Kingdom of Chriſt; not <hi>extrinſecal,</hi> that is, <hi>outward water,</hi> as many erroneouſly teach; ſuch as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have a Lot herein, though through the Malice of the old Serpent, they be caſt into a dark Dungeon, yet may ſay in Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Verity, as <hi>Oscolampadius</hi> upon his Death-bed ſaid, <hi>Hic ſat lucis,</hi> Here within is plenty of Divine Light.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Baptiſm of the Spirit makes the Heart the Lord's Temple, outward Water tends not to the cleanſing of the inſide; but in the Faith the Spirit is received, which baptizes into one Body: <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Know ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you? and if any man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy; for the Temple of God is holy, which Temple ye are,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.16, 17. And this Temple is not waſhed by <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration of out ward Water, but by Chriſt's Miniſtration of the Water of Life, 'tis ſwept by the Lord's Power, 'tis beautified with Holineſs, perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſweetned with Heavenly Graces, like Inceaſe and Myrrh; the Lord will dwell in a <hi>poor,</hi> provided it be a <hi>pure Heart,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.19, 20.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The Spirit's Baptiſm enables to the Work of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Miniſtry; not Arts nor Sciences, nor Humane Endowments; not <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Ethicks, nor his Phyſicks, nor his Metaphyſicks, makes a Miniſter of Chriſt, but the Virtue of the Spirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt baptizeth; <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me</hi> (faith
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104215:17"/>Chriſt) <hi>he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel to the Poor;</hi> ſee Luke 4 18. even the Goſpel, a Word of Excellency, Authority, Certainty and Sufficiency: yea, and Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, John <hi>truly baptized with Water, but ye ſhall be baptized with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit not many dayes hence; and ye ſhall receive Power, after that the holy Spirit is come upon you; and ye ſhall be Witneſſes unto me both in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and in all</hi> Judea, <hi>and in</hi> Samaria, <hi>and unto the uttermoſt parts of the Earth,</hi> Acts 1.5, 8 Conſider this, Chriſt himſelf here calls Baptiſm of the Spirit, the Power qualifying and enabling them to be his Witneſſes. Yea, and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Holy Men of God ſpake as they were moved by the holy Spirit;</hi> they were acted, carryed out of the Dungeon of Self, whence iſſue Dreams &amp; Uncertainties, to ſay &amp; do what God would have them. Yea and on the Day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> Cloven Tongues like as of Fire, ſate upon each of the Diſciples, &amp; they were all filled with the holy Spirit, and ſpake as the Spirit gave them Utterance, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. Thus were they baptized with the Spirit, Chriſt's Baptiſm, without Water, <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm; and they were taught, both <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, to divide the Word aright, as alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, to feot it aright, to teach well, and live well; ſo that in the ſenſe of God's Innocency wrought in them, they commended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as Examples for others to follow. Yea, and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. <hi>As every man hath received the Gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, at good Stewards of the manifold Grace of God.</hi> Cloups when full pour down, Preſſes over-flow, Aromatical Trees ſweat out their precious and ſoveraign Oyls; ſo the divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly qualified Witneſſes bring out rich Treaſures, even lively and life-giving Oracles; this is through the Spirit's Baptiſm, not through Acquired Attainments and Accompliſhments.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Seventhly,</hi> The Spirit's Baptiſm brings into the true Service of God; for no Kindred, Tongue, Language, Nation, Family, Man or Woman hath an entrance into the pure Service of God; but inaſmuch as they feel the Spirit of the Lord in them, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Heaven ward; for, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>But now we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the Law, that being dead wherein we were held, that vve ſhould ſerve in newneſs of Spirit, and not in the oldneſs of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104215:18"/>the Letter,</hi> Rom. 7.6. The true ſervice of God is in the newneſs of that Spirit wherewith Chriſt baptizeth, in which man being kept, he holds conſtantly a Countermotion to the courſe of the World, to the torrent of its reigning corruptions, in this, Bodies are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented a living Sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which is their reaſonable ſervice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. a living Sacrifice inſtead of a Ram; ſinful Paſſions are here ſlain inſtead of a Goat; unclean affections, inſtead of flying Fowls; vain Thoughts, foaring Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, wandring Imaginations are ſlain; this is read in thoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that are this living Sacrifice.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eighthly,</hi> The Spirits Baptiſm makes all that partake of it one in and with Chriſt, the Head: Chriſt prayed to his Father, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>John</hi> 17.11. <hi>Holy Father, keep through thy own Name thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they may be one, as we are;</hi> he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their Oneneſs, who was heard of his Father: and Verſe 20, 21. <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo which ſhall believe on me through their word; that they all may be one, as thou, Father art in me, and I in thee, that they all may be one in us.</hi> No true Unity is out of the Lords Name; it is a ſtrong Tower, a Munition of Rocks; here ſecurity and ſafeguard is known, a ſure and ſweet Haven to have recourſe unto. After Chriſts A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion, when the Spirit was received with which Chriſt bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth, the Churches were Witneſſes of this Oneneſs; ſo <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Galatians,</hi> Chap. 3.27, 28. <hi>As many of you as have been baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt; there is neither</hi> Jew <hi>nor</hi> Greek, <hi>there is neither Bond nor Free, there is neither Male nor Female; for ye are all one in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Theſe were clothed with the Sun; theſe were beautiful through divine Ornaments: Conſider this, it was not through Water-baptiſm, but through the Spirits baptiſm, that Chriſt was put on, that Oneneſs was witneſſed. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>By one Spirit we are all baptized into one Body:</hi> So who become living Members of that Body whereof Chriſt is the Head, and feel themſelves to be of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration and Company of Believers, 'tis through the Spirits Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, not through outward Water. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>He that is joyned unto the Lord is one Spirit.</hi> Further, <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi>
                              <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104215:18"/>ſaid, <hi>Endeavouring to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace,</hi> Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>eſ 4.3. So the Unity and Unanimity is in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in which Chriſts Baptiſm is.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ninthly,</hi> The Spirits Baptiſm cleanſeth from ſin and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo fulfils inwardly what. <hi>John</hi>'s Water-baptiſm ſhadowed forth outwardly; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Know ye not that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God:</hi> it is an undefiled Inheritance, the Unclean muſt not tread on that golden Pavement. And this Apoſtle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving branched out ſuch and ſuch Workers of Iniquity, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes thus, <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi> Conſider this, when they came to be Partakers of the Spirit, to know its Baptiſin, then they came to be waſhed, ſanctified, yea, and juſtified alſo. The ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle wrote to the Saints at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Chriſt loved the Church, and gave himſelf for it, that he might ſanctiſie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of Water, by the Word, that he might preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church, without Blemiſh, Spot or Wrinkle.</hi> Now 'tis not Water without, though man were waſhed a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times therewith, but the Spirit of the Lord, wherewith Chriſt baptizeth, where a Well of Water is known ſpringing up unto eternal Life, that effects theſe things in the Church.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Tenthly,</hi> The Spirits Baptiſm makes true <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> ſo deny it, and ſweep true <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> from off the Earth. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſaid, <hi>He is not a</hi> Jew <hi>which is one outwardly, neither is that Circumciſion which is outward in the Fleſh; but he is a</hi> Jew <hi>which is one inwardly, and Circumciſion is that of the Heart, in the Spirit, and not in the Lettir, whoſe Praiſe is not of man, but of God:</hi> and as truly it may be ſaid, He is not a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that is one outwardly, neither is that Baptiſm which is outward in the Fleſh; but he is a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> which is one inwardly, and Baptiſm is that of the Heart, and not in the Letter, whoſe Praiſe is not of men, but of God: Gods Eye and Regard is to the inward <hi>Iew;</hi> and the inward Circumciſion, to the inſide <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104215:19"/>inward Baptiſm; but mans Eye and Regard who knows not the Laver of Regeneration, is to the out-ſide <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to outward Baptiſm; for of the many <hi>Eplſcopalians, Presbyterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Baptiſts,</hi> and others, who have written of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and <hi>Rantiſm,</hi> that is, <hi>dipping</hi> and <hi>ſprinkling,</hi> few if any have written of the Baptiſm of Chriſt, with the Spirit, which <hi>John the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, Chriſt, Peter, Paul, &amp;c.</hi> bare witneſs to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Virgins Birth was by the Angel unto <hi>Joſeph</hi> named <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by interpretation a <hi>Saviour;</hi> for ſaith he, <hi>He ſhall ſave his People from their Sins,</hi> Matth. 1.21. After he was baptized of <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Jordan,</hi> and the holy Spirit deſcended like a Dove upon him, from the divine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing, which came upon him, he came to be called <hi>Meſſias</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which both ſignifie <hi>anointed; Christ</hi> in <hi>Greek,</hi> as <hi>Meſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                                    <desc>•••</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi> in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſignifies <hi>anointed,</hi> becauſe he was anointed of the Father: <hi>Peter</hi> bare record of Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>God anointed</hi> Jeſus <hi>of</hi> Nazareth <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>th the holy Spirit and with Power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who were about doing good, and healing all that were oppreſſed of the Devil; for God was with him,</hi> Acts 10.38. Thus Jeſus was the Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of the Father, the Chriſt, the Meſſias, and him the High Prieſts, Prophets and ſome Kings under the Law, anointed with material Oyl, repreſented: ſo <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſignifies <hi>Anointed Ones;</hi> and none are truly <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but as they partake of the Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby they become Members of Chriſt, ſpiritually influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced by Chriſt their Head, ſo become Kings and Prieſt unto God. The Diſciples (as <hi>Acts</hi> 11.26.) were called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> firſt in <hi>Antioch,</hi> called ſo by divine Direction, as the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, ſaith <hi>Trapp</hi> on this place; the ſame Anointing which came upon Jeſus, which God gave not by meaſure unto him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3 34. the ſame Anointing is given in meaſure to the Members of Chriſt, of his Fulneſs they receive Grace for Grace; theſe are true <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> truly Anointed Ones, Hebr. 1.9. <hi>Thou haſt loved Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and hated Iniquity, therefore God, even thy God, hath anointed thee with the oyl of Gladneſs above thy Fellows.</hi> Thus real <hi>Chriſtians</hi> partake of the Anointing in their reſpective Meaſures; <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are Chriſt's, and they that are Chriſts, have crucified the Fleſh, with the Affections and Luſts, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5 24. Now ſuch as take not up the Croſs, but live in the Fleſh, in the carnalizing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104215:19"/>Principle, and in this profeſs the Scriptures, God, Chriſt, and his Ordinances, ſo become ſwel'd with hiſtorical Knowledge and Notions, and hence conclude themſelves <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> I ſay, they are not really ſo, <hi>Non re, ſed nomine Chriſtiani;</hi> Not real, but nominal <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in Name only; even as ſuch, who ſaid, <hi>they were</hi> Jews, <hi>but were not, but were the Synagogue of Satan,</hi> Rev. 2.9. The <hi>Tucks</hi> at this day ſtile themſelves <hi>Muſulmans,</hi> that is, <hi>The only true believers:</hi> The Angel of the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> was thus reproved, <hi>Thou haſt a Name that thou liveſt, but art dead,</hi> Rev. 3.1. ſo could neither praiſe nor ſerve the living God: A Ship may be called <hi>Safeguard</hi> or <hi>Goodſpeed,</hi> yet may fall into the Hand of Pirats: So ſpecious Names of <hi>Chriſtians, Believers, Church-members,</hi> advantage nothing, except the Croſs of Chriſt be borne, the Anointed received, which truly makes ſuch.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> The Spirits Baptiſm ſaves, is preſent Salvation: Now who contend for <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Miniſtry, Water-baptiſm, be it Dippers or Sprinklers, their diſcourſe is of what the Saints en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in the primitive times, and of what Salvation ſhall be in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World, not waiting for Salvation and Redemption in this Life; but they that live not the Life of the Righteous, ſhall not dye the Death of the Righteous, nor ſhall have the Reward of the Righteous: but the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> preached preſent Salvation, not by <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Baptiſm, or Water-waſhing, but by the Baptiſm of Chriſt, through the renewing of the Spirit, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5. <hi>According to his Mercy he ſaved us, by the Laver or Waſhing of Regeneration and renewing of the holy Spirit:</hi> ſo that, ſo far as a man is regenerated, renewed by the holy Spirit, which is Chriſts Baptiſm, ſo far he is ſaved from ſin, and from the Reward thereof: this Laver of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation fulfils inwardly what <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Laver and <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Jordan-waſhing ſhadowed forth outwardly: this Laver of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on removes the old Nature, and brings in a new Nature, whence iſſues new Thoughts, new Deſires, new Words and new Works; he lives, thinks, ſpeaks, works, loves and acts otherwiſe then he was wont; the Old Man and his Deeds are put off, the New Man and his Deeds are put on; Outward Water is not of that virtue to effect this in man, 'tis a Water of a more Heavenly Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104215:20"/>
                              <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Saints at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> ſaid, <hi>By Grace ye are ſaved, through Faith, and that not of your ſelves, it is the Gift of God,</hi> Epheſ. 2.8. Theſe were Witneſſes of preſent ſalvation; they had known ſtirrings in the Womb of Grace, precious unto God, had perſevered therein, ſo became God's Workmanſhip, to know the glorious Fabrick of the New Man erected in them; theſe were truly made alive unto God, who had lain rotting and ſtinking in the ſepulchre of Corruption; theſe knew Chriſt's ſpiritual Baptiſm; to this purpoſe <hi>Peter</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>are record, ſaying, <hi>The like Figure whereunto even Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave, not the putting away of the Filth of the Fleſh, but the Anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt. Peter</hi> here ſpeaks of the Ark of <hi>Noah,</hi> which by Command of the Lord was made of <hi>Gopher wood, Gen.</hi> 6.14. <hi>a kind of Cedar,</hi> ſaith the old Naturaliſt <hi>Pliny, which is not ſubject to Rottenneſs nor Worm-eatenneſs, but endures forever;</hi> a ſhadow of Chriſt Jeſus, who is the ſame to day, yeſterday and forever: ſo the Ark was a Figure of Chriſt, as it ſaved by Water outwardly: ſo Chriſt by his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, the Water of Regeneration ſaves inwardly from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of ſin, from the drowning Waves of iniquity and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Baptiſm ſaves now,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter:</hi> But what Baptiſm doth he ſpeak of? of <hi>John</hi>'s with Water, or of Chriſt's with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? the Apoſtle anſwers this, leſt any ſhould miſapprehend his ſenſe and intent, he explains himſelf evidently and fully, ſaying, <hi>Not the putting away the Filth of the Fleſh,</hi> the cleanſing of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, the effect of <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, but the Anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God, the effect of Chriſts Baptiſm in and with the Spirit, which inwardly ſaves, and brings to know and witneſs the Anſwer of a good Conſcience, by the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9, 20, 21.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Piſcator</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. gives his Teſtimony altogether anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what is here written, ſaying, <q>That the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> here aſcribes Salvation to inward Baptiſm, not to the outward, which extends no further the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the outward man.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hammond,</hi> in his Paraphraſe and Annotations on the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, ſaith on the aforeſaid place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <q>As the Ark in the Water kept men ſafe from drowning, even ſo Baptiſm doth ſave; not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104215:20"/>that of <hi>John,</hi> which cleanſed but the Body, but that which is ſignified by it, even the Baptiſm of Chriſt with the Spirit, who ſaves from ſin, and from the wages thereof.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Obj. <hi>The Baptiſm here ſpoken of by</hi> Peter, <hi>muſt needs be Water-baptiſm, becauſe he calls it a Figure; for it were not proper to call the Spirits Baptiſm a Figure.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> I confeſs, while I had recourſe only to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlations, this before was my own Objection; but conſulting the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies, the thing was cleared unto me, and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlations appeared not ſo ſound and clear as might be deſired; <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of the Preſervation of 8 Souls in the Ark by Water, ſaith, if truly tranſlated, <hi>Whoſe Antitype Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us;</hi> And what is this Antitype? even Chriſt, who baptizes with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and ſaving Baptiſm, even Chriſt, the Truth, the Sum, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the Thing ſignified by Types and Figures; Circumciſion outward was a <hi>Type,</hi> Circumciſion inward the <hi>Antitype; Moſes</hi>'s Laver a <hi>Type,</hi> the Evangelical Laver of Regeneration the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type;</hi> Anointing without a <hi>Type,</hi> Anointing within the <hi>Antitype;</hi> the Ark ſaving by Water without, a <hi>Type,</hi> Chriſt by his ſpiritual Baptiſm ſaving from the proud Billows of Wickedneſs and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs is the <hi>Antitype;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Antitype</hi> comes in lieu, ſtead, place or room of the <hi>Type:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is the Greek word, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſignifies <hi>pro</hi> as well as <hi>contra;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Conſul,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Proconſul,</hi> the Conſuls Deputy, one that officiates for him; theſe things Linguiſts underſtand: ſo that though our Engliſh Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion renders it, <hi>The like Figure whereunte even Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us;</hi> yet it is properly, truly and anſwerable to the nature of Truth rendred, <hi>Whoſe Antitype Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us, even as the Ark ſaved them of old.</hi> And if any ſay, This is but a Conceit or Whimſie of my own Head, let ſuch read <hi>Gerh.</hi> on this word, who ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in hoc loco ipſam veritatem ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat, typo ac figurae reſpondentem; that is, <hi>Antitype in this place of</hi> Peter, <hi>ſignifies the Truth it ſelf, anſwering to the Type and Figure:</hi> Truth, that is Chriſt, the Way the Truth and the Life, who baptizeth with the Spirit, and ſaves from ſin, as the Ark ſaved
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104215:21"/>outwardly. <hi>Vatabalus, Grotius, Frafmus, Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>dus, Beza, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> gave their Teſtimonies to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                     <p>If chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Scripture of <hi>Peter</hi> held out a Figure or Type, then one Type would anſwer another, which were improper; for every <hi>ſhadow, type</hi> or <hi>fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ure,</hi> rew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> as its Fulfiller. Again, it were to conclude the Goſpel-Diſpenſation, to be a ſtate of <hi>figures</hi> and <hi>ſhadows,</hi> which is the ſum and ſubſtance of all; the Kingdom of God ſtand not in Meat and Drink, but in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>, Peace and Joy in the holy Spirit, wherein the Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cry <hi>Abba</hi> Father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. Viſibles are temporal, as <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Laver-waſhing, <hi>John</hi>'s Jordan-waſhing, impoſed only until the Time of Reformation; but Inviſibles are eternal, as the Spirit of the Lord is eternal, in which Chriſts Baptiſm is; ſuch as center in temporals, that Eye being ſhut which ſees into the beginning, before the temporals, theſe are but as an Houſe without Pillars, tottering with every Blaſt, as a Ship without Anchor, toſſed with every Wave; for the Eſtabliſhment is in that which is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal.</p>
                     <p>— <hi>Whoſe Antitype Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us.</hi> By this Scripture (as all the wiſe in heart underſtand) <hi>Peter</hi> puts an End to Baptiſm of the Fleſh, as <hi>Paul</hi> did to Circumciſion of the Fleſh; for ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 2.28, 29. <hi>He is not a</hi> Jew <hi>which is one out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, neither is that Circumciſion which is outward in the Fleſh; but he is a</hi> Jew <hi>which is one inwardly, and Circumciſion is that of the Heart, in the Spirit, and not in the Letter, whoſe Praiſe is not of men, but of God:</hi> which in effect is this, In Goſpel-dayes, where all <hi>ſhadows</hi> are fulfilled, Circumciſion in the Spirit puts an end to Circumciſion in the Fleſh, in effect <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith as much of Baptiſm; Baptiſm (ſaith he) ſaves, but not that Baptiſm which puts but away the Filth of the Fleſh, but that Baptiſm of Chriſt in the Spirit, where the Anſwer of a good Conſcience is known: Yea, by this <hi>Peter</hi> intimates, that Baptiſm in the Spirit puts an to Baptiſm in the Fleſh; for of a Truth it may be ſaid, He is not a Chriſtian who is one outwardly, neither is that Baptiſm which is outward in the Fleſh; but he is a Chriſtian which is one inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Baptiſm is that of the Heart, in the Spirit, and not in the Letter, whoſe Praife is not of men, but of God: For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104215:21"/>
                        <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Laver-ſhawing, nor <hi>John</hi>'s Jordan-waſhing, could bring inward Cleanneſs and Purity of Conſcience; therefore Chriſt put an end to all outward ſhadows, figures and Types, by the Power of his Spirit inwardly effecting and fulfilling that which they in an outward manner ſhadowed out. Many bear record in Truth to the Apoſtles Teſtimony, who ſaid, <hi>The Law make nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope, by the which we draw nigh unto God,</hi> Hebr. 7.19. Here is the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Children of Light; here they are truly joynted whom Satan had diſlocated. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was not ſent to baptize, but to preach the Everlaſting Goſpel, a more weighty and ponderous Concern, he had his Call from Heaven; in writing to the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> he ſpeaks of Gifts differing, and exhorts every one to be faithful; but of baptizing with Water, he ſpeaks not; but in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places ſets up the Spirit's Baptiſm, as conducing to the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Soul.</p>
                     <p>So who are ſerious in the things of God, cannot but conclude from what is ſpoken, that the Spirit's Baptiſm is the only Baptiſm, peculiar to Goſpel-dayes, and that the continuance thereof is of abſolute neceſſity, whatever you be that deny it, to and in the Church, you ſhut out of the Church the divine Nature, the new Name, the true Worſhip, Tranſlation into the Kingdom of God, the Lords Temple, the Goſpel-Miniſtry, the true Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, true Unity, inward cleanſing, true Chriſtianity, preſent Salvation: and what is that Church, and what are the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Members thereof, that are deſtitute hereof? Out-ſides, Formaliſts, toſſed to and fro, as a Feather or Froth upon the Waves, hurried about with every Wind of Doctrine, like Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes blown into this or that ſhape at the pleaſure of mans breath; what are Profeſſors that are deſtitute of the Spirit and its Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? as hollow Trees in an old Wood, tall, but pithleſs, ſapleſs and unſound. What are theſe lifeleſs Formaliſts? as a Bulruſh, whoſe Colour is freſh, Skin ſmooth, Body knotleſs, yet nothing is within but a kind of ſpongeous unſubſtantial ſubſtance. The Swan in the Law was rejected for ſacrifice, as ſome affirm, becauſe of her Black Skin under White Feathers: thus it is with Unſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalized Out-ſide Formaliſts; their Performances, how ſpecious
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104215:22"/>ſoever, black Death reigning within, brings them not unto divine Acceptance, their moſt Religious Duties and Performances iſſue from Art and Acquired Parts, not from divine In-dwellings, who then touched with the ſenſe and poſſeſſion of the Lord's Preſence, and with the Virtue of his ſpiritual Baptiſm, can be ſilent? And not, as the Lord's Worthies contend for it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the which ſuch excellent things are ſpoken; if Chriſt muſt have preheminence in all things, if he be All in his Church, beautified out of his Wardrobe, why is Outward Water ſo much magnified in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel dayes? Chriſt is ſufficient to and in his Church, without <hi>John,</hi> though <hi>John</hi> was of uſe in his ſeaſon, to point out Chriſt to come; ſo the Baptiſm of Chriſt, without viſible Water, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in his Church, without the Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> with Water, though the Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> with Water was uſeful in its ſeaſon, being a ſhadow of a better thing to come, even of Chriſts Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm with the Spirit, who ſaid, <hi>He that believes on me, out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of living Water: but this ſpake he of the Spirit, which Believers in him ſhould receive,</hi> John 7.38, 39. So that Believers receive the Spirit; ſo Chriſts Baptiſm, living Water is to flow out of the Womb of their Souls; they know the precious Virtue thereof, its Cooling, Cleanſing, Thirſt-quenching and Fructifying Virtue; they know the fulfilling of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Laver and <hi>John</hi>'s Jordan-Waſhing in their Mortal Bodies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="assertion">
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:104215:22"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>The Fourth Aſſertion.</hi> Rantiſm, that is, Sprinkling of Infants, is a Caſe unpreſidented in the Primitive times, an Irreptitious Cuſtom, ſprung up in the Night of Apoſtacy, after the Falling Away from the Primitive Order.</head>
                     <p>I Have already ſhewed the Temporary Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> and have likewiſe ſpoken of the Baptiſm of Chriſt with the Spirit, and that this Baptiſm put an end to <hi>John</hi>'s Water-baptiſm, as to the other ſhadows; ſo that to and in the gathered Churches one Baptiſm was preached, and that by one Spirit into one Body, the ſhadow being left off: now it remains that I inform you, how Dipping, which was <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration came to be re-aſſumed, and likewiſe how Sprinkling of Infants got entrance among the Profeſſers of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſt being upon the Mount of <hi>Olives</hi> with his Diſciples, told them, <hi>that Falſe Chriſts and Falſe Prophets ſhould come,</hi> Mat. 24. which <hi>John</hi> ſeeing fulfilling and fulfilled, ſaid expreſly, <hi>they were come,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Little Children, it is the laſt time; and as ye have heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, even now are there many Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, whereby we know that it is the laſt time,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> John 2.18</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paul</hi> in the Spirit of Diſcerning ſore-ſaw and fore-told of an <hi>Apoſtacy, a Departure from the Faith, that ſeducing spirits ſhould be heeded, and Doctrines of Devils,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>John</hi> in the Spirit fore-ſaw <hi>all the world wondring after the Beaſt,</hi> Revel. 13.3. yea, and he ſaw and fore-told of <hi>a great Whore, that ſhould ſit upon many Waters, even upon Peoples, Multitudes, Nations and Tongues,</hi> Revel. 17.1, 15. yea, and he ſaw and fore-told, <hi>that all Nations, yea, Kings themſelves, ſhould be drunk with the Cup of Fornication,</hi> Revel. 18.3. Now as theſe things were in fulfilling, Darkneſs entred the Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> yea, and loſing the Virtue and Influence of the Heavenly Pearl,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104215:23"/>Chriſt in them, the End, Fulfilling, and Subſtance of all ſhadows from <hi>Abel</hi> to himſelf, then they began to re-aſſume ſhadows and figures without them, then loſing the pure Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to magnifie the Husk, loſing Chriſts ſpiritual Baptiſm, the bubling Spring of living Water, purifying inwardly; then they began to re-aſſume <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration of Water-baptiſm out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, yea, and to call it Chriſt Ordinance, then Diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded; <hi>ſome baptized or ſprinkled Old People on their Death-beds; ſome-baptized people in their more early Age, as when they were on pable of being catechized; ſome began to baptize or ſprinkle Young Children; ſome baptized or ſprinkled people after they were Dead; ſome baptized the living for the Dead; ſome baptized Children in their Mothers Womb, before they were born; ſome made the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Croſs in their Foreheads with a Burning Iron, which they called Chriſt's Baptiſm; ſome baptized themſelves every year,</hi> ſtill pretending and crying, <hi>Chriſts Ordinance. Zuinglius</hi> in his Ago taking notice of the Confuſion of men in reference to Baptiſm, bore record in this manner, ſaying, <hi>In the beginning of my Book</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I muſt ingeniouſly profeſs, that almoſt all thoſe that have undertaken to write of Baptiſm, even from the very times of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, have (which I deſire may be ſpoken with the favour of all) not in a few things erred from the Truth:</hi> Yea, and this <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> as well as they, erred alſo, the truly illuminated, Branches of the true Vine, turns from ſuch as turn from the Life of the Scriptures, the End of Shadows, into Shadows and Inventions, 'tis more honourable to joyn to the Word without Men, then to joyn to Men without the Word.</p>
                     <p>Now of the fore-mentioned Confuſion and Inventions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Baptiſm and Rantiſm, Dipping and Sprinkling, more followeth.</p>
                     <p>I profeſs, I have traced the ſteps of Antiquity, and have been diligent to ſearch out the Original of <hi>sprinkling,</hi> that if poſſible I might find him out to whom this Tradition, <hi>Rantiſm,</hi> that is, <hi>sprinkling,</hi> may cry <hi>Abba Father;</hi> and what I have found there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to relating, I freely commend to him that reads me.</p>
                     <p>I find it recorded, that about the year 230. lived one <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who was Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> in which time the foggy Exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:104215:23"/>of Darkneſs much aſcended the Hearts of the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, yea, ſo much as that Chriſt's Baptiſm in and with the ſaving Spirit, the Water of Life being much loſt within, they began exceedingly to magnifie Water without, the viſible Element, thinking Water-baptiſm ſaved, aſcribing Waſhing of Souls, Regeneration, taking away of Original Sin, freeing from Perdition, and eternal Salvation to it; yea, and in effect the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of this Doctrine remains, and in ſuch as would be accounted high Sharers in Reformation, that the thing is ſo, multitudes of Teſtimonies might be produced.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whence</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>hath Water ſo much Virtue, as that it touches the Body, and waſhes the Heart,</hi> Auguſt. in Hom. 8.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Through baptiſmal Water men paſs from Earth to Heaven,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi> de ſacramentis.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>As Water extinguiſheth, cleanſeth, and whiteneth above other Liquors, ſo in baptiſmal Water fleſhly Luſts are quenched, Sin both original and actual waſhed away, Innocency begotten,</hi> ſaith <hi>Algerus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Not particular men only, but even Councils were involved in this erroneous Conceit and Miſapprehenſion.</p>
                     <p>The Council of <hi>Florence</hi> taught, <hi>That by Baptiſm we are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually born again; and that it imprints in the Soul a Character, that is, ſome ſpiritual ſign; indeleble, that is, which cannot be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out:</hi> and further, <hi>That we are thereby made Members of Chriſt, of the Body of the Church,</hi> Summa Concil et Pontif.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Trent</hi> Council taught, <hi>That by</hi> Baptiſm <hi>we put on Chriſt, and are thoroughly made New Creatures.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Children dying without it, are by the <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Heathen,</hi> and muſt not be buried in Hollowed Mould, Church, or Church-Yard. <hi>Proteſtants</hi> dancing after the ſame Pipe, accoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſuch <hi>Heathen,</hi> and <hi>wanting their Chriſtendom,</hi> ſo bury them behind the Church, ſo called.</p>
                     <p>This ancient Error of magnifying outward Water, when the the purifying Virtue of the Water of Life was loſt, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains; 'tis read in the beginning of the old Catechiſm of preſent allowance, <hi>My Godfathers and Godmothers in my Baptiſm, wherein I was made a Member of Chriſt, a Child of God, and an Inheritor
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104215:24"/>of the Kingdom of God.</hi> Is not here unſpeakable Virtue aſcribed to baptiſmal Water.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mayer,</hi> in his Explanation of the Engliſh Catechiſm, para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſing on the before-cited words, ſaith, <hi>Outward Water makes none Partakers of ſuch Priviledges, and that the Externals of the New are of no more Vertue then the Externals of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> alledging, <hi>that in Chriſt Jeſus neither Circumciſion avails any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but a New Creature, and the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Commandments of God. Baptiſm</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>confers not Grace,</hi> ex opere operato, <hi>as the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>teaches; and if not Grace, neither thoſe precious Effects of Grace, neither is external baptiſmal Water any more effectual then the Blood of Bulls and Goats to take away ſins,</hi> Hebr. 10.4.</p>
                     <p>But to return from this digreſſion, in <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Age, though the Degeneration was not ſo great and general, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it became, yet they greatly magnified Water, and aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Salvation to it; ſo that converted Perſons deferred their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm to as near their Latter-end as they could gueſs, ſo that they might have an Evidence of the Remiſſion of their ſins all at once; they were not willing to have it before, leſt by after-ſinning they ſhould loſe their Evidence: now in propounding this End to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſometimes they deferred their Baptiſm ſo long, as that through Extremity of Sickneſs and Weakneſs, or the like, they could not be baptized, that is, <hi>dipped;</hi> then one <hi>Magnus</hi> enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of <hi>Cyprian, What they ſhould do in ſuch a caſe?</hi> Cyprian anſwered, <hi>Seeing it could not be done as it ought, without the hazard of the ſick Perſons Life, they muſt do it as well as they could, ſo that they might have the Element of Water applyed to them on their Beds, ſprinkled upon them,</hi> alledging Ez. 36. <hi>I will ſprinkle clean Water upon them, yet if they were reſtored again, they ſhould be dipped in a River.</hi> Now <hi>Cyprian</hi> allowing of <hi>ſprinkling</hi> in this caſe, people would make uſe of it in other caſes; ſee <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Epiſtle to <hi>Magnus.</hi> Here you ſee the Author of <hi>Rantiſm,</hi> that is, <hi>Sprinkling,</hi> not Chriſt, nor the Apoſtles, but <hi>Cyprian;</hi> not in the dayes of Chriſt, but ſome Two Hundred and Thirty Years after; yet not Infants, but Old People were ſprinkled. Alſo he pleads for the <hi>sprinkling</hi> of new converted Priſoners in the Priſon-houſe; by degrees they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104215:24"/>let in the Cuſtom of Sick Children, afterwards of All Children, <hi>Cypr.</hi> Lib. 4. Epiſt. 7. Magdib. pag. 126.</p>
                     <p>For further confirmation hereof, <hi>Muſculus</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Common-Places,</hi> pag. 741. <hi>Anciently very many did defer their Baptiſm to the very utmoſt term of their Life, to the end that they might depart pure and blameleſs out of this Life, and ſo they did not ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to be baptized, except in their Bed, and that by sprinkling only, in the very point of Death, that they might dye with an Evidence; for this cauſe theſe were called</hi> Clinicks, <hi>that is,</hi> Bed-rid, <hi>and</hi> Clinick Baptiſm: <hi>in this manner</hi> Conſtantine <hi>the great, the Son of</hi> Helena, <hi>a zealous Profeſſor, was baptized when about Sixty Five years old, being ſick, and dyed a few dayes after,</hi> Socrat. Scholaſt. lib. 1. cap. 26. Mark this, that in the coming in of <hi>Rantiſm,</hi> that is, ſprinkling; Old Men were ſprinkled, not Infants.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In early Ages of the Church, Baptiſm</hi> (ſaith Cave) <hi>was defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red till old Age.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Baſil</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Geſaria,</hi> though born of believing Parents, as his Father being Biſhop of <hi>Niſen,</hi> was not baptized till aged, <hi>Oſiander,</hi> Cent. 4. lib. 3.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperor, though born of Chriſtian Parents, and inſtructed in the Faith, yet was not baptized till aged, <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoria tripartita,</hi> lib. 1.</p>
                     <p>Further, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <hi>Bohemiaen</hi> Confeſſion holds out, that Baptiſm for the moſt part was adminiſtred to Men of riper years.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Alexandria</hi> the holy Scriptures were read and interpreted by the Unbaptized, as well as by them that were Baptized: Which thing plainly evidences, that they aſcribed not that vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to Sprinkling or Infants, as afterwards men did, and now do.</p>
                     <p>It was a Cuſtom among the Ancients, that they that were baptized, were baptized Naked, ſuppoſing that as they were ſtripped of their Garment, ſo by baptiſmal Water the old man, that is, in-dwelling ſin and corruption was put off, <hi>Wolfgangus Muſculus Duſanus</hi> in his Comment on the <hi>Pſalms.</hi> This Cuſtom continued very long, as Authors ſay.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They had</hi> a <hi>Cuſtom in the Primitive Church</hi> (ſaith <hi>Trapp</hi> on Col. 2.12.) <hi>that the Party to be baptized clod himſelf with old cloaths, Which he put off when he entred into the baptiſmal Water, and at his coming
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104215:25"/>out he put on new Clothes: What did they ſignifie hereby? That they conceived, that by the Virtue of baptiſmal Water, they put off the rotten Rags of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, and put on the Garment of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Salvation.</hi> Thus the Water of Life being much loſt within, which cleanſeth, waſheth, purifieth, ſanctifieth and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away Spots, Blemiſhes and ſpiritual Deformity, they aſcribed this Work to Water without.</p>
                     <p>One ſaid,
<q>
                           <l>Ardua ſacrati baptiſmatis aula coruſcat</l>
                           <l>Quo delicta Adae Chriſtus in amne lavat.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>After this it came to be conſidered, that many dyed before they became old, therefore it was decreed, That Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when growing to years of Diſcretion, ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in Chriſtian-Principles, and then baptized. <hi>Zuinglius</hi> ſaith in his Book of Articles, <hi>That Children were alwayes openly inſtructed, and when their Faith had made an impreſſion in their Hearts, and they confeſſed the ſame with their Mouthes, then were they admitted to Baptiſm.</hi> Here was Teaching before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; but now they Sprinkle Infants, and many years after teach them.</p>
                     <p>The one Baptiſm, by one Spirit into one Body, being much loſt, then they re-aſſumed <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration of Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, or an Imitation thereof. <hi>Johannes Bohemius</hi> ſaith, In time part it was the Cuſtom to adminiſter Baptiſm alone to thoſe that were inſtructed in the Faith, and were before <hi>Eaſter</hi> (ſo called) and <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> catechized, and then upon their Confeſſion they were baptized; this was done twice a year, at <hi>Eaſter</hi> (ſo called) and <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> ſuch as were baptized put on a White Garment when they came out of the Water, for the aforeſaid Reaſon, or in token of that innocent courſe of Life they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to walk in; this White Raiment, being exorcized and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffed with ſundry Ceremonies, they wore till the Sunday after <hi>Eaſter</hi> (ſo called) and on that day put it off; which Day, from thoſe White Rayments, was called <hi>Dominica in Albis,</hi> that is, The Lord's Day in White. Concerning this <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaid,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104215:25"/>
                        <q>
                           <l>Fulgentes animas veſtis quo<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> candida ſignat</l>
                           <l>Et grege de niveo gaudia paſtor habet.</l>
                        </q>
                        <q>
                           <l>White Rayments Repreſent Souls chaſt and pure;</l>
                           <l>The Shepherd for his Flock takes Gladneſs ſure.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſame Ceremony was obſerved by thoſe that were baptized at <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> ſo from their White Rayments <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> came to be called <hi>Whit ſunday,</hi> that is, <hi>White-Sonday,</hi> in Memorial or Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof: When Infants are now baptized, they have on their Heads a White Cloth, called a <hi>Chriſome, Johan. Bohemius de gentium moribus,</hi> lib. 2. <hi>Cambdens Bret.</hi> pag. 768. <hi>Cave</hi> in his <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pope <hi>Siricius,</hi> in the year of the Lord 389. decreed, <hi>That Baptiſm ſhould not be celebrated but at the aforeſaid two ſeaſons,</hi> Eaſter <hi>and</hi> Pentecoſt, Summa Concil. et Pontif.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Baptizing at theſe two ſeaſons became almoſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> ſaith Caſſander de Baptiſmo.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou haſt received after Baptiſm</hi> (ſaith Ambroſe de ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis) <hi>a White Rayment, a Token that thou haſt put off the Pleaſure of Sin, and haſt put on the chaſt or pure Rayment of Innocency.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Luther, Bullenger, Eraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>us, Ludovicus Vives, Melancton, Beza, Bucer, Auguſtine, Marlolat, Chamier, Hammond, Field, Hugo Grotius, Zuinglius, Taylor, Parens, Tertullian, Origen, Cyprian, Euſebius, Heracles, Dyonyſius, Athanaſius, Hillary, Baſil, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nazianzen, Ambroſe, Arnobius, Jerom, fourth Council of</hi> Carthage, <hi>the Council of</hi> Laodicea, <hi>the Council of</hi> Neoceſaria, <hi>Balſamon, Zo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>, Walafridus Strabo, Monſieur Daille, Beatus Rhenanus,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Book <hi>De Fide,</hi> gave in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Teſtimonies, that in the more early Ages of the Church, Repentance, Confeſſion of Faith, and Inſtruction in Chriſtian-Principles, was commended to people as the only Qualifications for Baptiſm; thoſe thus inſtructed in Chriſtian Principles were called <hi>Catechumens,</hi> ſo were admitted to Baptiſm, which Cuſtom (ſaith <hi>Zuinglius</hi>) I wiſh it were in uſe in our Age: <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and others charged their Opinions, if their Writings be not corrupted by the <hi>Index expurgatorius,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:104215:26"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the Son of the vertuous <hi>Monica,</hi> being inſtructed in the Faith, was not baptized till about the thirtieth year of his Age, as ſaith <hi>Nauclerus,</hi> in the year 301. His Mother would not have him baptized young, leſt through youthful Propenſity he ſhould fall into ſin, which after Baptiſm would be greater and more perilous, as ſhe conceived, <hi>White</hi>'s Apology for <hi>Kuſhworth</hi>'s Dialogues.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> born of Chriſtian Parents, his Father being a Biſhop, was baptized about the twentieth year of his Age, <hi>Oſiander,</hi> Cent. 4. Lib. 3.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ambro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e,</hi> born of Chriſtian Parents, remained inſtructed in Chriſtian Principles, and was unbaptized till he was choſen Biſhop of <hi>Millain,</hi> Paulinus in vita Ambroſij.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jerom,</hi> born of Chriſtian Parents, was baptized when about thirty years old, <hi>Eraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>us in vita Hieron.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> born of Chriſtian Parents, was not baptized till the one and twentieth year of his Age, <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> on Matth. 19.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nectarius</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> before he was baptized, <hi>Voſſius de baptiſmo,</hi> pag. 100.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Northumberland</hi> is a River called <hi>Glen,</hi> in which <hi>Paulinus</hi> (coming into thoſe parts with the King and Queen, and ſtaying there ſome thirty ſix dayes) baptized many, all which time he ſpent in catechizing and baptizing, being inſtructed, he baptized them in the River <hi>Glen;</hi> theſe were not Infants, neither were they ſprinkled at a Baſon, Bowl or Font, but they were return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Shadow, <hi>Camb. Brit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid, None were to be baptized, but the <hi>Catechumens,</hi> that is, ſuch as were duly inſtructed in Chriſtian Principles, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>contra Eunomium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> mentioning the Canon, pag. 238. ſaith, <q>It inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates a Practice abſolutely univerſal in the Church of interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Catechumens,</hi> concerning the Articles of their Creed, which is one Argument, that either they allowed not of Infants Baptiſm, or that they did prevaricate egregiouſly in asking Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of them, who, as themſelves well knew, were not capable of anſwering.</q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104215:26"/>
                     <p>Now, what high Thoughts they had of Baptiſm, what Virtue they aſcribed to it, how they magnified it, further appears by the Canon of a Council under Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the firſt, who put forth, that <hi>No commemoration of an holy Oblation, nor the Office of Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhould be beſtowed on thoſe</hi> Catechumens, <hi>that dyed without the Redemption of Baptiſm,</hi> Concil. Bacarenſe ſub Honorio primo, <hi>vide</hi> Summa Concil. et Pontif.</p>
                     <p>In the dayes of the Apoſtles, when the Woman was clothed with the Sun, the Church was beautified with the Garments of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs and Innocency, Satan operated to entangle them in the Net of Shadows, Elements and beggarly Rudiments, as appears by <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles to the <hi>Galatians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Colleſſians, &amp;c.</hi> Now after the Apoſtles dayes, as Satan, the old Adverſary, was more and more prevalent, ſo the purifying Faith, and the bleſſed, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive, apoſtolical Order was more and more departed from, the one Baptiſm, which is ſpiritual, was in a high meaſure loſt, then they began to re-aſſume <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration of Water-baptiſm without, or an Imitation of it, as dipping or ſprinkling Aged Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, baptizing Middle Age, Youth after they were catechized; and as Darkneſs encreaſed, Inventions were multiplyed, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Throne of the Hearts of Chriſtianity, as ſprinkling of Infants, Godfathers and Godmothers, Chriſm, Chriſoms, Fonts, &amp;c. in this Apoſtacy they aſcribed the virtue of Saving, Sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Regenerating, inward Waſhing to Baptiſmal Water with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as now, of making Members of Chriſt, Children of God, &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> aſcribed no ſuch Virtue to his Baptiſmal Water, but only uſed it as a Figure of that inward Waſhing which ſhould be witneſſed in the Church, by the Baptiſm of Chriſt in the Spirit, without Outward Water.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:104215:27"/>
                     <head>Of the Original and Progreſs of <hi>Paedo-baptiſm,</hi> rather <hi>Paedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiſm</hi> now, that is, <hi>Sprinkling of Infants.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AFter this it was conſidered, that many Infants and Children dyed before they were capable of catechizing and inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Principles of Chriſtian Religion, and being doubtful concerning the Salvation of ſuch, they wrote to <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Father, to have his Thoughts concerning the State and Caſe of ſuch as dyed unbaptized: To whom <hi>Auguſtine</hi> returned this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Infants, who whether they begin to live in the Mothers Womb, and there dye, or being born of their Mothers, depart out of the World without the Sacrament of holy Baptiſm, they are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, being guilty of Original Sin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Conſider the Fury of this Uncharitable man, how he plants his great Gun againſt innocent Children. Chriſt told certain, <hi>that they muſt become as Little Children;</hi> which implies Children to be harmleſs and innocent, elſe they could not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven: But this <hi>Auguſtine</hi> taught, that Infants born or unborn are damned if they dye without Baptiſm. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he was ſtiled, <hi>Durus pater infantum,</hi> a hard Father to Infants. Again, He aſcribes to Outward Water the waſhing away o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin and actual alſo; ſo ſets corruptible Water in the place of the Blood of Chriſt, which indeed cleanſeth from all Sin.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Caſſiodor</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. thus wrote, <hi>That in Baptiſm Original Sins and Offences are ſo cleanſed, that it reſtores us to that Purity in which</hi> Adam <hi>was created.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Conſider into what a Gulf of Error this Doctrine leads ſuch as receive it, aſcribing the cleanſing away of Sin to outward Water, yea, and that it reſtore to that Purity in which <hi>Adam</hi> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: When ſuch poyſonous Pills as theſe were ſwallowed, ſuch pernicious Doctrines credited, that Children quickened in the Womb, or brought forth, dying without Water-baptiſm, were damned; and that by Water-baptiſm they were cleanſed, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:104215:27"/>made as pure and innocent as <hi>Adam</hi> was before his Fall, from ſuch accompts as theſe the Neceſſity of Infants-Baptiſm was concluded, and the Danger without it, and the unſpeakable Benefits of it; thus were Monſters conceived &amp; brought forth out of the Womb of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and further to beget people into a Veneration &amp; Eſteem of it, it muſt have no lower Title and Denomination then of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt's Ordinance;</hi> and thoſe Scriptures which were ſpoken of Chriſt's Baptiſm in the Spirit, of the Water of Regeneration, muſt be wreſted and perverted to defend Water-Baptiſm and Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; yea, and the Doctrine of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and ſuch like, being rooted in mens Belief, Sprinkling of Infants muſt be accounted Chriſt's Ordinance, and all that deny the ſame muſt be branded as <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And that <hi>Auguſtine, Fulgentius, Leonardus Coquaeus, Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and many of the Ancients were of Opinion, <hi>That Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, born or unborn, if they dyed without Baptiſm, were damned,</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory plentifully ſhews; <hi>Auguſt. ad vicentium vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorem, Fulgentius, Leonardus Coquaeus in Auguſt. de Civit. Dei Auguſt. de fide ad Patrum Diaconum, Caſſander de baptiſme, Epitome operum Auguſtini,</hi> pag. 75.</p>
                     <p>Again, Some will have <hi>Poedo-baptiſm</hi> or <hi>Poedo-rantiſm,</hi> that is, dipping or ſprinkling of Children, to be of more Antiquity then <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> for 'tis recorded, that about the year 248. lived a Prieſt called <hi>Fidus,</hi> who willed people to baptize young Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren according to the manner of Circumciſion; about which thing <hi>Cyprian</hi> with ſixty ſix Biſhops and Elders gather'd together, ordained, <hi>That Children ſhould timely be baptized, as well before as after the eighth day.</hi> It ſeems the Doctrine of <hi>Fidus</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Dipping</hi> or <hi>Sprinkling</hi> of Children was new, and ſeemed ſtrange to <hi>Cyprian,</hi> ſeeing he would not ratifie nor confirm the ſame without the Sentence and Advice of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>y ſix Biſhops; had it been commanded by Chriſt, practiſed by the Apoſtles, and continued in Matter and Manner to <hi>Cyprian</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> dayes, there had not been a Neceſſity for the conco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>e of ſo many Biſhops concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame: and though <hi>Cyprian</hi> here enjoyned Baptizing of Children, yet a few years before, he was for the Dipping or Sprinkling of Aged People. See his Epiſtle to <hi>Magnus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:104215:28"/>
                     <p>Now <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his fellow Biſhops allowing of Childrens Baptiſm, hence it got great entrance among the Churche, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtianity; ſo that <hi>Caſſander,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Infantium baptiſmo,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Baptiſm of Infants came to be much uſed by the Fathers, who lived ſome three hundred years after the Apoſtles.</hi> He excludes it from being Chriſt's Command, or practiſed by the Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p>As the Apoſtacy was more and more manifeſted, Sun and Air, the Purity of the primitive Church, through the Smoak of the Bottomleſs Pit, darkned, then Traditions and Inventions of men were multiplyed, then the Neceſſity of Infants Baptiſm by <hi>Auguſtine, Cyprian,</hi> and ſuch like, was introduced, and by the Ratification and Enjoynment of Popes, Councils, General, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional or Provincial Synods, Kings, as abſolutely neceſſary, was ſtrengthned.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Johannes Bohemius</hi> ſaith, <q>That Baptiſm of old was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to none (unleſs upon urgent Neceſſity) but to ſuch as were before inſtructed in the Faith, and catechiſed; but when it came to be iudged Neceſſary to Everlaſting L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>fe, it was ordained that Infants ſhould be baptized, and that they ſhould have Godfathers and Godmothers, who ſhould be Sureties for Infants, and ſhould renounce the Devil in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfs, it grew to this in the <hi>Roman-Catholick-Church,</hi> that at the baptizing of a Child, the Prieſt 1. blows three times in the Infants Face; 2. he anoints his Eyes, Ears and Noſtrils with Earth moiſtned with his Spittle; 3. he names him, and marks him with the ſign of the Croſs upon his Breaſt and Back with Hallowed Oyle; 4. he dips him into the Water, or pours Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon him three times in form of a Croſs; 5. dipping his Thumb in the Holy Chriſm (as they call it) he ſigns the Childs Forehead with the ſign of the Croſs; 6. he covers him with a White Garment; 7. he puts into his Hand a Burning Candle, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Gentium moribus.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>When the primitive Purity was turned from, the one Baptiſm by the one Spirit into one Body loſt, then ſteamed ſuch like things out of the Bottomleſs Pit into the Church; and to gain Eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they muſt be ſtiled Chriſt's Commands, or at leaſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Traditions.</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:104215:28"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (as 'tis ſaid) was the firſt that preached the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Infants Baptiſm; and as Nations became drunk with the Cup of Abomination and Fornication, idolatrous and ſtrange Erroneous Doctrines ſtreamed out of Apoſtatized Chriſtendom.</p>
                     <p>About the year 402. the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council, celebrated by ninety two Biſhops, put out this Canon, <q>All that affirm that young Children receive Everlaſting Life without the Sacrament of Baptiſm, and will not that young Children newly born be baptized, to the taking away of original Sin, that they be ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematized, <hi>Magdiburg.</hi> Cent. 5.</q> This Canon then ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> had the Ratification of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third.</p>
                     <p>In the 5th General Council at <hi>Carthage,</hi> held in the year 416. 'twas decreed, <q>That whoſoever denies, that little Children by Baptiſm are freed from Perdition, and eternally ſaved, let them be accurſed.</q> Tuis was confirmed and ratified by the ſaid Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, after by Pope <hi>Zoſimus,</hi> after by Pope <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſidore</hi> ſaith, <q>If Children were not baptized, ſo thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and original Sin waſhed away, they were in a ſtate of Damnation, <hi>Madg.</hi> cent. 7.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pope <hi>Hormiſda</hi> ordained, <q>That Children, if they be weak, ſhould be baptized the ſame day in which they are born, <hi>Summa Concil. et Pontiſ</hi> And what care is taken in this Nation for weak Children, to make ſure their Chriſtendom (as they ſay) I may be ſilent.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>About the year 692. <hi>In a</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> ordained, <q>That every Infant ſhould be baptized within thirty dayes after its Birth on the Penalty of his Parents forfeiting thirty ſhillings; and if the Child dyed unbaptized, the whole Eſtate.</q> Theſe <hi>Saxons</hi> received the Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> from the mouth of <hi>Auſtine</hi> the Monk, and others.</p>
                     <p>About the year 816. the Council under <hi>Wolfred</hi> ordained, <q>That they ſhould not pour Water upon the Heads of Infants, but immerge, that is, dip them in the Font, <hi>Full.</hi> pag. 109.</q> It ſeems they were for Dipping, not for Sprinkling.</p>
                     <p>In the 9th Century it crept in, 'That in Exorciſm, the Head,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104215:29"/>Ears and Noſe ſhould be ſalted, and anointed before Baptiſm, <hi>Magd.</hi> Cent. 9.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Auguſtine's</hi> Doctrine, <hi>That Children born or unborn, were damned, if they dyed within Baptiſm,</hi> being received at a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Oracle, hence Infants Baptiſm was enjoyned by Popes, Councils and Kings, and great Virtue was aſcribed to it, as the taking away of Original Sin, and of regenerating Infants, and renewing of them, and freeing them from Perdition, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſaving them, and of making them Members of Chriſt, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> it made the Receivers as pure and innocent as <hi>Adam</hi> was before his Fall; theſe things being believed, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men became Defenders and Propogators of it, common people received it with Greedineſs: Who would refuſe an Eternal Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance tendred upon ſuch terms? Thus Ignorance &amp; Blindneſs enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtendom, the Cuſtom and idolatrous Tradition of Infants Baptiſm became ſo epidemical and general, as that in the eleventh Century it was ſcarce queſtioned; in this Age it crept in, <hi>That Salt ſhould be put into the Mouth of the Baptized,</hi> Magd. Cent. 11.</p>
                     <p>In the Diſcourſe between Dr. <hi>Harpsfield</hi> Arch-Deacon, and <hi>John Bradford</hi> Martyr, this <hi>Bradford</hi> ſaid, <hi>I dare not exclude from Chriſt all that dye without Baptiſm.</hi> He placed not Salvation in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible elementary Water; but the <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded, and thruſt the Souls of Infants that dye without it into a <hi>Limbus infantum,</hi> a place very nigh Hell, and their Bodies out of Chriſtian-burial, into an Unhallowed Place; and in this Nation, who pretend to Reformation, behind the Church (ſo called) if granted for burial to the Unbaptized, muſt be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as a Favour.</p>
                     <p>And to the Decrees of Popes, Councils and Kings, there are ſeveral wreſted Scriptures and Objections alledged for the defence and confirmation of Infants Baptiſm.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. Obj. <hi>Whole Families were baptized, ſo Children.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis written, that <hi>whole Families believed,</hi> John 4.53.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104215:29"/>Muſt it be inferred hence, that Children, not grown up to years of Diſcretion, believed; Families may be without Children, they may be grown up, or they might be newly married Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, or their Children might be dead: ſo 'tis a wild Inference to ground Infants Baptiſm on this, ſaith <hi>Optatus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">II. Obj. <hi>The Spirit accompanies Water in Baptiſm, and Water ſo accompanied is Chriſt's Baptiſm, the Spirits Baptiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture bears record againſt that; the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſell on the Apoſtles on the day of Pentecoſt; this was Chriſts Baptiſm, the Spirits Baptiſm, and here was no Water made uſe of, <hi>Acts</hi> 1, &amp; 2. yea, and in <hi>Acts</hi> 11.15. he call, the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit falling on them, the Spirits Baptiſm, without the Element of Water; as for Water, that he calls <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. Obj. <hi>Thoſe that have right to the Promiſe, they have right to the Seal thereof; but the Children of Believers have right to the Promiſe;</hi> ergo, <hi>they have right to the Seal, that is baptiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Chriſt, the Promiſe of the Father, all the Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of the Earth obtain the Bleſſing; he is alſo the Covenant of Light, given for Salvation to the Ends of the Earth, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43.6. and that ſuch as have right to the Promiſe, have right to the Seal thereof, that is a real Truth; but that Dipping or Sprinkling of Infants ſhould be the Seal of the Covenant, that I deny, as Antichriſtian: conſider, the firſt Covenant ſtood in Meats and Drinks, and divers Baptiſms, that is, Waſhings; it had a temporary Seal, to wit, Circumciſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. but the New Covenant, Chriſt Jeſus, the great Promiſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath a ſpiritual, yea, an eternal Seal: this is my poſitive Affirmation in this caſe, that the Old Covenant ſtanding in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, had an outward Seal; but the new Covenant, the Promiſe of the Father, hath a ſpiritual Seal: <hi>Paul</hi> a Witneſs of Chriſt, the <hi>new covenant,</hi> the great Promiſe of the Father, in writing to the Saints at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he teſtified on their behalf, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>After that ye believed, ye were ſcaled with the holy Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:104215:30"/>Epheſ. 1.13. He calls the Spirit the Seal of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Chriſt, the Promiſe of the Father, not Baptiſm not Rantiſm, <hi>dipping</hi> or <hi>ſprinkling.</hi> Further, he exhorted them in theſe words, <hi>Grieve not the holy Spirit, whereby ye are ſealed to the Day of Redemption,</hi> Epheſ. 4.30. He preaches up the Spirit to be the Evangelical Seal of the New Covenant, the Promiſe of the Father; ſo who preach up Water-baptiſm to be the Seal, they oppoſe the Apoſtles Teſtimony, deny the Lord's Privy and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Seal, and introduce another of mans making; the ſealed are the Lord's Excellent Ones, his Worthies. And as for that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>The Promiſe is unto you, and to your Children, unto all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord ſhall call.</hi> This makes nothing for Water-baptiſm or Rantiſm to be the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Seal: <hi>Peter</hi> told the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>the Promiſe was to them, to their Children, yea, to all the called of the Lord.</hi> Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Water was not the Promiſe which they were to wait for, but a thing of a more Heavenly Nature. Chriſt told the <hi>Jews, John</hi> 8.39. <hi>If ye were</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Children, ye would do the works of</hi> Abraham: ſo that ſuch were the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and had right to the Promiſe, who were found doing the Works of <hi>Abraham:</hi> yea, and the Apoſtle told the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that <hi>they which were of Faith, were the Children of</hi> Abraham, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7. ſuch Children as theſe have right to the Promiſe, and know the Seal thereof.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. Obj. <hi>Infants-baptiſm is an ancient Cuſtom, ſo to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> The antiquity of a humane Tradition proves it not to be of divine Inſtitution; the ſpreading or over-ſpreading of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, proves it not to be Soundneſs; the Entrance of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation thruſts out humane Inventions, old as well as new: what Chriſt received of his Father, that he taught his Diſciples, Apoſtles; what the Apoſtles received from Chriſt, the treaſury of Wiſdom and Knowledge, that they taught to and in the Churches, and the ſame was to be committed and commended to faithful men in the Faith; the Tongue of the Learned was their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:104215:30"/>All to them, and in them; and in this Faith that Tongue was kept ſilent, which afterward brought the Darkneſs into the Church: in the Eye of divine Illumination we ſee to before <hi>Auguſt in</hi> was, or <hi>Cyprian</hi> was, or Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third was, who (as 'tis ſaid) firſt eſtabliſhed Infants-baptiſm, by ratifying the Canon of the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council; by this Eye we ſee and feel to the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Order, before the Apoſtacy was, Chriſt, the Apoſtles and primitive Church, in the Beauty of Heavenly Virginity, taught no ſuch thing, as <hi>dipping or ſpriekling of Infants,</hi> and in the Faith the primitive Order is to be preſſed after &amp; contended for, &amp; the Smoak of the Pit, Inventions, Traditions and Idolatious Cuſtoms, inconſiſtent with the living &amp; Life-giving Truth are to be warred againſt: <hi>Id verum quod prius, prius quod ab initio, ab initio quod ab Apoſtolis,</hi> Tertul. contra Marcion, lib. 4. That is Truth, that was firſt; that was firſt, which was from the beginning; which was from the beginning, which was from the Apoſtles; what the Apoſtles preached, that they received from Chriſt, who is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Firſt and the Laſt, the Beginning and the End, glorified with the Father before the Foundation of the World. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo</hi> teſtified, ſaying, <hi>Cuſtom is not to be preferred before Truth, but ought to give place to the Truth:</hi> but who plead for Infants-baptiſm or Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, they would keep Cuſtom in the Throne, and exclude Truth. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> bare Teſtimony, ſaying, <q>Cuſtom crept in among ſome people, ought not to hinder Truths pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing and overcoming; for Cuſtom without Truth is nothing but ancient Error, wherefore forſaking Error, let us purſue the Truth.</q> Theſe two ſaid well, though true it is, as their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings evidently demonſtrate, they were guilty of mingling their <hi>traditions, inventions</hi> and <hi>imaginations</hi> with the Doctrine of Chriſt and of the Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p n="5">V. Obj. <hi>'Tis ſaid, Except a man be born of Water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God,</hi> John 3.5. <hi>deth not this perpetuate Infants-baptiſm?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt gave no command for Infants-baptiſm, neither
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:104215:31"/>did the Apoſtles practiſe any ſuch thing; whoever alledge this, or any other Scripture for it, they uſe the Scriptures as Torturers, who putting innocent men upon the Rack, ſo force them to ſpeak that which they never thought; ſuch are theſe, who wreſt the Scriptures, to draw a ſenſe out of them which the holy Spirit never intended, ſo tortures and perverts them as to make them ſpeak for maintaining thoſe things which were not commanded nor ſpoken of in thoſe dayes wherein the Scriptures were given forth. After the Apoſtles dayes Satan made an Encroachment upon the Garden of the Lord, Earthly Exaltations of Darkneſs fumed into the Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> then their Judgment became carnal, and being not able to ſavour divine things, they wreſted thoſe Scriptures which ſpoke of the Water of Life, and applyed them to outward Water, aſcribing inward Waſhing and Regeneration thereto, whenas indeed external Water can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute nothing thereunto in this place. Chriſt preached unto <hi>Nicodemus</hi> the Neceſſity of Regeneration, and informed him how it was brought forth, not by outward Water, which can reach no further then outward things, but by a Water able to renew a man, to make him a New, Holy and Heavenly Creature, to diſſolve the rotten and loathſom Fabrick of unrenewed, untranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed man, where Belial is King, and to erect a Building in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs, where Chriſt is Monarch, ſole Lord. Other Scriptures give witneſs to this, as <hi>John</hi> 4.10. Chriſt ſaid to the Woman of <hi>Samaria, If thou knew the Gift of God, &amp;c. thou wouldſt have asked of him, and he would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this living Water.</hi> Mark, here is a Living Water, a Life-giving Water, effecting a living Work; and this all the Re-born know. Further, ſaith Chriſt, Verſ. 14. <hi>The Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall be in him a Well of Water, springing up unto Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 7.38, 39. <hi>He that believeth on we, out of his belly ſhall flow Revers of living Water,</hi> which Believers in him ſhould receive; there is a living Water producing a Work of Wonder in the Bodies of men, making all things new; this fulfils inwardly what Water elementary ſhadowed out out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, which cools, cleanſes quenches the Thirſt, makes fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful outwardly.</p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104215:31"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Piſcator</hi> on this <hi>John</hi> 3.5. ſaith very evidently, <hi>Seeing that without this Water, whereof Chriſt ſpake to</hi> Nicodemus, <hi>no man can attain unto eternal Life, it follows, that Chriſt spake not of Baptiſmal Water. Lombard, Voſſius,</hi> yea, a Cloud of Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have ſhowred down Teſtimonies to the ſame purpoſe; but if notwithſtanding all this, thou wilt have <hi>John</hi> 3, 5. to ſpeak of material Water, then <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>He ſhall baptize you with the holy Spirit and with fire,</hi> muſt be underſtood of material Fire, then outward Fire muſt be uſed in Baptiſm, which would be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Abſurdity, and a ſtrange Doctrine; Water and Fire are in theſe places added, to ſhew the effectual Operation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, working that inwardly which Fire and Water repreſent out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, as many have obſerved; born of Water and of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or of Water which is the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 7.38, 9. as <hi>Piſcator</hi> obſerves: ſo baptized with the holy Spirit and with Fire, baptized with the holy Spirit, which is Fire, a Coal from the Lord's Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, giving light to the inward man, ſpiritualizing him, chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him into the divine Image, from Glory to Glory, elevates and carries the Renewed Heaven-ward, purifying from the droſs of Sin, Polutious and Defilements, uniting to the Called, Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Choſen, ſeparating from the World, in a word, who dwell in the Light of Grace, theſe more and more receive the Spirit, in which Chriſt's Baptiſm is a Coal from the Lord's Altar, operating inwardly as elementary Fire outwardly.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of Children in the Womb Baptized.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Satan, the grand Adverſary, by Helliſh Suggeſtions, Wicked Temptations, Unclean Injections, by little and little after the primitive Times disjoynted, and as I may fay, diſ-ſpirited many, ſo that the pure ſerious Worſhip in Spirit and in Truth came by little and little to be departed from, and a Will-Worſhip clouded with Ceremonies, Shadows, Traditions, Inventions of men came to be eſtabliſhed, ſo that <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in his day taught, <hi>That Children born or unborn, if quickened in the Womb, were Damned, if they dyed without baptiſm:</hi> hence the Neceſſity of baptizing Infants was concluded, as before I have touched. Now it being obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:104215:32"/>that many Children dyed in the Womb, and according to Father <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Doctrine ſuch were damned, if unbaptized; the conſideration of this ſet them to ſeek a Remedy for that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, and none could be found, except the Child in the Womb could be baptized; but if it might, then all was well: in order to this concern, a great Queſtion was propounded, <hi>An pueri in utero poſſint baptizari, it a ſalvari;</hi> that is, <hi>Whether Children in the Womb could be baptized, ſo ſaved, yea or nay?</hi> This was look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as a Myſterious Queſtion, and neceſſary to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and it ſet the moſt curious Wits on work, and out of the Magazine of carnal Reaſoning came this Concluſion:</p>
                     <p>If a Quickened Child in the Mothers Womb ſhall be in danger to dye, thorough the Weakneſs of the Mother or of the Child, or thorough hard Labour, let them bleſs or pray for the Child, and let them ſtrengthen the Mothers Womb, let them commend the Child to God, with Deſires to baptize it, and can proteſt, ſaying, The Fault is not in them why that Child is not baptized; the Obſervation of theſe Ceremonies upon the Child's account, was judged equivalent to Baptiſm, and the Child concluded to be ſaved thorough its Parents Belief, <hi>Caſſander de baptiſmo.</hi> Thus after the ingreſs of Apoſtacy, multitudes of Inventions were brought into the Church, and to the end they might have favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Entertainment, they were ſtiled <hi>Decent,</hi> and <hi>Doctrines of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>Apoſtolical Traditions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Concerning Baptizing of the Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thorough the Smoak of the Apoſtacy after the Apoſtles dayes, ſuch was the Depravation of mens Underſtandings, as that they aſcribed the virtue of Renovation, Regeneration and Eternal Salvation to Baptiſmal Water; yea, and not a few concluded it effectual not only for the Living, but alſo for the Dead, ſo that the <hi>Cataphygians</hi> and <hi>Montaniſts</hi> baptized the Dead Bodies of men, as ſaith <hi>Philaſtrius,</hi> and <hi>Georgius Ederus</hi> in his <hi>Mataeologia haereticorum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There were ſome (ſaith <hi>Sparke</hi>) that baptized the Dead, and put the Sacramental-Bread in their Mouths, as their <hi>Viaticum,</hi>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:104215:32"/>udging it better to have ſuch a neceſſary Ordinance by Proxy then altogether to go without it.</p>
                     <p>A Child that dyed unbaptized was taken up and Chriſtened (as 'tis ſaid) and had his Fathers Name given him, <hi>Magd.</hi> Cent. 7.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Concerning Baptizing the Living for the Dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thorough the Apoſtacy many fell into a dead Lethargy (as I may ſay) into a ſpiritual Sleepineſs, Drowſineſs and Forgetfulneſs, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, who forgot the Lord dayes without number, a Cuſtom crept in among the <hi>Marcionites</hi> and <hi>Cerinthians,</hi> that when any <hi>Catechumeniſt</hi> dyed without Baptiſm, that is, ſuch a one as had been inſtructed in the Principles of Chriſtianity, ſome living Perſon was placed under the Bed of the Deceaſed, then the Prieſt came unto the Deceaſed Party, ſaying, <hi>Deſireſt thou to be baptized?</hi> the Dead Man replying nothing, the Party under the Bed anſwered for it, ſaying, <hi>I would be baptized:</hi> thus they baptized him for the Dead, as if they acted a Play upon a Stage, <hi>Tertull. Epiphan. de Cerinth. haereſ. Goodwins Roman &amp; Jewiſh Antiquities.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſaid, <hi>If the Dead riſe not at all, why are they then baptized for the Dead?</hi> 1 Cor. 15.29. a Cuſtom (ſaith <hi>Piſcator</hi> on this place) not univerſal, nor taken up in all Churches, nor among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> is here noted. A Cuſtom (ſaith this <hi>Piſcator</hi>) ſprung up among the ancient <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> of being baptized at or over the Graves of the Dead of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, to teſtifie (ſaith he) that with Chriſt they were dead to ſin, and ready to dye for him, &amp;c. But the Churches who bare about in their mortal Bodies the Dying of the Lord Jeſus, ſo came to witneſs his Life manifeſt in them, they knew the Ground of Rudiments and beggarly Elements caſt out, the End of Shadows and Figures manifeſted, in which they left off <hi>John</hi>'s typical Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm without, and all other irrePtitious Cuſtoms and Confuſions about the ſame.</p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:104215:33"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of an Annual Baptiſm, that is, of ſuch as Baptize themſelves every Year.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Habbaſines,</hi> a kind of mongrel Chriſtians in <hi>Affrica,</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize themſelves every year on the day of <hi>Epiphany,</hi> ſo called, in Lakes or Ponds, thereby to keep a Memorial of Chriſts Baptiſm in <hi>Jordan,</hi> which was performed on the aforeſaid day, as many of the Ancients conjectured, <hi>Trapp</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of Outward Fire uſed in Baptiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Apoſtacy prevailed with and in the Church as a Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon a Mortal Body, which weakens the Body by little and little, cauſeth Leanneſs, and turns the Body to the Duſt; ſo the Apoſtacy crept in by little and little, the Croſs of Chriſt being turned from, Weakneſs followed, ſpiritual Leanneſs; that was loſt which opens Scriptures, and fulfils them in men; ſo <hi>conceits, conceivings, miſ-apprehenſions, miſ-interpretations</hi> got place, as from that Scripture, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. <hi>He ſhall baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire;</hi> a People called <hi>Jacobites,</hi> from one <hi>Jacobus Syrus</hi> their Leader, a kind of mongrel Chriſtians in <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſign their Children many in the Face, ſome in the Arm, with the ſign of the Croſs, imprinted with an hot burning Iron, at or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſm, alledging the aforeſaid Scripture, <hi>Concil. Cacka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuſe</hi> 2. <hi>Can.</hi> 34, 35. <hi>Trapp on Acts</hi> 8.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of Fonts, and their Riſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Some Authors mention, that when firſt they began to confer upon Infants the Tradition of Baptiſm, they dipped them in Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers or Fountains quarterly; but in Winter the ſeaſon being cold, and Children tender, Fonts were invented, and Children dipped or ſprinkled thereat.</p>
                     <p>There is a Book, called, <hi>A View of the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Law,</hi> written by one Sr. <hi>Thomas Ridley,</hi> wherein is written, that <q>The Rites of Baptiſm in the primitive Times were perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104215:33"/>in Rivers and Fountains, and this manner of baptizing (ſaith he) 'the ancient Church entertained from the Example of Chriſt, who was baptized of <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Jordan;</hi> in thoſe Ages (ſaith he) there were no Fonts.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Further (ſaith he) in the dayes we now live in, we have no other remainder of the Rite of baptizing in Rivers and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains then the very Name; hence it is (ſaith he) that the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels containing Baptiſmal Water are called <hi>Fonts,</hi> from the Latin word <hi>Fontes,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Fountains.</hi>
                        </q> Conſider, he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges a great Degeneration from the Primitive Order.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Further (ſaith he) The Cuſtom of Dipping in Rivers and Fountains being left off, Fonts were erected in private Houſes.</q> Thus Invention followed Invention, as Wave after Wave.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Further (ſaith he) Becauſe of the violent Perſecution of thoſe dayes, they were debarred of that Convenience, and had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Woods, and ſuch like places, where they had ſuch Baptiſterials as Fonts, with them, as they could.</q>
                        <hi>Mede</hi> ſaith the ſame.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>But in more peaceable Times (ſaith he) they drew nearer, and ſet their Fonts a little diſtant from their Churches, ſo called; after they obtained to ſet them in Church-Porches, and at laſt got them into the Church.</q> As a Cloud by the Winds, ſo 'twas toſſed from place to place.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Further (he ſaith) that at the firſt they were not placed in every Church, but in Cities, and that in the Mother Church, ſo called; and why in the Mother Church? becauſe (ſaith he) as people in their Mothers Wombs are born men, ſo in the Fonts of Baptiſm, as in the Churches Womb, men are born Chriſtians.</q> Here Regeneration is aſcribed to Font-Water, an Antichriſtian Doctrine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>But in ſucceeding times (ſaith he) it being conſidered, that the Mother Church, ſo called, was far off Towns and Villages, and that in Winter ſeaſon people could not well repair thither, the Biſhop took occaſion to transfer the Rite of Baptiſm and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial to the Rural Churches, ſo called, together with the Rite of Tythe, ſo made Parochial Churches.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Further (he ſaith) That in Pariſhes, ſome living remote from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104215:34"/>the Church, it was permitted them, to build in or nigh their Houſes a Private Oratory, reſerving for the moſt part the Rite of Sepulture and Baptiſm to the Pariſh Church; yea, and on high dayes (ſo called) they were to repare to the Pariſh Church.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>In after Times theſe Oratories were called <hi>Chappels,</hi> and ſuch as exerciſed the Miniſterial Function in them, were called <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, Tho. Ridley.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Fonts of old were adorned with Pictures of Holy Men, to the end that ſuch as were baptized might have before their Eyes whoſe Deeds they were to imitates, as ſaith <hi>Pontius Paulinus</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Severus.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of Godfathers and Godmothers, and Goſſips, ſo called; and the word</hi> Goſſip <hi>interpreted and explained.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Faith and Repentance were the Qualifications of ſuch who were admitted to <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, the outward Cleanſing, a ſhadow of Chriſt's Baptiſm, the Laver of Regeneration, Waſhing inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where the pure and undefiled Religion is known; <hi>John</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized not Infants, Sureties to engage for Infants Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance when at years of Diſcretion had not allowance in his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; when thorough the ingreſs of Apoſtacy the ſaving ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Baptiſm was loſt, the ſhadow got entertainment in the Church; as the corruptible earthly part prevailed within, then men grew irreligious; then credens being given to <hi>Auguſtins</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and others, <hi>That Children born or unborn were Damned, of they dyed unbaptized,</hi> hence the Neceſſity of Infants Baptiſm was concluded, and Church-men became Defenders and Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators of it: now they being conſcious, that Children knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Faith and Repentance, Qualifications for <hi>John</hi>'s Water-baptiſm, through the Door of this conſideration crept in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers to be Sureties for Infants, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Devil in their behalfs, and to Promiſe and Vow, that when thoſe Infants are grown up to years of Diſcretion, they ſhall both believe and repent, a thing not heeded by one of many, though formerly promiſed. See more of this in the old Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:104215:34"/>
                     <p>Pope <hi>Higinus</hi> ordained, <hi>That at the leaſt one Godfather or one Godmother ſhould be concerned at Baptiſm,</hi> Platina de vitis Pontif. but for every male Child (as 'tis now enjoyned) two Godfathers and one Godmother, and for every female Child two Godmothers and one Godfather are in this Nation required. About the year 680. Godfathers and Godmothers, ſo called, began to be uſed to Men of mature age; <hi>Wolphere</hi> the <hi>Mercian</hi> King was Godfather unto <hi>Edelwalch</hi> King of the <hi>South-Saxons,</hi> and this (ſaith my Author) was faſhionable in that Age, that ſuch being baptized, ſhould walk worthy of their Profeſſion, were it but to ſave their Friends Reputation, who had undertaken for their Sincerity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>Fuller</hi> pag. 89. Great Virtue in idolatrous Times was aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to Water-baptiſm, as is more fully handled before, to which the Teſtimony of <hi>venerable Bede,</hi> ſo called, hold out in his <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtory</hi> may be added, who ſaid, <hi>An ignorant Infant is ſaved in Baptiſm, thorough the Faith of its Parents and Godfather:</hi> a Teſtimony ſavouring of a carnal mind.</p>
                     <p>As for Goſſips, I have obſerved, that our Anceſtors underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a ſpiritual affinity or aliance (as they ſuppoſed) to grow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and ſuch as undertook for their Children in Baptiſm, called each other by the Name of <hi>Goſſip,</hi> which is as much as <hi>akin through God;</hi> and the Child called ſuch his <hi>Godfather</hi> or <hi>Godmother;</hi> the word <hi>Goſſip</hi> is derived from the <hi>Saxon</hi> word <hi>Godſib,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>affinity</hi> or <hi>alliance in God; Sibbe</hi> in the <hi>Saxon</hi> Tongue ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>affinity, alliance:</hi> as for a ſhe Goſſip the <hi>Belga</hi> called ſuch a one <hi>Ghemoeder,</hi> which is compounded of <hi>Ghe</hi> with, and <hi>moeder</hi> Mother: ſuch a one in the northern parts is uſually called a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother:</hi> for further confirmation of this thing, it was ordained in the ſeventh Century, <hi>That no Goſſips might Marry together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the spiritual Affinity and Relation they had contratcted at the Font,</hi> Madg. pag. 147.</p>
                     <p>In the tenth Century it crept in, <hi>That Goſſips were to put on white Garments as well as the Prieſts and the Baptized,</hi> Madg. Cent. 10. That is, at or about the baptizing of any one, both Prieſt, Goſſips, and the Party baptized put on White Garments.</p>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:104215:35"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of the Chriſom.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Of old the Cuſtom was (when the Earthly Mind turned to Earthly Rudiments and Elements) to baptize none till at years of Diſcretion, and the Baptized for certain dayes put on a white Garment; in Imitation hereof, when Infants are now baptized, they have on their Heads a White Cloth, called a <hi>Chriſom;</hi> why called a <hi>Chriſom?</hi> becauſe a white Cloth, at the firſt Inſtitution of it, was put upon a Childs Head, newly anointed with <hi>Chriſom,</hi> a hallowed Oyntment among <hi>Papiſts,</hi> after Baptiſm; ſo from this Oyntment, this Chriſom, the White Cloth, as 'tis ſaid, was called <hi>Chriſom;</hi> now 'tis taken for the White Cloth put upon a Child newly chriſtned (as 'tis called) in token of its Baptiſm; and its uſually brought to the Church, ſo called, at the day of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Woman, and pinned behind her Head; and in many places it is beſtowed upon the Prieſt; and in ſome places Money inſtead thereof.</p>
                     <p>Thus the In-dwellings of Truth being loſt, and turned from, after the primitive times, <hi>ceremonies, inventions, cuſtoms, human traditions,</hi> as <hi>Sprinkling of Infants, Godfathers, Godmothers, Goſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ps, Gommothers, Chriſom, Chriſoms, Sign of the Croſs, &amp;c.</hi> ſprung up among the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, as Weeds in untilled Grounds, yet to gain acceptance they are ſtiled by many <hi>Commands of Chriſt,</hi> or at the leaſt <hi>Apoſtolical Traditions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now after Rantiſm, that is, <hi>ſprinkling of Infants,</hi> was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into the Churches as a Doctrine meet to be obſerved, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Supream Authorities and Church-Liturgies in divers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries commending and commanding it, hence the Clergy, ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, judged themſelves concerned to propogate and defend the ſame, it being that Nonconformity is not the Way to Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yet in divers Ages, ſeveral who had Glimpſes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Light in them, queſtioned <hi>Infants-baptiſm,</hi> yea, and eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it as Counterfeit Coyn, as ſuch may ſee who trace the ſteps of Eccleſiaſtical Writers, ſome of whoſe Teſtimonies I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tertullian</hi> (as 'tis ſaid) oppoſed ſome Introducers of Infants<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104215:35"/>ſaying, <q>That Confeſſion of Sins, Faith, Repentance and Renouncing of the Devil, was required of the Baptized, which Infants are not capable of, <hi>Tertull. de baptiſmo.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Walafridus Strab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> who lived about the year 840. in his Book of Church Affairs, chap. 26. ſaid to this purpoſe, <q>That in the early Ages of the Church, Baptiſm was adminiſtred on the <hi>Adul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> only.</q> When the Subſtance, ſay I, was turned from, then they re-aſſumed the Shadows. <q>But afterwards (ſaith he) Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans underſtanding Original Sin, and left their Children ſhould periſh, without any Means of Grace, they began to baptize them by the Decree of the Council of <hi>Africa,</hi> and then God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers were invented.</q> This, I ſay, is carnal Reaſoning, and charging the Apoſtles of Chriſt, as not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Original Sin, or as denying Means of Grace to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but I ſay, ſuch as reaſon thus, they reject the Lord's means of Increaſe in Grace, and entertain Inventions of men in place thereof.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zuing lius,</hi> ſpeaking of Infants-baptiſm, ſaith, <q>There is no plain words of Scripture where the ſame is commanded.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Magdiburgenſes</hi> in their learned Hiſtory tell us, <q>That as to the baptizing of Infants, they read of no Example in the Scriptures, <hi>Cent.</hi> 1. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2.</q> They alſo therein declare againſt conſecrating of Water before Baptiſm, as alſo againſt Fonts, Baptiſterions, and againſt baptizing at two times in the year, <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide,</hi> ſo called, againſt Goſſips or Sureties for the Adult and Infant, giving of Names in Baptiſm, Exorciſms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſms or Anointing, Conſignations, that is, Sign of the Croſs, Albs, Salt, Spittle, giving or receiving of Gifts, Confirmation of Biſhoping; theſe things were not in primitive Times, but ſteamed in as the Smoak aroſe out of the Bottomleſs Pit, <hi>Magdib-Cent.</hi> 1. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bellarmine, de baptiſmo,</hi> ſaith, <q>That in Scripture there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Command nor Example for Infants-baptiſm; but he refers it to the immaginary Catalogue of Apoſtolical Traditions.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Beringarius</hi> with the Biſhop <hi>Bruno</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> gave publick Teſtimony againſt Infants-Baptiſm, which Doctrine ſpread through <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> Bar. Ann. 1050. Hence they
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104215:36"/>were called <hi>Beringarians</hi> and <hi>Waldenſes;</hi> they teſtified alſo againſt the Real Preſence, <hi>Magd. cent.</hi> 11.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Peter de Bruſius</hi> taught againſt Infants-baptiſm, Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, praying for the Dead, for which Teſtimony he was burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Death, <hi>Bar. Ann.</hi> 1116.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Arnaldus</hi> taught againſt Infants-baptiſm, Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>Bar. Ann.</hi> 1116.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Peter Abailardus</hi> oppoſed Infants-baptiſm, ſo did many of the Clergy; this <hi>Abailardus</hi> was burned to Aſhes at <hi>Rome</hi> for his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony.</p>
                     <p>In the year 1176. a People was raiſed up in the Province of <hi>Albi,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> who preached, <hi>That Infants-baptiſm was not neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> Bar. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 310.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith expreſly, <hi>That Infants-baptiſm is not mentioned by any of the Evangeliſts,</hi> Inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 16.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They that baptize Children</hi> (ſaith Taylor) <hi>make Baptiſm to be wholely an outward Duty, a carnal Ordinance, it makes us be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Shadows, and to relinquiſh the Subſtance and Spirituality of the Goſpel,</hi> pag. 242.</p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Jerom Taylor</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Parents of</hi> Auguſtin, Jerom <hi>and</hi> Ambroſe, <hi>though</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>did not baptize their Children till aged; which thing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is very effectual for deſtroying the ſuppoſed Neceſſity of derivation of Infants-baptiſm from the Apoſtles,</hi> Lib. proph. pag. 239.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Luther in Poſtill.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Young Children hear not, ſo if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand be followed, they are not to be baptized.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> in his Book of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Church,</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is no where expreſſed in the Apoſtolical Writings, that they baptized Children.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bucer</hi> upon <hi>Matthew</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Chriſt no where commanded to baptize Infants.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Staphil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> in his <hi>Epitome,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That it is not expreſſed in holy Scriptures, that Young Children ſhould be baptized.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chocleus</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Jeſus took a Child, &amp;c. but he thinks he did not baptize it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Melancton,</hi> in his Treatiſe concerning <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That there is no plain Commandment in the Scriptures, that Children ſhould be baptized.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:104215:36"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Daniel Rogers</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconvinced by Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture, that Infants ſhould be baptized,</hi> De bapt. part. 29.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Baxter,</hi> though much for Infants-baptiſm, yet in pag 3. he confeſſes, <hi>That Infants-baptiſm is not plainly determined in the Scriptures.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> ſaith, <q>It is againſt the perpetual Analogy of Chriſts Doctrine to baptize Infants. Saying further, 'That Chriſt gave no Command for the ſame, neither did he or his Apoſtles bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize any of them, <hi>lib.. proph.</hi> pag. 239.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Further, he ſaith in pag. 237. of the ſame Book, <q>As there was no Command for Infants-baptiſm, ſo the Neceſſity of it was not determined in the Church, till the Canon made by the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levitan</hi> Council, a Provincial in <hi>Affrica.</hi> Some I grant (ſaith he) uſed it before this time in <hi>Affrica,</hi> having good Thoughts of it, yet none of them pretended it to be neceſſary, nor a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Precept, and for every Ordinance the Inſtitution is to be eyed, and neither to be ſtretched under, nor drawn narrower then the Lord hath made it.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have read of a great <hi>Papiſt</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> who going to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about Infants-baptiſm, told his Friend, <hi>He was going to hear a Miracle,</hi> viz. <hi>Infants-baptiſm to be proved by Scriptures.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Oxford</hi> Divines, in a Convocation held in the year 1647. ſaid, <hi>That without the conſentaneous Judgment and Practice of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, they ſhould be at a loſs when they are called upon for Proof in the Point of Infants-baptiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eccius</hi> acknowledges, <hi>That Infants-baptiſm is not clear from the Scripture,</hi> ſee his <hi>Enchiridion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Monſieur Daille,</hi> a learned <hi>Frenchman,</hi> a great Searcher into Antiquities, ſaid, <hi>That in ancient times they often deferred the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Infants,</hi> and produces many Examples: <hi>but whence is it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the very mentioning hereof is ſcarce to be endured at this day?</hi> Lib. 2. pag. 149.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Claudius Eſpontius,</hi> Biſhop, ordained at a Council at <hi>Pyſoy</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> about the year 1500. <hi>That Infants-baptiſm ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by Tradition, becauſe it could not be proved a Command of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Long Parliament, which ſate in the year 1647. in their
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104215:37"/>Declaration in Anſwer to the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners, declared thus, <hi>The Opinion touching the Baptizing of Infants is ſuch, wherein former Ages as well as this, learned and godly Men have differed both in Opinion and Practice; and</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>herein we hold it fit, that men ſhould be convinced by the Word of God, with Gentleneſs and Reaſon, and not be beaten out by Force and Violence.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is no ſmall Evidence</hi> (ſaith Hugo Grotius on Matth. 19.) <hi>tho Baptiſm of Infants for many Hundred Years was not ordinary in the Church, becauſe</hi> Conſtantine <hi>the Great, the Son of</hi> Helena <hi>a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>was not baptized till aged.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By what hath been ſpoken, the Sober mind may underſtand, that ſuch as dip people are relapſed into the Shadow, <hi>John</hi>'s tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary Baptiſm, and not confirmed in the one Baptiſm, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cleanſing, the Spirits Baptiſm into one Body, and that ſuch as rantize or ſprinkle Infants have no Command from Chriſt, nor Example among the Apoſtles, nor the firſt primitive Chriſtians for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o doing, but only the Commands of Popes, Councils, Kings, Earthly Powers, and the Examples of men deviated from the primitive Order and Miniſters of Chriſt, ſhould not be hurried away with the heady Torrent of Times, Cuſtoms, Traditions, Unſcriptural Non-apoſtolical Doctrines, but ſhould have an Eye to Chriſts Command and the Apoſtles Practice for what they do, I cannot but ſubſcribe to the Teſtimony of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Id verum quod prius, prius quod ab initio, ab initio quod ab Apoſtolis;</hi> that is, That is Truth, which was firſt; that is firſt, which was from the beginning; that is from the Beginning, which was from the Apoſtles, <hi>Tertul. contr. Marcion. lib.</hi> 4. for what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preached, the ſame they received from Chriſt, who is <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Firſt and the Laſt, the Beginning and Ending, glorified with the Father before the Foundation of the World.</p>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:104215:37"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Now if any queſtion in their Minds; why I call</hi> Sprinkling of Infants Rantiſm, <hi>let them conſider what follows for their ſatisfaction.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Ceremony of <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtration according to Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, was by Dipping, Plunging or Overwhelming their Bodies in Water, as <hi>Scapula</hi> and <hi>Stephens,</hi> two great Maſters of the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue teſtifie; as alſo, <hi>Grotius, Paſor, Voſſius, Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus, Leigh, Caſanbon, Bucan, Bullenger, Zanchy, Spanhemius, Rogers, Taylor, Hammond, Calvin, Piſcator, Aquinas, Scotus:</hi> Now this Dipping or Plunging of the Bodies of ſuch as repented and believed, in Rivers or Fountains, the <hi>Greeks</hi> called it <hi>baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> the <hi>Latius</hi> call it <hi>baptiſmus,</hi> in imitation of whom in our Orthography we call it <hi>baptiſm;</hi> the before-cited fully agree hereunto. Now as for Sprinkling, the <hi>Greeks</hi> call it <hi>rantiſmos,</hi> which I render <hi>rantiſm;</hi> for 'tis as proper to call Sprinkling <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> as to call Dipping <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> this Linguiſts cannot be ignorant of, that <hi>dipping</hi> and <hi>ſprinkling</hi> are expreſſed by ſeveral words, both in <hi>Latin, Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew;</hi> 'tis very evident, if Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling had been of divine inſtitution, the <hi>Greeks</hi> had their <hi>rantiſmos;</hi> but as Dipping was the Inſtitution, they uſed <hi>baptiſmos,</hi> ſo main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the purity and property of the Language. <hi>Meds</hi> in his <hi>Diatribe</hi> on <hi>Titus</hi> ſaith, <hi>That there was no ſuch thing as Sprinkling, or Rantiſm, uſed in Baptiſm in the Apoſtles dayes, nor many Ages after them; to sprinkle Young or Old, and call it</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>is very incongruous, yea, as improper as to call a</hi> Horſe <hi>a</hi> Cow; <hi>for</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm <hi>ſignifies</hi> Dipping, <hi>&amp;c. Zepperus</hi> is as clear as the Sun in this thing, ſaying, <hi>Ex ipſa vocis notatione, et etymo apparet quae bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmi adminiſtrandi conſuitudo fuerit initio; cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> not pro baptiſmo Rantiſmon potius, hoc eſt, aſperſionem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>unc habeamus;</hi> that is, It appears by the genuine ſignification of the word, what their Cuſtom in adminiſtering Baptiſm was at the firſt, foraſmuch as for Baptiſm we now rather uſe Rantiſm, that is, <hi>sprinkling, Zepperus de ſacramentis.</hi> However Rantiſm hath entred into &amp; among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Chriſtianity, and to gain the more acceptance, 'tis called <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> Since the Ingreſs of the Apoſtacy, great hath been the Confuſion of men about this Point, as hath beenſhewed, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:104215:38"/>might further be made apparent. <hi>If any Biſhop or Prieſt</hi> (ſaith a Canon fathered upon the Apoſtles) <hi>do not immerge, that is, dip the Party to be baptized three times in the Water, but content himſelf with one Immerſion, that is, Dipping, let him be depoſed,</hi> Summa Concil. et Pontif. But the fourth <hi>Toletan</hi>-Council, under Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the firſt, taught, <hi>That whether an Infant be baptized with three Immerſions, or but with one</hi> (in plain Engliſh, whether the Infant were dipt thrice or but once) <hi>yet he ſhould be accounted baptized, and the Prieſt not to be depoſed.</hi> Here was Canon againſt Canon, and the Canon fathered upon the Apoſtles wholely or in a high meaſure made void; but it hath been a Sleight of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, to father upon the Apoſtles his ſmoaky Inventions, that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming under that guiſe they may find Acceptance.</p>
                     <p>But drawing to the Haven, let me ſeriouſly tell the Reader, That <hi>John's Water-baptiſm</hi> in its ſeaſon I own, as an uſeful Shadow, fulfilled and ended by Chriſt's Spiritual Baptiſm; and that ſuch as are for dipping Believers, are thorow the influence of Earth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in turned to Shadows without, and Relapſes are dangerous: And as for Rantiſm, that is, Sprinkling of Infants, with Godfathers, Godmothers, Goſſips, Commothers, Fonts, and all other Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Appurtenances, the ſame I deny.</p>
                     <p>Now, to what I have ſpoken of Fonts, I further ſay, that they are uſually hallowed in this manner; The Prieſt makes two Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the Water with his Right Hand, &amp;c. then he takes a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Candle, and drops it into the Water in form of a Croſs, then cries aloud over it and prayes, <hi>That the holy Spirit would deſcend into it, and make it fruitful, that it may have Power to regenerate and beget anew;</hi> then he breathes thrice into the Font, and puts Oyl and Cream into the Water, &amp;c. Further, the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> taught, <hi>That at the Font a spiritual Kindred and Relation was contracted between the baptized Child, its Parents, and the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers;</hi> ſuch a near Relation as that a Council de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed as followeth, <hi>Let none Marry with Godfather or Godmother, whoever doth this, let the ſame be accounted as a</hi> Heathen <hi>until they be ſeperated, and let them de Pennance Twenty Years,</hi> Canon Nicaeni Concilij ex Codice Arabico. Summa Concil et Pontif. Chriſt and the Apoſtles taught not ſo, but that true Fellowſhip, Brotherhood and Siſterhood is in the Light of Life.</p>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:104215:38"/>
                     <p>Now to what hath been ſpoken concerning <hi>John</hi>'s typical Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of <hi>Water-baptiſm,</hi> which many would not have to be a Shadow, I further add; that the <hi>Jews</hi> before <hi>John</hi>'s time, under the firſt Covenant, had their Baptiſm or Waſhing; if any one was made unclean by the touch of a Dead Body, he was to be made clean by the Water of Seperation, ſo that the <hi>Jews</hi> had their <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, a Baptiſm or Waſhing after the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Dead body: thus much ſaith <hi>Godwyn</hi> in his <hi>Jewiſh Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities. He that is waſhed or baptized</hi> (as the Septuagint renders it) <hi>after the touching of a Dead Body, if he touch it again, what avails his Waſhing,</hi> Eccleſ. 34.25. <hi>In the firſt Covenant</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>there was much Obſervation of Meats, Drinks, and divers Waſhings, or Baptiſms,</hi> as the <hi>Greek</hi> renders it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. Now Chriſt, the End of the firſt Covenant, he put an End to the Shadows and Figures, to the Water of Separation without, to the divers Waſhings or Baptiſms without, as Legal and Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, ordained to continue till the time of Reformation, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of Chriſt Jeſus, who introduced a Spiritual Baptiſm, by a Living Water, having a Living Effect, waſhing inwardly, <hi>John</hi> 7.37, 38, 39.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:104215:39"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104215:39"/>
                  <p>A TESTIMONY FOR THE Evangelical Communion, IN THE Bread of Life, IN THE Cup of Bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Lawſon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104215:40"/>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:104215:40"/>
                  <head>A PREFACE to the READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reader,</hi> in this following Teſtimony is ſpread before thee, how after the Primitive Times, when thorow the ingreſs of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, the Bread of Life, the Cup of Bleſſing, where the true Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip is, was loſt within, then they let in a Sea of Confuſion about <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> without, wherein their <hi>Communion</hi> hath ſtood.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Some would have it miniſtred to all.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Some would have it miniſtred to Believers only.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> For many Ages it was miniſtred to Children.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Some have miniſtred it to Dead People.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Some would have both Bread and Wine given.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Some are for giving Bread only.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> Some ſay Chriſt is preſent Tranſubſtantially.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> Some ſay he is preſent Conſubſtantially.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> Some ſay he is preſent Sacramentally.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10.</hi> Some ſay Bread and Wine are Figures of Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>11.</hi> Some ſay, they are the ſame Chriſt that was born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, after Conſecration; hence <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day, and the Feaſt of the <hi>Sacrament of the Altar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>12.</hi> Some are for taking Bread and Wine before Supper, others after Supper, others at any time.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>13.</hi> Some would have a whole Meal of it, ſome are for a Sup, others for a Draught.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>14.</hi> Some would have the Bread and Wine ſtanding, ſome ſitting, ſome kneeling, ſome any way.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>15.</hi> Some would have the Bread broken by the Miniſter, ſome would break it themſelves.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>16.</hi> Some would have it in an upper Chamber, ſome in the Church ſo called, ſome matter not where, if they get it.</item>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:104215:41"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>17.</hi> Some are or have been for the Kiſs of Peace, ſome are for kiſſing the Pax, ſo called.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>18.</hi> Some are or have been for a Glaſs Cup, ſome for a Wood Cup, ſome for a Cup of Gold, ſome for a Cup of Silver, ſome for a Cup of Pewter.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>19.</hi> Some are for Wine only, ſome for Wine mixed with Water,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>20.</hi> Some have been for taking it every day, ſome on all Sundays, ſo called, ſome for once a year, ſome for thrice a year.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>21.</hi> Some would have the Bread and Wine given freely, many are for taking Money for it.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>22.</hi> Many give it as Dinner time, yet call it a Supper.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Moſt of theſe things, if not all, are more or leſs touched in this following Diſcourſe, and may be read and ſeen by ſuch as trace the ſteps of Eccleſiaſtical Writers.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:104215:41"/>
                  <head>A Teſtimony for the Evangelical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, in the Bread of Life, in the Cup of Bleſſing.</head>
                  <p>BEfore the Armies of <hi>Iſrael</hi> went harneſſed out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the Lord inſtituted a Paſſover, ſo called, becauſe in ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Firſt born of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> both of Man and Beaſt, and in executing Judgment upon all their Gods, the Houſes of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were paſſed over: What were the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to do? Every Houſe was to take a Lamb without Blemiſh, &amp;c. and eat it within the Doors, with Unleavened Bread: How were they to eat it? With their Loyns girded up, with Shoes on their Feet, with Staves in their Hands: Who were to eat of it? The <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites;</hi> no Stranger was to eat thereof, no Uncircumciſed Perſon, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. Who paſs thorow the Miniſtration of Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to Chriſt the Evangelical Paſſover, the ſpiritual Paſchal Lamb, they truly read this thing.</p>
                  <p>Now Chriſt, who came not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfil it, before he was ſacrificed up, or the Hand-writing blotted out, or nailed to the Croſs, the Hour approaching of his departing out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> (as I may ſay) a perverſe, froward, gain-ſaying, contradicting, life-oppoſing World, to be glorified with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as he was glorified with him before the World was, he enjoyned his Diſciples to prepare the Paſſover, a Figure, a Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; now he being offered up, the thing was to be read within, the Croſs to be known within, which crucifies Fleſh, with the Affections and Luſts thereof, the Word of God, quick and powerful, ſharper then a two-edged Sword, to be known with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, cutting down captivating Fleſh, and the Fruits thereof, and paſſing over the Seed which bears his Image; thus they came to Chriſt, the Evangelical Paſſover, to the Lamb without Blemiſh,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:104215:42"/>the Food of the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the Houſe of their ſanctified Hearts, which is not come unto but where the Loyns of the Mind have been girded up, Feet ſhod with the Preparation of the Goſpel, Staff in the Hand; on this no Stranger, no Uncircumciſed Perſon feeds: Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, as <hi>Luke</hi> relates it, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.15, 16. <hi>With Deſires I have deſired to eat this Paſſover with you before I ſuffer; for I ſay unto you, I will not any more eat thereof, until it be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God.</hi> Mark, the outward Paſſover was to be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God in the Church: How? By aboliſhing the old Paſſover, and introducing, that is, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Evangelical Paſſover, the Subſtance, Chriſt, the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Paſchal Lamb. <hi>Paul</hi> gave record to this, to the <hi>Corinthians, Purge out the old Leaven, that ye may be a new Lump; for even Chriſt our Paſſover is ſacrificed for us,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 5.7. Who are come to this Lamb without Blemiſh, they are crowned with a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Feſtival.</p>
                  <p>At the Paſſover Chriſt took Bread and bleſſed it, brake it, and gave it to his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>Take, eat,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>this is my Body;</hi> From theſe words no ſmall Confuſion hath riſen among School-men, and Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, as hereafter may be ſeen: <hi>This is my Body;</hi> that is, this betokens, denotes, ſignifies or ſhadows out my Body; the word <hi>[is]</hi> is often ſo taken, as by ſeveral Scriptural Inſtances it may appear: <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Pharaoh, The ſeven good Kine are ſeven years, and the ſeven good Ears of Corn are ſeven years;</hi> that is, ſignifieth or betokeneth ſeven years, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.25, 26. <hi>The ſeven Stars are the Angels of the ſeven Churches,</hi> Rev. 1.20. that is, denotes, betokens, or ſignifies them. <hi>And the ſeven Heads are ſeven Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, on which the Woman ſitteth, and the ten Horns are ten Kings;</hi> that is, ſignifies, betokens or denotes theſe things, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1, 12. And <hi>Zech.</hi> 5.3. <hi>The flying Rell is the Curſe;</hi> that is, ſignifies or betokens the Curſe: The Shadows of the Old Teſtament are ſaid to expiate, becauſe they were Types of Expiation by Chriſt. So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>That Rock was Chriſt;</hi> that is, ſignified, betoken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or held out Chriſt, a Figure or Type of him. <hi>As in the Flower</hi> (ſaith Ludolphus) <hi>the Fruit is foreſhown, ſo by the Shadows of the Law Chriſt to come was ſignified.</hi> But the word <hi>[is]</hi> is
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:104215:42"/>never put for <hi>changed into, Poole.</hi> So, this is my Body; that is, betokens or ſignifie my Body; the outward Bread was a Figure or Shadow of Chriſt, who is that to the Soul which outward Bread is to the Body; thorow outward Bread the Body grows, is ſtrengthned, comforted, refreſhed, ſatisfied; this Chriſt ſaid ſhould be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God, in the Church; how? thorow his ſpiritual Return, who is the Heavenly Bread, Bread of God, living Bread, life-giving Bread, in, by, and thorow which the Churches grew, were ſtrengthned, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, refreſhed, ſatisfied. Moreover, Chriſt took the Cup, and gave it to them, ſaying, <hi>Drink ye all of it, for this is my Blood,</hi> ſignifies and denotes my Blood; Wine quenches the Thirſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes Strength, baniſhes Sorrow, cauſeth Mirth, gladdens the Heart, adds Courage; Chriſt ſaid it was to be fulfilled in the Kingdom of God, in the Church, the primitive Churches waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Blood of the Lamb, were Witneſſes hereof, thorow Draughts of the Cup of Bleſſing, in pourings of the Quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, they made Melody in their Hearts to the Lord; this Cup of Bleſſing made <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> ſing Praiſes unto God, though in an inner Priſon, and their Feet faſt in the Stocks, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>Further, <hi>Paul</hi> put the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (who were jangling and in Diſorder) in mind of Chriſt's Inſtitution, ſaying, <hi>I received of the Lord that which I delivered unto you;</hi> he informs them how he took Bread and the Cup, and bad them eat and drink in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him; <hi>for as often as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye de ſhew the Lord's Death till he come,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.23, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt, though he departed as touching his outward Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet he comforted them with Promiſes of returning; ſo though he departed in the Fleſh, yet he returned in Spirit; <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you the Comforter, that he may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with you forever.</hi> Again, <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſs, I will come to you.</hi> Again, <hi>The Comforter, which is the Holy Ghoſt, he ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your Remembrance, whatſoever I have ſaid unto you,</hi> John 14.16, 18, 26. Again, Chriſt ſaid unto his Diſciples, <hi>It is expedient for you that I go away; if I go not away, the Comforter will not come; but if I depart, I
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:104215:43"/>will ſend him unto you, and he will guide you into all Truth, and ſhew you things to come,</hi> John 16.7, 13. So their eating the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Bread, and drinking the Cup, was in Remembrance of him, till he came; and when he was returned in Spirit, and revealed in them, their Comforter, their faithful Remembrancer, their Guide into all Truth, then they had that in them which the Bread and Wine repreſented.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> writing to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> took them from the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the Inward, ſaying, <hi>Chriſt is in you, except you be Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5. And <hi>We have this Treaſure in Earthen Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.7. And <hi>The Myſtery hid from Ages and Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was, Chriſt in them the Hope of Glory,</hi> Col. 1.27. Thus Chriſt being in them, what need was there of Bread and Wine to keep them in Remembrance of him till he came?</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>John,</hi> a Witneſs of his ſpiritual Appearance, bare record, ſaying, <hi>We know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, to know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 John 5.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> travelled in birth for the <hi>Galatians,</hi> until Chriſt was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in them (<hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19.) in the Apoſtles dayes, and while the Church kept the Faith and primitive Order, the Life of Jeſus was manifeſt in their mortal Bodies, the Heavenly Birth was brought forth in them, Chriſt, the Bread of God, Bread of Life, Living Bread, which who eat of live forever, <hi>John 6.</hi> the redeemed Churches, waſhed in the Blood of the Lamb, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this, ſo had the thing in them, ſignified by outward Bread and Wine.</p>
                  <p>Further, <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſanctified by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints, ſaid, <hi>I ſpeak as to wiſe men, judge ye what I ſay; the Cup of Bleſſing, which we bleſs, is it not the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt? the Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt? we are all Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of that one Bread,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.15. This Cup and this Bread know none but who follow Chriſt in the Regeneration; the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mind feeds on Husks, drinks the Cup of Abomination; but in the Croſs a renewing is known, a Hungring after the Bread of Life is known, the immortal Seed is known, in which the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:104215:43"/>of the Earth are bleſſed; he ſpoke of a Cup, of a Bread, which only the Wiſe in the Wiſdom of God had knowledge of: Now the primitive Chriſtians, living Stones, being come to the the End of Shadows, teſtified againſt the Shadows, and did not ſtick in them, not jangle about them; the Kingdom of God ſtands not in Meat and Drink, but in Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the Holy Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. not in Bread and Wine, but in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the quickening Spirit, the End of Shadows. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Colloſſians,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Let no man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udge you in Meat, or in Drink, &amp;c. which are a Shadow of things to come, but the Body is of Chriſt,</hi> Col. 2.16, 17. Bread and Wine are Shadows as well as the outward Paſſover, and Chriſt is that in his People which the Shadows pointed at. <hi>To him that overcomes</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>will I give to eat of the hidden Maenna,</hi> Rev. 2.17. He promiſes a Food of a more ſpiritual nature, then outward Bread &amp; Wine, a Food hidden from the wiſe and prudent, yea, and from that Mind that ſticks in the Shadows. Further ſaid the true and faithful Witneſs, Rev. 3.20. <hi>Behold I ſtand at the Door and knock; if any man hear my Voice, and open the Door, I will come into him, and will ſup with him, and he with me:</hi> This is the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-communion, here was no outward Bread nor Wine, Cup nor Chalice, but here is that which the <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> pointed at, the <hi>cup</hi> of <hi>bleſſing. If we walk in the Light, as he is in the Light, we have Fellowſhip one with another, and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.7. In the Light Fellowſhip with the Lord is known, and Fellowſhip one with another; and the Word is known, which became Fleſh, and tabernacles in man, this the Redeemed eat, feed on, diſcern; and though it be ſaid, <hi>The Fleſh profitteth nothing,</hi> Joh. 6. and that <hi>Fleſh and Blood can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. yet 'tis ſaid, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you:</hi> and <hi>he that eateth my Fleſh, and drinks my Blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him,</hi> Joh. 6. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>We are Members of his Body, of his Fleſh, and of his Bones,</hi> Epheſ. 5.30. And theſe are no contradiction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, but fulfilled in the ground of Self-denyal, in the croſs to the mortal, the Lords Death is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth till he come, who lives forever, who aboliſhes Death, and brings Life and Immortality to light thorow the Goſpel,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:104215:44"/>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. yea, and Joh. 3.13. The ſame that deſcended, the ſame is aſcended, and is fleſh and bone, and nouriſhes the Soul to eternal Liſe; here the end of Shadows is known. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaid truly, if truly and livingly read, <hi>To eat Chriſt, is to believe in Chriſt; why provideſt thou a Tooth and a Belly? believe only and thou haſt eaten:</hi> Faith centers in the eternal Word, in the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Word; ſo that is revealed which fulfils outward Shadows, other things as well as Bread and Wine, were not of perpetual continuance, nor needful to be practiſed in the Church, after their bounds and ſeaſon, <hi>John</hi> 13.14, 15. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28, 29. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtified ſaying, <hi>Henceforth know we no man after the fleſh, yea, though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet now henceforth we know him no more,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.16. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualized, as that he centered in nothing below the eternal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; he ſtickt not in Bread and Wine, or any other Shadow, but in fervency of ſpirit waited to be comprehended in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed Life, as a man that ſo looks for a loſt Jewel, that he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looks all beſides it; outward things reach no further then fleſhly Knowledge, but a ſpiritual Underſtanding is revealed in, by, and thorow that which is ſpiritual.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaw the Wonders of the Lord in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the Execution of his Judgments for their Deliverance, though the Lord went before them by Day in a Pillar of a Cloud, and by Night in a Pillar of Fire, though they paſſed thorow the Red Sea as upon dry Land, and ſaw the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> drowned, ſo that thorow a ſenſe of his Power and mighty Acts they ſang a Song of Praiſe and Thankſgiving unto the Lord, ſaying, <hi>He was glorious in Holineſs, fearful in Praiſes, doing Wonders;</hi> yet coming unto Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> on to which <hi>Moſes</hi> was called, and continued 40 Dayes and 40 Nights, <hi>Iſrael</hi> fell into a ſpiritual Lethargy, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Lord and his Noble Acts; and loſing the ſenſe of the pure, living, inviſible, eternal God, they cryed for artificial Gods, Gods of Mans making, ſaying to <hi>Aaron, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p, make us Gods, which ſhall go before us; for as for this</hi> Moſes, <hi>that brought us out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> what is become of him,</hi> Exod. 32. <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:104215:44"/>made them a Calf, and they ſaid, <hi>Theſe be thy Gods, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which brought thee up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt; thus loſing the ſenſe of the Living and Life-giving God, they turned to, cryed up, and aſcribed their Deliverance to a Molten Calf, faſhioned with a Graving-Tool. In the Apoſtles days and primitive times, while their Garments were undefiled, being Branches of the Heavenly Olive, kept their Heavenly Places in Chriſt Jeſus, they had the Bread of Life, Water of Life, Heavenly Manna, the Word that became Fleſh in the perſumed Houſes of ſanctified Hearts, they drank of the Cup of Salvation, the Cup of Bleſſing, they were come to Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> they were Members of the New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> they were in the ſpiritual Worſhip, they came to the Life, Sum, Subſtance of all Types, Figures, Shadows, and all thorow the Operation of Chriſt Jeſus in them, who led them from the <hi>Aegyptian</hi>-Bondage of Helliſh <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> old <hi>Abaeddon,</hi> the Deſtroyer; they knew the Prince of Peace, Chriſt Jeſus; and their Labour and living concern was, that in all things he might have the Preeminence. But in dayes ſucceeding the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, when the Myſtery of Iniquity, which the Apoſtle ſaw in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly working in his day, was more and more manifeſted, the Star faln from Heaven, Sun and Air darkned, the Purity of the primitive Church ſpoiled, through the Smoke of the bottomleſs Pit; through the Darkneſs and Deluſion of this Smoke, they loſt the <hi>bread of Life,</hi> the <hi>cup of bleſſing</hi> within, ſo came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſume <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> without, and let in a Sea of Confuſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame, ſome miniſtring it to all, ſome to Believers only, ſometime to Young Children, ſometime to Dead People, &amp;c. and the more the Smoke aroſe out of the Pit, the greater Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs entred the Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> till at length, like as <hi>Iſrael,</hi> having loſt the ſenſe of the living God, called for Gods without, ſo had a Molten Calf, and worſhipped the ſame, aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing their Deliverances thereunto, even ſo apoſtatized <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> having loſt the Bread of Life, the Cup of Bleſſing, Chriſt Jeſus, thorow the in-ſteamings of the bottomleſs Pit, they muſt have an artificial Chriſt; how is that? ſince the Apoſtles dayes, when the Life and Power of Godlineſs was loſt, then this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine came to be preacht, That Bread and Wine after it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by the Prieſt, is no more Bread and Wine, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:104215:45"/>Chriſt, that was born of the Virgin, ſo to be worſhipped; that the Bread and Wine by the conſecration of the Prieſt, is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated, that is, changed into the very Body and Blood of Chriſt; from this came the word <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is grounded upon thoſe words, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> for from theſe words <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>Chriſt is preſent tranſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtantially; Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> ſay, <hi>conſubſtantially; Calviniſts</hi> ſay, <hi>He is preſent ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally,</hi> Author of the <hi>Naked Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whether the Bread and Wine after conſecration be tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated or not, hath been and is much controverted betwixt <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> One ſaid,
<q>
                        <l>Corpore de Chriſti lis eſt, de ſanguine lis eſt,</l>
                        <l>Lis eſt de modo, non habitura modum.</l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <l>How Bread and Wine the living Chriſt ſhould be,</l>
                        <l>'Tis controverted much, men diſagree.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> begun in the year 1545. and others taught, That Bread and Wine being conſecrated by the Prieſt, is turned into the true, real, ſubſtantial Body of Chriſt, Fleſh, Blood, Bones, &amp;c. even the ſame that was born of the Virgin, <hi>bread</hi> into his <hi>body, wine</hi> into his <hi>blood;</hi> and that this conſecrated Hoſt being offered to God by the Prieſt, is a Propitiatory Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the Quick and the Dead, and that men are thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, and that it muſt be worſhipped, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in Proceſſions; and that ſuch as denyed the ſame, ſhould be <hi>Anathema,</hi> accurſed: And not only this Council, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, Pope <hi>Nicholas,</hi> Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth, Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> &amp;c. taught the ſame; for denying of this Doctrine, many have been burned to Aſhes, as Eccleſiaſtical Writers teſtifie, <hi>Summa Concil. et Pontif. Oruphrius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third invented <hi>Pixes</hi> and <hi>Boxes</hi> (as 'tis ſaid) to put the ſacramental Bread in.</p>
                  <p>Again, ſuch Reverence came to be given to conſecrated Bread without, when the <hi>bread of life</hi> was turned from, yea, and the true Worſhip of God in Spirit and in Truth, that a Council put out a Canon, forbidding Women to receive the Euchariſt, that is,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:104215:45"/>the conſecrated Hoſt, with bare Hands, <hi>Concil. Antiſid. Summa Concil. et Pontif.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> tell of a Miracle of an Aſs, that left his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender to worſhip the conſecrated Hoſt; on ſuch Conceit as this (ſaith <hi>Mede</hi>) the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation is grounded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Aderation given to the Conſecrated Hoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When it came to be believed, that <hi>bread</hi> after conſecration was the very Chriſt, the Lamb of God that takes away the ſins of the World, then Popes and Councils ordained, that at certain times it ſhould be lifted up above the Prieſts Head, and that at the heaving of it up a <hi>Bell</hi> ſhould be rung, and that all that hear its found, ſhould not only do low Obeyſance, but fall down on their Knees, and with Hands lifted up towards Heaven worſhip it, and ſay <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> or ſome other Prayer; they ordained alſo, that it ſhould be born to the Sick with great Reverence, and that with lighted Caudles, though at noon day, for the ſame they inſtituted a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Feaſt, called, <hi>Corpus Chriſti Day,</hi> on which the conſecrated Hoſt is born about, lifted up and worſhipped.</p>
                  <p>Further, 'Twas enjoyned, That if a Prieſt were called in the Night ſeaſon to houſel the Sick, and there ſpent all his Hoſts, as he came Homeward he was to put out the Candle, left the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould adore the empty Tabernacle: ſuch as read the Canons of Pope <hi>Honorius, Gregory</hi> the ninth, Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> Pope-<hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the fifth, their Lives and Councils in their dayes, they may ſee theſe things.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>France</hi> (ſaith <hi>Heylin,</hi> in his Survey of the Eſtate of <hi>France</hi>) a couple of Prieſts carries the Hoſt under a Canopy, before it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Bell continually tinkling, all in Houſes perceiving their God to go by, make ſome ſhew of Reverence, all in the Streets with bended Knees, and elevated Hands do it Honour; to the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> it is as a Watch-Peal to be gone, left for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>reverence they be knocked down: in this (ſaith he) is a ſmatch of <hi>Turciſm,</hi> who when they hear the Cryers bawling in their Streets, they fall proſtrate on the Ground, where-ever they are, and kiſs it thrice, ſo perform their Devotions to <hi>Mahomet;</hi> their carrying it about the Streets hath a touch of <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> from the <hi>Levites</hi>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:104215:46"/>carrying about the Ark on their Shoulders; their Adoration of it is eſpecially from <hi>Gentiliſm;</hi> for never any people but <hi>Heathen</hi> (ſaith he) afforded divine Honours to things inanimate. Thus when Heavenly Salt, Wiſdom from above, was loſt within, multitudes of Inventious ſwarmed into Apoſtatized Chriſtendom.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lanctantius</hi> in his firſt Book of Inſtitutions, taxed the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of Ridiculouſneſs, who worſhipped <hi>Jupiter</hi> as a God, <hi>Cam cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem tamen Saturno et Rhea gentium confiterentur,</hi> ſeeing they ſo perfectly knew his Original, much more are they to be blamed, who impoſe upon the peole the Adoration of a Dead God, <hi>a principis non ita fuit,</hi> it was not ſo from the the beginning, <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins Survey,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt ſaid unto his Diſciples, <hi>Take, eat, this is my Body;</hi> this denotes, ſignifies, be tokens my Body; what <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> is to the <hi>body of man,</hi> that is Chriſt the Bread of Life, his Fleſh, his Blood to the Soul; the Doctrine of Bread-worſhip, Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints, Worſhipping of Images, and many other peſtilent Errors have ſteamed into the Church, from the miſ-underſtanding and miſ-interpretation of Scriptures, ſaith <hi>Rainold</hi> in his Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Paul,</hi> who had the Mind of Chriſt, a feeling &amp; ſenſe of Chriſts Inſtitution, ſaid thrice in a Breath (as I may ſay) that the Bread after it was bleſſed, or Thanks were given, which is called Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, remained Bread, he called it ſo, and he called it what it was; his words imply not his belief of Tranſubſtantiation, but expreſly the contrary, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26, 27, 28.</p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. Chriſt took the Cup, and gave Thanks, and bad them drink, ſaying, <hi>This is my Blood,</hi> that is, ſignifies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens or holds out my Blood; not his Blood after Conſecration, but a Shadow of his Blood; his own words immediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evidently demonſtrates this, <hi>I will not drink henceforth of the Fruit of the Vine;</hi> he calls what was in the Cup, the Fruit of the Vine; now his Blood was not the Fruit of the Vine, but Wine is the Fruit of the Vine; <hi>until that day when I drink it new with you in my Fathers Kingdom,</hi> ſaith he; now, whoever ſay, that Bread and Wine after Conſecration is Chriſt's Fleſh and Blood, conſider this, Did Chriſt cat his own Body? Did he drink his own Blood? you ſay, conſecrated Bread and Wine is Chriſt's Fleſh and Blood, and Chriſt eat and drank thereof; what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquences
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:104215:46"/>would follow this Doctrine? Chriſt, his Fleſh, his Blood, is hid from apoſtatized Ages and Generations; his Word became Fleſh, living Food, Food of living Souls; Chriſt is the living Bread, which came down from Heaven; his Fleſh is the Bread that he gives; who came from Heaven, given for the Life of the World; but periſhing Bread and Wine, though conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated a thouſand times, came not from Heaven; this ſaid he, who alſo ſaid, <hi>The Fleſh profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eth nothing, it is the Spirit that quickeneth;</hi> and <hi>the words that I ſpeak unto you, they are Spirit, and they are Life,</hi> John 6.</p>
                  <p>And whereas <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Corinthians, As often as ye eat this Bread and Drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lords Death till he come,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26. Now if the conſecrated Hoſt were Chriſt, then he were come; then how is it done till he come, and were it proper to ſay, till he come, when he is already come? Chriſt was obedient to Death, even the Death of the Croſs; &amp; the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were in the Croſs in the daily dying, having Taſtes of the eternal Inheritance, and in the dying; he comes with perfect Conqueſt, aboliſhing Death, and bringing Life and Immortality to Light. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>This do ye, as often as ye drink it in remembrance of me;</hi> this plainly ſhews, that conſecrated Bread and Wine is not his Body; where his Body is there is no need of a Repreſentation; conſecrated Bread works not the Works of the true Chriſt, the true and faithful Witneſs, ſo is not Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt, called alſo Jeſus, by interpretation a <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſuch is his Name, ſuch is his Nature; he ſaves his People from their Sins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. thorow his inward Operation they become new Creatures, God's Workmanſhip, in a word of <hi>Beth-aven,</hi> that is, a Houſe of Vanity or Iniquity, they become <hi>Bethel,</hi> that is, the Houſe of God, Sharers in the Riches &amp; Peace of the Lords Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; conſecrated Bread effects not theſe things in the Receivers, though a thouſand times conſecrated &amp; received, ſo is not the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins Birth; <hi>John</hi> teſtified, ſaying, <hi>The Blood of Jeſus Chriſt clenſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 Joh 1.7. this is the effectual remedy; the Lords Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle finds many a foul Flaw in man; ſuch as believe are reduced into the Order of the heavenly Truth: the Apoſtle further bare record, ſaying, <hi>He loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own Blood,</hi>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:104215:47"/>Rev. 1.5, 6. and hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto God, Kings to reign in Truths Dominion over the Earth, over the World, over Luſts, over ſpiritual Adverſaries, Prieſts to offer a Sacrifice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving unto the Lord; to this Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Bread and Wine, though a thouſand times conſecrated, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring.</p>
                  <p>Again, The true Chriſt, the Virgins Birth, is the ſame today, yeſterday and forever, incorruptible, periſhes not, immortal, the Holy One ſees not Corruption; but Bread and Wine, though conſecrated, corrupts, periſhes, grows mouldy, loſes Vertues, Taſte, Savour, ſo is not the Body and Blood of Chriſt: and the Diſciples were not to labour for the Meat which periſhes, but for that Meat which endureth unto everlaſting Life, <hi>John</hi> 6.27.</p>
                  <p>Again, Thorow the Body of Chriſt the faithful become dead to the Law, to be married to Chriſt, to be fruitful unto God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. dead to the Law, dead to ſin, yea, and the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus makes free from the Law of Sin and Death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2, 10. but the conſecrated Hoſt hath not this Operation in man, but leaves men alive in Sin, dead to God, ſo not Chriſts <hi>bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> not his <hi>fleſh,</hi> not his <hi>blood:</hi> Chriſt ſaid to the <hi>Jews, Your Fathers did eat Manna in the Wilderneſs, and are dead;</hi> ſuch Minds as ſtick in Viſibles are dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, though conſecrated by Man, they quicken not, it is the Spirit that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; and <hi>he that eats of the Bread</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that comes from Heaven,</hi> the Word, Chriſt's Fleſh, he knows a Vivification, a Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he dyes not, but <hi>lives forever,</hi> John 6. and 'tis the Lord that gives being and Vertue to all Creatures, not mans Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which cannot keep Viſibles from loſing their Vertue, Savour, Taſte; 'tis evident by their own Conſtitution, that they were conſcious of this, who enjoyned, <hi>That Prieſts on every eighth day ſhould renew the holy Euchariſt,</hi> that is, conſecrated Bread, &amp;c. leſt thorow Oldneſs thereof ſome ſhould be brought into Indevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to have the Spark of their Devotion (as I may ſay) in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure extinguiſhed, <hi>Summa Concil. et Pontif.</hi> but Chriſt is the ſame today, yeſterday and forever, his Years fail not, he waxes not old as a Garment.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:104215:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of giving Bread and Wine to the World; for this it is alledged, that</hi> Judas <hi>did eat of the Bread, and did drink of the Cup.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That was that the Scripture might be fulfilled, <hi>Mine own familiar Friend, which did eat of my Bread, hath lift up his Heel againſt me,</hi> Pſal. 41.9. yea, and Chriſt the Store-houſe of Wiſdom and Knowledge, ſaid, <hi>He that dippeth his Hand with me in the Diſh, the ſame ſhall betray me,</hi> Matth. 26.23. his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-commoner (as I may ſay) whereby the Indiguity of the thing was much aggravated: as for <hi>Judas,</hi> he was numbred with the Diſciples, and had obtained part of the true Miniſtry, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. but fell by Tranſgreſſion, and became a Member of that ſinful and unſociable Society which Chriſt teſtified againſt; and for giving Bread and Wine, the Sacrament, as 'tis called, to the World, have you no Example but <hi>Judas?</hi> who ſold Chriſt for Money, as many ſell Bread and Wine for Money now, which after Conſecration is truly and really Chriſt, as many in Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration affirm: Chriſt gave it to his Diſciples only, a Shadow of a more ſpiritual Bread, of a more ſpiritual Cup, after to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of giving Bread and Wine to Infants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After the Primitive Times, when thorow the inundation of Apoſtacy, and over-ſpreading of that foul Leproſie, the living Bread and living Cup was loſt, then ſtreamed in a Sea of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as I ſaid before, the Heavenly Key of pure Knowledge and Divine Underſtanding was loſt, things of God became as a Book ſealed with ſeven Seals, the Opener and Fulfiller of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth came in a high meaſure to be loſt, then a Cloud of Miſ-apprehenſions and Miſ-interpretations of Scriptures invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, then thorow a Miſ-apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Miſ-underſtanding of that Scripture of Chriſt, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you,</hi> John 6.53. the Fathers fell into that Error, that <hi>None but Communicants could be ſaved,</hi> whereupon they gave the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:104215:48"/>Sacrament (ſo called) to Infants, and put it into the Mouthes of Dead Men, &amp;c. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo</hi> was thus mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as appears by this his following Concluſion, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at <hi>It is in vain to promiſe Salvation and Life Eternal to little Children, unleſs they be baptized, and receive the Body and Blood of Chriſt, ſince the Neceſſity of them both is atteſted by ſo many, ſo great, and divine Teſtimonies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Practice of giving the Sacrament to Infants crept in the early Ages of the World, became wonderful general, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued above ſix hundred years in the Church, till the time of <hi>Charlemain;</hi> ſome were ſo ſtrict in it, as that a Canon enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That baptized Infants ſhould receive the Communion before they ſucked, or received any other Nouriſhment:</hi> the ſame is or hath been obſerved by the <hi>Greeks, Aethiopians, Bohemians, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravians;</hi> and that this was enjoyned by Popes, Biſhops, &amp;c. theſe following Authors teſtifie, recourſe being had to their Canons, Conſtitutions, &amp;c. Pope <hi>Innocent, Paganinus Gaudentius Theol. de moribus ſeculi. Nicephorus in Hiſtor. Eccleſ. Johannes Langius, Auguſtin, Taylors worthy Communicant,</hi> chap. 3. <hi>Alcninus, Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donate on John</hi> 6. <hi>Author of the Naked Truth, Grotius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> had appointed the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be given to Infants, and it became in a manner uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, of long continuance, yet the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> put out this Canon, <hi>If any one ſhall ſay, that the Communion of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, that is, conſecrated Bread, is neceſſary for Children before they attain unto years of Diſcretion, let him be</hi> Anathema, <hi>accurſed,</hi> Concil. Trident. Sect. 3. Can. 4. Here the Pope, who cannot err, as 'tis ſaid, came to be queſtioned, his Doctrine, <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Doctrine, and the Church Practice for above ſix hundred years, came to be caſt out as ſpurious by the <hi>Trent</hi> Council: What was become of the Unity of the Spirit, and the Spirit of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which is ſubject to the Prophets: Some ſaid,
<q>
                        <l>Ebrius, Infantes, Erroneus, atque furentes,</l>
                        <l>Cum pueris, domini non debent ſumere corpus.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:104215:48"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of giving the Sacrament, ſo called, to Dead People.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the before-mentioned Scripture, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you</hi> John 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. the Fathers in the Degeneration from the primitive, Faith, Doctrine, Worſhip and Practice, fell into the Gulf of that Conceit, <hi>That none but Communicants ſhould partake of the bleſſedneſs of Salvation;</hi> upon which they not only gave Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Bread, &amp;c. to Infants, but put it into the Mouthes of Dead Men: <q>There were ſome (ſaith <hi>Sparke,</hi> the Kings Chaplain, pag. 127.) that baptized the Dead, and put the Sacramental-Bread in their Mouths, as their <hi>Viaticum,</hi> judging it better to have ſuch a neceſſary Ordinance by Proxy then altogether to go without it.</q> That ſuch a thing was in uſe in the Church may be certainly concluded, from the ſixth Canon of the third Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> 'tis there apparent, that that Council con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned certain Hereticks, who thruſt the Sacramental Bread in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Mouths of Dead Men; yea, and the ſixth general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was concerned to eradicate the Tares of that Deluſion and ſmoky Conceit, ſaying, <hi>Let none give the Enchariſt, that is ſacramental Bread, to the Dead; for it is written, Take, and eat; but the Dead are neither in a Capacity to take nor to eat,</hi> Summa Concil. et Pontif. Thus the Cup of Bleſſing being loſt, they received at the old Serpents hand the Cup of Abomination. Fornication, Deluſions and Conceits, and they were drunk therewith.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:104215:49"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Time, and Times of taking the Sacrament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As the Churches in the Apoſtles days and primitive Ages grew up in the ſanctifying Faith, in the purifying Hope, thorow the Croſs of Chriſt, the Life of Jeſus came to be manifeſted in their mortal Bodies, they were true and living Witneſſes of Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Lord, thorow the Leadings and Teachings of the Anointing; they knew Chriſt ſupping with them, and they with him, without outward Bread and Wine, being in the Heavenly Banquetting Houſe, in the End and Subſtance of all Types, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure and Shadows, but as the Serpent ſeducing <hi>Eve,</hi> brought in a world of Wickedneſs, ſo the ſame by little and little wearing the Church from the Simplicity that is in Chriſt Jeſus, brought in a flood of Confuſion, an earthly Mind within, turned to earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Figures and Shadows without, Elements and Rudiments, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Life of Communion within, they placed it in Shadows without, and much Confuſion and Uncertainty hath been in the Church about the Times of taking it, as appears in the Writings of Men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Very anciently</hi> (ſaith Polydor) <hi>Chriſtians took the Euchariſt, that is, the ſacramental Broad, every day in the Morning, and Faſting,</hi> Polydor lib. 5.</p>
                  <p>After this <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaid, <hi>This daily taking of the Communion of the Eucharist, I neither Praiſe nor blame; yet my Perſwaſion is, that men take it every Lords Day:</hi> his Perſwaſion very likely took place; hence it came to be called, <hi>Panis hebdomadarius,</hi> Week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bread. <hi>Polydor lib.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zephyrinus</hi> afterwards appointed, <hi>That all Chriſtians, who were come to ſutable years, ſhould once a year at leaſt, take the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, namely, at</hi> Eaſter: Once every day, now once a year will ſerve; either much of Zeal was in the one, or much of Coldneſs was in the other. <hi>Polyd. lib.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fabian</hi> afterwards eſtabliſhed, <hi>That men ſhould take the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament thrice in the year, if not oftner, at</hi> Eaſter, Pentecoſt, <hi>and</hi> Chriſtmas, <hi>Polyd. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Summa Concil. et Pontif.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anacletus</hi> commanded, <hi>That they that would not take the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:104215:49"/>ſhould be excommunicated as Prophane Perſons,</hi> Polyd. lib. 5. Several are of another Diſpoſition in this our Age, who ſhew not much diſlike at peoples Refuſal of the Sacrament, provide they give them the ſame Price as they do who take it; but refuſing that, War is prepared.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the Communion Cup.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the primitive Times, the Church of living Stones was under the Rule and Government of the bleſſed Spirit, in and thorow which the Cry and living Soul-breathing was, <hi>Abba Father;</hi> here the Cup of Salvation, of Conſolation, of Bleſſing, full of Righteouſneſs, Peace, Joy, Aſſurance, Heavenly Riches was plentifully drunk of, this being loſt thorow the Smoke, Inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Deluſions, pompous Shew, bewitching Splendor, Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadings, Muzlings and enfatuating Sleights of Antichtiſt, and men faſt bound in the Dungeon of ſpiritual Servitude, and toil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Entanglements of Will-worſhip, Self-righteouſneſs, Traditions, Conceits, in this condition the Cup of Abomination and ſpiritual Fornication got entrance, making Nations drunk, and in the barren Wilderneſs of this State, there hath been no little jangling about the Sacramental Cup without, as of what Mettal it ſhould be made of; ſome have been for Wood, ſome for Glaſs, ſome for Pewter, ſome for Gold, ſome for Silver, as may be aſſuredly concluded by the Canons and Conſtitutions of Popes, Kings, Arch-Biſhops, Provincial Councils, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is very clear</hi> (ſaith Polydor) <hi>that the Cups uſed in the conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of divine Blood was at the firſt made of Wood,</hi> de Invent. lib. 2. cap. 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zepherinus</hi> afterwards commanded, <hi>That Glaſs Cups ſhould be uſed, not Wood Cups, as before,</hi> Polyd. lib. 2. cap. 12.</p>
                  <p>Succeeders skrewed a Peg higher, the former Decree by little and little vaniſhed, and it was conſtituted, <hi>That Golden, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or at the leaſt Pewter Cups or Chalices ſhould be uſed,</hi> Polydor lib. 2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bonifacius</hi> Martyr and Biſhop, ſaid, <hi>Formerly Golden Prieſt,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:104215:50"/>did wake uſe of Wood Cups or Chalices; but now on the contrary, Wood Prieſts uſe Golden Chalices.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As the Apoſtatical Pomp and Splendor increaſed, ſo the ſimple and homely uſe of Wood Cups came to be generally hiſſed at and ſleighted, ſo that the Provincial <hi>Triburienſian</hi> Council decree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus, <hi>We decree, that henceforth no Prieſt may by any means preſume to make the ſacred Myſtery of the Body and Blood of our Lord in Wood Cups or Chalices,</hi> Summa Concil. et Pontif.</p>
                  <p>Our King <hi>Edgar</hi> put out a Canan to this purpoſe, ſaying, <hi>We teach, that every Chalice or Cup, wherein any one ſhall conſecrate the Euchariſt, ſhall be of Molten Mettal, and not at all conſecrated in a Wood Cup or Chalice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One <hi>Remigius</hi> an Arch-Biſhop, appointed theſe his Verſes to be ſet on the ſide of the Sacremental Cup:
<q>
                        <l>Haurit hinc populus vitam de ſanguine ſacro</l>
                        <l>Injecto aeternus quem fudit vulnere Chriſtus, &amp;c.</l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <l>Hence People drink Eternal Life, that's good;</l>
                        <l>For in this Cup contained is Chriſt's Blood.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee what a ſtir hath been about Invention, after that the Simplicity and Stability of the Truth as it is in Jeſus was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from, and after that credens was given, that Bread and Wine by the Prieſts conſecration, was tranſmuted, that is, changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the real Body and Blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How Communion in both Kinds was forbidden.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That Chriſt gave Bread and Wine unto his Diſciples is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable; <hi>Paul</hi> mentioning the Inſtitution unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> mentions both, as 'tis evident the Bread repreſented his Body, the Bread of Life, that nouriſhes the Soul to eternal Life; the Wine his Blood, which they came to witneſs to cleanſe them from all ſin, as they kept to the Head, thorow the Ligament of living Faith, they came to the End of all Figures, to partake of the one Bread, one in all; but in the dark reign of Apoſtacy they
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:104215:50"/>re-aſſumed the Shadows, and divided <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> into <hi>Clergy,</hi> that is, Teachers, and <hi>Laity,</hi> that is, all others out of Holy Orders, ſo called; but all the Faithful are the Lord's Lot, as <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. tranſlated there <hi>Inheritance,</hi> but properly ſignifies <hi>Lot,</hi> if the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies be conſulted, and makes nothing for, but againſt the diſtinction of <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laity,</hi> Leighs Crit. However, the Diſtinction hath found continuance in the Church; and in the year 1215. Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third did firſt of all, as 'tis recorded, forbid that the Lay People ſhould receive their Communion in both kinds, he would allow them Bread, but no Drink; this kind of Communion (as 'tis ſaid) was not before the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> where in the thirteenth Seſſion they depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the People of the Cup: yea, and a Canon was put out, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in down-right and expreſs terms:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If any one ſhall deny whole and entire Chriſt, the Fountain and Author of all Graces, to be taken under one Species of Bread, &amp;c. let him be</hi> Anathema, <hi>accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus in this, as in other things, it appears, that not only the Power of Godlineſs hath been loſt, but great Confuſion hath followed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Mixed Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> (if I may uſe the Language of my Author) the ſeventh Pope from <hi>Peter,</hi> being about to conſecrate, was the firſt of all that mingled Water and Wine together, <hi>Polydor lib.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of taking Money for Bread and Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ſhewed before, how Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, and the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> denyed the Cup to the Laity, ſo called; one <hi>Eckius</hi> complying with this Doctrine, gives an irrational Reaſon for it, <hi>The Laity</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ought to content themſelves with the Bread only, becauſe,</hi> equi donation ſunt inſpiciendi dentes, that is, <hi>a gift Horſe is not to be looked in the Month,</hi> Apud Manlium in loc. com. He though belike, that Lay Men could not claim any Right to the Bread neither.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:104215:51"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> grants, that they have Right to the Bread, but adds, <hi>that in eating the Bread tranſubſtantiated by the Prieſt into the Body of Chriſt, they drink his Blood alſo.</hi> But <hi>Lombard</hi> (his Maſter) contradicts this his Doctrine, ſaying, <hi>That the Bread is not turned but into Chriſts Fleſh, nor the Wine but into his Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let him that is crowned with Heavenly Wiſdom, judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Contradictions beſpeak them to be Builders of <hi>Sion,</hi> a City of Unity, the Joy of the whole Earth, or Builders of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Babel,</hi> a City of Confuſion.</p>
                  <p>The Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> acknowledged, that Chriſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and adminiſtred both Bread and Wine, <hi>tamen hoc non obſtante,</hi> yet notwithſtanding the Authority of the holy Canons and the Cuſtom of the Church hath and doth deny the Cup to the Laity.</p>
                  <p>But to return, Neither did Chriſt take Money for the Bread and Wine which he gave to any; but as the ſpirit of Selfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs entred the Temple of the Church, it produced other Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: ſurely there was occaſion why the ſix the general Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> decreed, <q>That no Biſhop, Prieſt or Deacon, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring the Communion to people, ſhould take any Money whatever of them for the ſame; and that, who as did ſhould be depoſed, <hi>Summa Concil. et Pontif.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet notwithſtanding the <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> Canon in <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches now, the Pariſh buyes Bread and Wine, and the Prieſt ſells it them again, that the Prieſt may have an Offering at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> ſo that many otherwiſe zealous for the eſtabliſhed Miniſtry, blame their Miniſters, their ſpiritual Hoſts, as they call them, that firſt the Pariſh muſt buy Bread and Wine, and give it to the Miniſter, and then the Miniſter give it to the People, and after call for a Reckoning, yea, and force ſuch as neither bite nor ſup thereof to reckon and pay.</p>
                  <p>Let us hear the Lord's Proclamation, <hi>Ho, every one that thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, come ye to the Waters,</hi> to the Water of Life, the Cup of Salvation, Conſolation and Bleſſing; a ſpiritual Thirſt is called for, neither Money nor Price. And further, <hi>He that hath no
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:104215:51"/>Money, come ye, buy and eat, yea come, buy Wine and Milk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Money and without Price.</hi> Here is Bread, and Wine, and Milk at the Lord's Hand, without Money or Price, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. but ſuch as are made Miniſters by the will of man, through the ſtrength of Arts, Sciences, Natural Parts, Abilities, Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Endowments, Acquiſitions, they have another Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ſo another Spirit, forcing Money and Price not only from Receivers, but from Non-receivers alſo; ſo that the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of many, I ſay, not all, beſpeaks them, ſaying, We preach the Goſpel, <hi>tantum ut nos paſcat, et veſtiat,</hi> meerly for Food and Rayment, to pick a living by, <hi>Trap</hi> on 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>Yea, and <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. <hi>The Spirit and the Bride ſay, come; and let him that heareth ſay, come; and let him that is athirſt come; and whoſoever will, let him take the Water of Life free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Here is Communion, Royal Communion, Water of Life, Bread of Life, the Cup of Bleſſing, freely, without Money or Price.</p>
                  <p>But their Voice is not the Voice of the Spirit, nor of the Bride, nor of him that heareth, nor of him that is athirſt, who forces Money and Price for Bread and Wine, the Shadow, not only from the Receiver, but the Non-receiver alſo; for where Chriſt's Doctrine and the Apoſtles is tranſgreſſed, his Inſtitution for Goſpel-Maintenance violated, their Voice is the Voice of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who was for Gifts, Rewards, Wages of Unrighteouſneſs, filthy Lucre, who have nothing but the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, which maketh not alive, they make Gain of it, ſell it; but who are Members of Chriſt's Body, of his Fleſh, of his Bones, as freely they have received the Bread of Life, ſo they freely give.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Kiſs of Peace, and of the Pax.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>David,</hi> the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> exhorted Kings and Judges of the Earth, to <hi>kiſs the Son, leſt he be angry,</hi> Pſal. 2.12. Theſe are Greetings, cordial Embraces, not known but in the operating Virtue of the Seed of Regeneration, and in ſpiritual Submiſſion to his Heavenly Will. <hi>Let him kiſs me</hi> (ſaith the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:104215:52"/>Church) <hi>with the Kiſſes of his Mouth,</hi> Cantic. 1.2. In the ſenſe-reſtoring Life theſe are felt as Seals and Aſſurances of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Favour and Acceptance, Earneſts and Fruits of the Spirit, like Balm to the Wounded. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſaid, <hi>Salute one another with an Holy Kiſs,</hi> Rom. 16.16. This <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> called, <hi>The Kiſs of Love,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.14. In after Ages, as Fellowſhip with the Lord, and with one another in the Light, in a high meaſure came to be loft, then the Obſervation of Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows more and more got entrance, then their Fellowſhip and Communion began much to conſiſt in Externals, as Bread and Wine, then Chriſtians entertained a Cuſtom of Kiſſing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before they received the Communion, thereby teſtifying their Love to one another, as faith <hi>Parens</hi> on the <hi>Romans;</hi> In <q>the ancient Church, when they aſſembled (ſaith <hi>Meds</hi>) to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the Communion, the Deacon was wont to proclaim, <hi>Nequis contra aliquem,</hi> Let no Man have ought againſt his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and then, <hi>Salutate alij alios oſculo ſancto,</hi> that is, Salute one another with an Holy Kiſs, which they did, firſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Clergy, then the Laity, the Men apart by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the Women by themſelves, in token of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; this was called, <hi>Oſculum pacis,</hi> The K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſs of Peace: After this entred a Ceremony, (in the Midnight of Apoſtacy, as I may ſay, ſtill uſed among the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> to this day) 'for the Prieſt to ſend a little Gilded or Painted Table with a Crucifix, or ſome Saints Picture thereon, to be kiſſed of every one in the Church, before they receive the Bread; this they call, <hi>The Kiſſing of the Pax,</hi> Mede.</q> What there is of the Power of Godlineſs, or of the Form thereof, in this thing, without further Remarks, I leave to the Wiſe to judge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Feaſt of the Sacrament of the Altar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The outward <hi>Jew</hi> had ſeveral Feaſts of eſpecial Solemnity, which ſhadowed out a ſpiritual Feaſt under the Goſpel-Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, to be truly and inwardly witneſſed in the purified Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of inward <hi>Jews.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The outward <hi>Jew</hi> was to obſerve the Feaſt of the Paſſover
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:104215:52"/>of Unleavened Bread, wherein for ſeven dayes they were to eat Unleavened Bread, no Leaven was to be found in their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p>The outward <hi>Jew</hi> was to obſerve the Feaſt of Pentecoſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in Remembrance of the Law delivered unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount, fifty dayes after their departure out of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> this was called the Feaſt of Weeks, in which they were to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a new Meat-Offering unto the Lord, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. a Tribute of a Free-will Offering, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.</p>
                  <p>The outward <hi>Jew</hi> was to obſerve the Feaſt of Harveſt, the firſt ripe Fruits of the Land were to be offered unto the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. As alſo the Feaſt of In-gathering, when Fruits were gathered in, and this was to continue ſeven dayes, called alſo the Feaſt of Tabernacles, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, The outward <hi>Jew</hi> was to obſerve the Feaſt of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Now Chriſt Jeſus put an End to all theſe, as Typical, Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, Figures, being the End of the Law for Righteouſneſs to every one that believes, the inward <hi>Jews,</hi> the truly Gathered of the Lord, had the true ſenſe and feeling hereof, bearing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to Chriſt Jeſus, their Paſſover, their Unleavened Bread, Bread of Life, their ſpiritual Law-giver, making them free from the Law of Sin and Death, they were come to the Evangelical Meat-Offering, to the Free-will Offering, they bare record to Chriſt, the Firſt Fruits of them that ſleep; they knew the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical In-gathering, having Heavenly Treaſure in Earthen Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; they knew a Tabernacle not of man's building; <hi>John</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſaying, <hi>The Word became Fleſh, and tabernacled in us,</hi> dwelt in us as in a Tabernacle, ſo they ſaw his Glory; and the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of God is with men, and he will in-dwell in them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3. yea, and by Chriſt they were Witneſſes of Attonement; the inward <hi>Jews,</hi> Called and Choſen, were come to the End of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Shadows, Feaſts, as other things; they were come to the Joy of the holy Spirit, to the Marriage Supper of the Lamb; theſe knew a Good Conſcience to be a continual Feaſt; bleſſed are they which are called unto the Marriage Supper of the Lamb, if they obey his Call, and frame not Excuſes, as thoſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:104215:53"/>Gueſts did mentioned by the Evangeliſt: and that the Apoſtles who were come to the End of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Obſervances, as o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Days,, and Feaſts, did inſtitute others, I have not found nor obſerved, further then that the Churches in the Apoſtles dayes uſually ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, to wait upon and worſhip the living God on the Firſt Day of the Week; and in primitive Times, the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it was as a Badge of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> when the Queſtion was propounded, <hi>Servaſti Dominicum?</hi> Haſt thoú kept the Lord's Day? the Anſwer was returned, <hi>Chriſtianus ſum, intermittere non poſſum;</hi> I am a Chriſtian, I cannot but keep the Lord's Day: <q>But Profeſſors of Chriſtianity are grown perfectly prophane, (ſaith one) as that they can play on that day without Book, <hi>Trapp.</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <q>Let us keep that day (ſaith <hi>Ignatius</hi>) in a ſpiritual manner, rejoycing in the Meditation of the Law, not in the Reſt of the Body, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Magneſ.</hi>
                     </q> The Apoſtle in Chriſt, the End of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Obſervation of Dayes, ſaid thus, <hi>He that obſerves a Day, he obſerves it to the Lord,</hi> Rom. 14.6. ſo ſay we. Further, the <hi>Galatians</hi> Judaizing, turning to beggarly Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Paul</hi> wrote unto them, ſaying, <hi>Ye obſerve Days, Moneths, Times and Years; I am afraid of you,</hi> Gal. 4.10, 11. Now, as the Apoſtacy prevailed, the Sun-ſhine of the Evangelical Day was loft, then they brought in multitudes of Saints Dayes, ſo called, to be obſerved to this and that Saint, till ſuch times as all the Dayes of a Year were not ſufficient to afford a particular Day to each Saints whom they deſired to honour with a Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, then came in <hi>All-Saints Day,</hi> ſo called, and among other dayes ſet apart, in the year 1254. Pope <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the fourth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the Feaſt of the <hi>Sacrament of the Altar,</hi> with Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Pardons; in this Degeneration of Chriſtianity came in (as I ſaid before) theſe things; and as for <hi>Chriſtmas, Shrovetide, &amp;c.</hi> the very Names diſcover their Founders, and thoſe that plead for the Obſervation of thoſe Times are generally the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Prophaners thereof, in Sports, Games, vicious Courſes, Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers rather of the Rule of <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> (who ſaid, <hi>Ede, bibe, lude, poſt mortem nulla voluptas;</hi> Eat, drink, play, &amp;c.) then of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:104215:53"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the word Sacrament, and Euchariſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The old <hi>Roman</hi> Soldiers took an Oath, <hi>to be true to their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, to live and dye with him;</hi> and that Oath was called, <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum militare,</hi> Rivet, Horace. Now when the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire turned <hi>Chriſtians</hi> by the lump, and painted themſelves with the Form of Godlineſs, few beautified with the Power and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue thereof, they began to apply the Term of their <hi>Heathen</hi> Cuſtom to the Signs or Shadow of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, ſo that the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> came from the <hi>Heathen Romans,</hi> Leigh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> is ſaid to be the firſt who uſed the word <hi>Sacrament,</hi> in order to the Signs or Figures of the Church, who was about the year 210.</p>
                  <p>It is a word not found in the Scriptures, if truly tranſlated, yet it hath got ſuch rooting among the Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as that if any deny it, they are branded as Hereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks by <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> Now, as it were to allure peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into a Reverence and Veneration of it, <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, have put it in the Body of the Scripture; for, whereas <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>This is a great Myſtery, but I speak concerning Chriſt and the Church,</hi> Epheſ. 5.32. their Tranſlations render it, <hi>This is a great Sacrament.</hi> But true it is, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation is true herein, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Tranſlation is faulty; and their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>ſeven Sacraments</hi> they have from <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> they are not mentioned in any Scripture, but firſt deviſed by <hi>Peter Lombard, Bellarmine</hi>'s Maſter, firſt decreed by <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, firſt confirmed in the Provincial Council of <hi>Senes,</hi> after in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> Leigh, Chamier de luc. lib. 4. cap. 1. And our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlations have the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the tenth Chapter of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> but the Diviſion of the Scripture into Chapter and Verſe is not from the Authors thereof, but of late time; as alſo, the inſerting in of the Contents, many <hi>Almanacks</hi> inform us of the Authors hereof.</p>
                  <p>Now as for the word <hi>Euchariſt; Luke</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the Inſtitution, mention, how <hi>Jeſus Chriſt took Bread, and</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Euchariſteſas,</hi> that is, <hi>giving Thanks:</hi> Now from the <hi>Greek</hi> word
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:104215:54"/>
                     <hi>Euchariſteſas,</hi> the <hi>Sacrament</hi> (ſo called) came alſo to be called <hi>Euchariſt:</hi> and after Chriſt had taken the Cup, and given thanks, and given it unto his Diſciples, after this Conſecration, as 'tis called, Chriſt called it the <hi>Fruit of the Vine;</hi> now if the Wine had been really tranſmuted, changed into the Blood of Chriſt, then it had not been the Fruit of the Vine; but ſaith he, <hi>I will not drink henceforth of the Fruit of the Vine, until that day, when I drink it new with you in my Father's Kingdom,</hi> Matth. 26. <hi>Peter</hi> preaching Chriſt to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> ſaid, <hi>That they did Eat and Drink with Chriſt after he roſe from the Dead,</hi> Acts 10.</p>
                  <p>This Teſtimony I have given concerning Bread and Wine, which <hi>Tertullian, Origen, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Jerom, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, Baſil</hi> and many others call Figures, Types, Shadows, &amp;c. though their Writings be very uncertain; and my Teſtimony is, That Chriſt is the End of all Figures, Types and Shadows, as before; true Union, Communion and Soul-feeding is in the Light of the living God, in Chriſt, whoſe Life is the Light of Men, the Soul's Food. Now, in citing the Teſtimonies of men who were ſince the primitive Times, I do it not to build mens Faith, or my own, on the Authorities of Men, but for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of ſuch who plead, <hi>that ancient Writers are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous, yea, and Harmonious in defending ſuch and ſuch things:</hi> and who turn from divine Grace manifeſted, ſuch know not the Mouth nor the Stomach, which feeds upon Heavenly Food, Bread of Life, the Word that became Fleſh, ſuch diſcern not the Lord's Body; but cleaving to that which is earthly, are carnallized thereby, made earthly-minded, labouring for the Meat that periſheth, and drink not the Cup of Bleſſing, but become drunk with the Cup of Fornication, from the Preſence of the Lamb.</p>
                  <p>Now, to what hath been ſpoken, I further add, That the <hi>Jews</hi> Paſſover, with its Appurtenances, was ended and fulfilled by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; Chriſt wa circumciſed; he taught in the Temple; he ſaid to the cleanſed Leper, <hi>Shew thy ſelf to the Prieſt, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a Gift according to the Law;</hi> thus Chriſt, the Subſtance, the End of the Law, the End of the Shadows, owned them in their
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:104215:54"/>ſeaſon, before he was offered up, or the Hand-writing nailed to the Croſs; and as Chriſt owned other Shadows in their ſeaſon, before he was offered up, ſo he owned the Paſſover, in which the <hi>Jews</hi> had their Bread and Wine, bleſſed and conſecrated it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame to be a Shadow, ſo by Chriſt fulfilled and ended.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>Jews</hi> in eating the Paſcal Lamb, took a Cup of Wine, bleſſed and conſecrated it, ſo it paſſed round the Table; this was called [Bircath-hajajin] <hi>the Bleſſing of the Cup;</hi> in this manner Chriſt began his Supper, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.17, 18.</item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>Jews</hi> in eating their Paſcal Lamb, took Break, bleſſed and conſecrated it, and after conſecration all were to eat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; this conſecration of the Bread they called [Bircath halechem] <hi>the Bleſſing of Bread;</hi> thus Chriſt took Bread, bleſſed it, and gave it to his Diſciples.</item>
                     <item>3. The <hi>Jews</hi> at the end of their Paſſover took a Cup of Wine, and bleſſed it, and called it [Bircath hamazon] ſo after the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Chriſt took the Cup, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.20. this ſaith <hi>Godwyn</hi> in his <hi>Iewiſh Antiquities.</hi> Thus Chriſt, the End of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Shadows, the Life and Subſtance they pointed at, owned the Shadows be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was offered up; but being returned in Spirit, the End of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Paſſover, Bread and Wine, was manifeſted; and the Apoſtle preached Chriſt to be their Paſſover, the Bread of Life, Cup of Bleſſings, the End of <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Figures.</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
